<problem>
	<question>1. Which of the following is a key characteristic of the Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS)? The GIPS  standards:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">rely on the integrity of input data. </choice>
		<choice id="B">address every aspect of performance measurement. </choice>
		<choice id="C">consist of required provisions for firms to follow to achieve best practice. </choice>
		<choice id="D">must be applied with the goal of achieving excellence in performance presentation. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS) 2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 127-128 Study Session 1-4-a  describe the key characteristics of the GIPS standards and the fundamentals of compliance A key characteristic of the  Standards is that the Standards rely on the integrity of input data. The accuracy of input data is critical to the accuracy of  the performance presentation.  </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>2. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, a member who is an investment manager is most likely to breach his  duty to clients by:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">disclosing potential conflicts of interest. </choice>
		<choice id="B">habitually voting with management on proxies that relate to non-routine governance issues.  </choice>
		<choice id="C">disclosing confidential client information to the CFA Institute Professional Conduct Program.  </choice>
		<choice id="D">using client brokerage to purchase goods or services that are used in the investment decision-making process. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook 2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 50 Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code  and Standards to specifi c situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct A fi duciary who  votes blindly with management on non-routine governance issues may breach their duty to clients by violating the  standard that relates to loyalty, prudence, and care.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>3. Carla Scott, CFA, is a portfolio manager for a company that manages investment accounts for wealthy individuals.  Scott has no beneficial interest in any of the fee-paying accounts she manages, including her uncle's account. When  shares in initial public offerings (IPOs) become available, Scott first allocates shares to all her other clients for whom  the investment is appropriate; only if shares are still available does she purchase shares in her uncle's account, if the  issue is appropriate for him. Scott provides each of her clients with full disclosure of her allocation procedures and has  received each client's verbal consent to her allocation procedures. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook,  does Scott's method of allocating oversubscribed IPOs violate any CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, because she has breached her duty to her uncle. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, because she has failed to obtain written consent with respect to her allocation procedures.  </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, because her allocation procedures contribute to market manipulation of initial public offerings.  </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook 2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 50-55, 94-95, 98,  Example 3 Study Session 1-2-a demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional  Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to specifi c situations presenting multiple issues of questionable  professional conduct B is correct because Scott's method of allocating oversubscribed IPOs discriminates against her  uncle, who is a fee-paying client; she violates the Standard related to Fair Dealing. Family accounts that are fee-paying  client accounts should be treated like any other fi rm account. They should neither receive special treatment nor be  disadvantaged because of an existing family relationship.       </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>4. Kim Li, CFA, is a portfolio manager for an investment advisory firm. Li delegates some of her supervisory duties to  Janet Marshall, CFA, after educating Marshall on methods to prevent and detect violations of the firm's compliance  procedures. Despite these efforts, Li discovers that an employee reporting to Marshall may have violated the law.  According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, Li's initial course of action must be to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">suspend the employee. </choice>
		<choice id="B">suspend Marshall from her supervisory duties. </choice>
		<choice id="C">initiate an investigation to determine the extent of the wrongdoing. </choice>
		<choice id="D">demand that the employee involved provide assurances that the activity will not be repeated. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook 2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 76-79 Study Session  1-2-a demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the  Code and Standards to specifi c situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct A supervisor  may delegate supervisory responsibilities, but such delegation does not relieve them of their supervisory responsibility; Li  must immediately begin an investigation of the matter to ascertain the extent of the wrongdoing. Relying on assurances  from the employee or simply reporting the misconduct up the chain of command are not enough.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>5. Marcus Takeda, CFA, is an analyst at a small investment advisory firm. His firm routinely purchases third-party  research that Takeda has found to be sound and reliable. Takeda drafts a research report recommending the purchase of  Crozet Corporation common stock to clients for whom the investment is suitable. The report contains financial  projections from third-party research providers referenced by Takeda. Takeda writes, "This recommendation is based  on expectations for continued strong demand for Crozet's products." Finally, Takeda notes at the end of the report that  he owns Crozet Corporation convertible bonds. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, has Takeda violated  the CFA Institute Standard of Professional Conduct relating to:    reasonable basis? independence and objectivity? 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No No </choice>
		<choice id="B">No Yes </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes No </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes Yes  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. I, pp. 21-23, 29-31, 80-82  Study Session 1-2-b  distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code  and the Standards  Takeda may rely on and issue reports based on third-party research providers if he has no reason to  question the soundness or reliability of their research and he appropriately references his sources. He also  appropriately discloses his interest in the company. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>6. David Gunard, CFA, is an equity analyst at Curry Securities. He receives an assignment to analyze Enterloch  Corporation, a stock owned by several of Curry's clients. Gunard completes a thorough, fundamental analysis of  Enterloch. Given his analysis and the sharp rise in the company's stock price during the past year, Gunard concludes  that the shares are substantially overvalued. After the report is approved by Gunard's supervisor, but prior to the release  of the report, Gunard calls his father to suggest that he sell his Enterloch shares immediately. Gunard's father informs  him that he has already disposed of his holdings in Enterloch. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, has  Gunard violated the CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct relating to:    duties to clients? reasonable basis? 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No No </choice>
		<choice id="B">No Yes </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes No </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes Yes  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D.  </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 48-51, 53-58, 80-82  Study Session 1-2-b  distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code  and the Standards  By communicating this information to his father prior to release of the report, Gunard failed to put the  firm's clients' interests above his own. Nothing in the question indicates that he did not have a reasonable  basis for his recommendation; he conducted a thorough fundamental analysis and his report was approved.  The fact that Gunard's father had already disposed of the shares does not negate the fact that Gunard  violated a duty to the firm's clients.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>7. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, may a member who inadvertently learns about an unannounced  tender offer:      trade on the  information?  cause others to  trade on the  information? 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No No </choice>
		<choice id="B">No Yes </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes No </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes Yes  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 36-39  Study Sessions 1-1-c, 1-2-b   explain the ethical responsibilities required by the Code and Standards, including the multiple subsections  of each Standard;  distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code  and the Standards  A member in possession of material nonpublic information that could affect the value of an investment  may not act or cause others to act on the information.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>8. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, do candidates violate the CFA Institute Standards of Professional  Conduct by cheating on:    the CFA examination? any other examination? 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No No </choice>
		<choice id="B">No Yes </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes No </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes Yes  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 101  Study Sessions 1-1-c, 1-2-b  explain the ethical responsibilities required by the Code and Standards, including the multiple subsections  of each Standard;  distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code  and the Standards  Conduct covered and prohibited under Standard VII (A) includes cheating on the CFA examination or any  other examination.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>9. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, a member who copies employer records in violation of the  employer's policies may violate CFA Institute Standards unless the member's clear intent is to protect:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">clients. </choice>
		<choice id="B">colleagues. </choice>
		<choice id="C">his reputation. </choice>
		<choice id="D">the employer's reputation. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 71  Study Sessions 1-1-c, 1-2-b   explain the ethical responsibilities required by the Code and Standards, including the multiple subsections  of each Standard;  distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code  and the Standards  Activities that would normally violate a member's duty to his employer (such as copying employer  records) may be justified. Such action would be permitted only if the intent is clearly aimed at protecting  clients or the integrity of the market and not for personal gain.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>10. Buta Singh, CFA, has a large extended family and manages the portfolios of several family members. Singh does not  charge the family members a management fee, but receives a small percentage of each portfolio's profits. Singh accepts  a position as portfolio manager for Bhotmange Investments to manage high net worth accounts. Because the family  portfolios are not normal client relationships, Singh does not inform his new employer of his side activity. With respect  to the family portfolios, does Singh violate any CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, because he failed to obtain consent from his employer. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, because he failed to disclose his new employment to his existing clients. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, because he violated his duty to his employer by not requiring his relatives to transfer their accounts to his new  employer. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 83-85, 91  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 69-71, 75  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by  applying the Code and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable  professional conduct  Members who plan to engage in independent practice for compensation should not render services until  receiving written consent from their employer. </comments>
</problem>



<problem>
	<question>11. Meryl Mamet, CFA, manages an emerging markets fund which has generated annual returns of 30% for the past three  years. Mamet distributes a marketing brochure which includes the following statement "My investment expertise has  generated annual returns of 30% for the past three years and you can expect a similar rate of growth over the next two  years." Does Mamet violate any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, because the performance should be stated net of fees. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, because the returns must include terminated accounts. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, because the presentation makes assurances regarding investment performance. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 75-76  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 64-65  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by  applying the Code and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable  professional conduct  Members must not knowingly make statements of assurances or guarantees regarding an investment.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>12. Crandall Temasek, CFA, filed for personal bankruptcy two years ago after incurring large medical expenses. He was  hired recently as a portfolio manager. According to the CFA Institute Standards, must Temasek disclose his bankruptcy  filing to his new employer?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, because he has a duty of loyalty to his employer. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, because bankruptcy represents a potential conflict of interest. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, because bankruptcy reflects poorly on his conduct and character. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), p. 33  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 35  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by  applying the Code and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable  professional conduct  Members who are involved in a personal bankruptcy filing are not automatically assumed to be in  violation of the standards because bankruptcy may not reflect poorly on the integrity or trustworthiness of  the person involved.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>13. Sallie Lewis, CFA, is a research analyst covering the mining industry. Along with other analysts, Lewis visits the  primary mine of Gold Rush Mines (GR). During the visit, a major piece of equipment fails and Lewis overhears an  unidentified employee state that production will be stalled for six months. Lewis immediately files a sell  recommendation on GR without any additional research. Has Lewis violated any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to client confidentiality. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to diligence and reasonable basis. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to material nonpublic information. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 37-40  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 36-39  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by  applying the Code and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable  professional conduct  Lewis must investigate the reliability of the information before making an investment recommendation  based on the information.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>14. Clive Bowers, CFA, is a portfolio manager at Burlington Advisors (BA). Bowers manages two mutual funds along  with a number of individual accounts. All of the portfolios, including the mutual funds, have similar return objectives,  risk tolerances, and tax constraints. When Bowers allocates shares from block trades he fills the mutual fund orders  first and then allocates the remaining shares to the individual accounts based on their portfolio size. When allocating  shares from block trades, does Bowers violate any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to suitability. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to fair dealing. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to priority of transaction. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 61-63  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 53-55  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by  applying the Code and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable  professional conduct  Members must deal fairly and objectively with clients when taking investment actions for them. By  treating the mutual funds more favorably than the individual portfolios, Owens violates the standard  relating to fair dealing.  </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>15. Narupa Rhasta, CFA, is manager of the fast-growing individual account division of a bank and treats all clients  equally. When the bank's research department issues a buy or sell recommendation on a security, she ensures that the  recommended action is implemented in all accounts. Do Rhasta's investment actions violate any CFA Institute  Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to suitability. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to fair dealing. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to diligence and a reasonable basis. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 69-71  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 60-62   Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by  applying the Code and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable  professional conduct  Members must consider the needs, circumstances and objectives of clients when taking investment action  for their accounts. By treating all accounts as if they were the same, Rhasta failed to consider the  uniqueness of each client's circumstances.  </comments>
</problem>

<problem>
	<question>16. Jimmy Lee, CFA, is an investment banker in a country with strict confidentiality laws. He is working on an  acquisition for Panda Mining Co. (PMC). While performing due diligence, Lee notices that PMC has a number of  questionable offshore partnerships. He investigates the legality of the partnerships and finds evidence of illegal activity.  According to the Standards of Professional Conduct, Lee's best course of action would be to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">tip the media. </choice>
		<choice id="B">alert CFA Institute. </choice>
		<choice id="C">consult outside counsel. </choice>
		<choice id="D">notify regulatory authorities. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 79-80  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 67-68  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code  and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  Members must keep client information confidential and must comply with applicable law. If applicable law requires  disclosure of client information in certain circumstances, members and candidates must comply with the law. If  applicable law requires members to maintain confidentiality, even if the information concerns illegal activities on the part  of the client, members should not disclose such information. Lee's best course of action would be to consult with outside  counsel to determine applicable law.  </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>17. Rene Whatcom, CFA, is an independent contractor who writes research reports for several investment publications.  Whatcom refuses to sign contracts with exclusivity clauses. Whatcom sometimes revises work he submits to one  publication and sends slightly altered versions of the report to additional publications. Does Whatcom violate any CFA  Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to loyalty. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to disclosure of conflicts. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to additional compensation. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 83-85  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 69-71   Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code  and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  A member's duties within an independent contractor relationship are governed by the oral or written agreement between  the member and the client. Members should take care to define clearly the scope of the responsibilities and the  expectations of each client within the context of each relationship. Members have a duty to abide by the terms of the  agreement. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>18. Angus Draper, CFA, is a senior portfolio manager and member of the investment committee at Tillahook Investments.  Draper serves as a board member for several non-profit organizations. These commitments require eight workdays per  month of Draper's time. Because he does not receive any form of compensation for these activities, Draper does not tell  anyone at work about his board activities. Does Draper violate any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to conflict of interest. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to additional compensation. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to responsibilities of supervisors. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp 83-85, 113-115  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 69-71, 89-91  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code  and Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  Members must make full and fair disclosure of all matters that could reasonably be expected to impair their independence  and objectivity or interfere with respective duties. Draper should discuss his outside activities with his employer and  come to mutual agreement regarding how to manage his personal commitments with his responsibilities to his employer.  </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>19. The yield to maturity on otherwise identical option-free bonds issued by the U.S. Treasury and General Motors is 6%  and 8%, respectively. If annual inflation is expected to remain steady at 2.5% over the life of the bonds, the most likely  explanation for the difference in yields is:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">liquidity. </choice>
		<choice id="B">maturity. </choice>
		<choice id="C">default risk. </choice>
		<choice id="D">business risk. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"The Time Value of Money," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.  Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 172-174  Study Session 2-5-b  explain an interest rate as the sum of a real risk-free rate, expected inflation, and premiums that  compensate investors for distinct types of risk  The difference in yield on otherwise identical U.S Treasury and corporate bonds is attributed to default  risk. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>20. Rachel Kelly, age 24, is planning for retirement. Kelly's annual consumption expenditures are currently $30,000. She  assumes her consumption expenditures will increase with the rate of inflation, which she expects to average 3% until she  retires at age 68. Given a life expectancy of 83 years and constant expenditures in retirement, the amount Kelly must  accumulate by her retirement date, assuming an 8% rate of return on her retirement account, is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$320,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$423,000. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$1,176,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$1,552,000. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"The Time Value of Money," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 190-208  Study Session 2-5-d, e  calculate and interpret the future value (FV) and present value (PV) of a single sum of money, an ordinary annuity, an  annuity due, a perpetuity (PV only), and a series of unequal cash flows;  draw a time line, specify a time index, and solve time value of money applications (for example, mortgages and savings  for college tuition or retirement)  Kelly expects her consumption spending (currently $30,000 annually) to increase with the rate of inflation (3%) over the  next 44 years until she retires. Her annual consumption spending at the time she retires will be $110,143.57 (PV = 30,000,  %I = 3, N = 44, solve for FV). To support that level of spending for 25 years of retirement, assuming an 8% return on her  retirement account, she must accumulate $1,175,756 by her retirement date (PMT = 110,143.57, N = 25, %I = 8, solve for  PV). </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>21. An analyst gathered the following information about a capital investment's cash flows:  Time Cash Flow  0 ($500,000)  1 $100,000  2 $200,000  3 $100,000  4 $300,000                  If the risk-free interest rate is 6%, expected inflation is 3%, and the opportunity cost of capital is 12%, the investment's  net present value (NPV) is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">($24,537.) </choice>
		<choice id="B">$10,558. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$49,825. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$93,929. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Discounted Cash Flow Applications," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and  David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 214-216  Study Session 2-6-a  calculate and interpret the net present value (NPV) and the internal rate of return (IRR) of an investment,  contrast the NPV rule to the IRR rule, and identify problems associated with the IRR rule  The NPV equals the present value (at time = 0) of the future cash flows discounted at the opportunity cost  of capital (12%) minus the initial investment, or $10,558 (CF0 = -500,000, CF1 = 100,000, CF2 = 200,000,  CF3 = 100,000, CF4 = 300,000, I = 12, solve for NPV = 10,557.94 ? 10,558). </comments>
</problem>

<problem>
	<question>22. An analyst gathered the following information about a common stock investment:    Date Amount  Stock purchase 15 January 2007 EUR48.00  Cash dividend 14 July 2007 EUR4.00  Stock sale 15 July 2007 EUR54.00                The holding period return on the common stock investment is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">12.5%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">20.8%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">25.0%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">41.7%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Discounted Cash Flow Applications," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 221-222  Study Session 2-6-b  define, calculate, and interpret a holding period return (total return)  The holding period return (HPR) is calculated as follows:  HPR = (P1 - P0 + D1) / P0, where P0 is the initial investment, P1 is the price received at the end of the holding period,  and D1 is the cash paid by the investment at the end of the holding period. In this case: HPR = (54 - 48 + 4) / 48 = 20.8%.  The HPR is not annualized for holding periods shorter than a year. </comments>
</problem>

<problem>
	<question>23. A 270-day U.S. Treasury bill with a face value of $100,000 sells for $96,500 when issued. Assuming an investor  holds the bill to maturity, the investor's money market yield and effective annual yield, respectively, are closest to:    Money market yield Effective annual yield  A 4.667% 4.903%  B 4.667% 4.934%  C 4.836% 4.903%  D 4.836% 4.934%                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Discounted Cash Flow Applications," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and  David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 229-233  Study Session 2-6-d  calculate and interpret the bank discount yield, holding period yield, effective annual yield, and money  market yield for a U.S. Treasury bill; and convert among holding period yields, money market yields,  effective annual yields, and bond equivalent yields  The money market yield is computed by annualizing the holding period yield (HPY) assuming a 360-day  year. In this case, the HPY is (100,000 - 96,500) / 96,500 = 3.627% and the money market yield = 3.627%  x (360 / 270) = 4.836%.  The effective annual yield (EAY) compounds the HYP forward to one year (assuming a 365-day year). In  this case, the EAY = (1 + 0.03627)365 / 270 - 1 = 4.934%. </comments>
</problem>

<problem>
	<question>24. An analyst gathered the following information about the price-earnings (P/E) ratios for the common stocks held in a  foundation's portfolio:    Interval P/E range Frequency  I 8.00 - 16.00 24  II 16.00 - 24.00 48  III 24.00 - 30.00 22  IV 30.00 - 38.00 16        The relative frequency and the cumulative relative frequency, respectively, for Interval III are closest to:    Relative frequency Cumulative relative frequency  A 20% 36%  B 20% 85%  C 22% 36%  D 22% 85%                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Statistical Concepts and Market Returns," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto,  and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 243-250  Study Session 2-7-c  calculate and interpret relative frequencies and cumulative relative frequencies, given a frequency  distribution, and describe the properties of a dataset presented as a histogram or a frequency polygon  The relative frequency is the number of observations in an interval divided by the total number of  observations. For Interval III, relative frequency = 22 / 110 = 20%.  The cumulative relative frequency is the sum of the relative frequencies of the relevant class and all the  classes before it. For Interval III, the cumulative relative frequency = (24 + 48 + 22) / 110 = 85.45% ?  85%. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>25. An analyst gathered the following annual return information about a portfolio since its inception on 1 January 2003:    Year Portfolio return  2003 8.6%  2004 11.2%  2005 12.9%  2006 15.1%  2007 -9.4%          The portfolio's mean absolute deviation and variance of annual returns, respectively, for the five-year period are closest  to:    Mean absolute deviation Variance 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">6.83% 77.5 </choice>
		<choice id="B">6.83% 96.8 </choice>
		<choice id="C">7.68% 77.5 </choice>
		<choice id="D">7.68% 96.8                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Statistical Concepts and Market Returns," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.  Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 279-284  Study Session 2-7-f  define, calculate, and interpret 1) a range and a mean absolute deviation, and 2 ) the variance and standard deviation of a  population and of a sample  First, compute the mean portfolio return = (8.6 + 11.2 + 12.9 + 15.1 - 9.4) / 5 = 7.68%  Mean absolute deviation = (|8.6 - 7.68| + |11.2 - 7.68| + |12.9 - 7.68| + |15.1 - 7.68| + |-9.4 - 7.68|) / 5 = 6.83%  Variance = [(8.6 - 7.68)2 + (11.2 - 7.68)2 + (12.9 - 7.68)2 + (15.1 - 7.68)2 + (-9.4 - 7.68)2 / 5 = 77.4536 ? 77.5  The population variance calculation is appropriate because the analyst is analyzing all the annual returns on the portfolio  since its inception. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>26. An analyst gathered the following information about a common stock portfolio:  Arithmetic mean return 14.3%  Geometric mean return 12.7%  Variance of returns 380  Portfolio beta 1.35         If the risk-free rate of return is 4.25%, then the  coefficient of variation and the Sharpe ratio, respectively, for the portfolio are closest to:     Coefficient of  variation  Sharpe ratio 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">1.36 0.52 </choice>
		<choice id="B">1.36 7.44 </choice>
		<choice id="C">1.53 0.52 </choice>
		<choice id="D">1.53 7.44                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Statistical Concepts and Market Returns," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.  Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 291-297  Study Session 2-7-h  define, calculate, and interpret the coefficient of variation and the Sharpe ratio   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>27. If an analyst estimates the probability of an event for which there is no historical record, this probability is best  described as:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">a priori. </choice>
		<choice id="B">objective. </choice>
		<choice id="C">empirical. </choice>
		<choice id="D">subjective. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Probability Concepts," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 319-320  Study Session 2-8-b  explain the two defining properties of probability, and distinguish among empirical, subjective, and a priori probabilities  An empirical probability cannot be calculated for an event not in the historical record. In this case, the analyst can make a  personal assessment of the probability of the event without reference to any particular data. This is a subjective  probability. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>28. Which of the following statements regarding correlation and covariance is most likely correct? The correlation  between two random variables is their covariance standardized by the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">product of the variables' variances. </choice>
		<choice id="B">variance of the dependent variable. </choice>
		<choice id="C">variance of the independent variable. </choice>
		<choice id="D">product of the variables' standard deviations. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Probability Concepts," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 342-347  Study Session 2-8-j  calculate and interpret covariance and correlation  The correlation between two random variables is equal to the covariance between the variables divided by the product of  the variables' standard deviations. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>29. Which of the following best describes the discrete uniform distribution? The discrete uniform distribution:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">has a finite number of specified outcomes. </choice>
		<choice id="B">is based on the Bernoulli random variable. </choice>
		<choice id="C">is approximated by the log-normal distribution. </choice>
		<choice id="D">has an infinite number of unspecified outcomes. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Common Probability Distributions," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 373-374  Study Session 2-9-d  define a discrete uniform random variable and a binomial random variable, calculate and interpret probabilities given the  discrete uniform and the binomial distribution functions, and construct a binomial tree to describe stock price movement  The discrete uniform distribution is known as the simplest of all probability distributions. It is made up of a finite number  of specified outcomes and each outcome is equally likely. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>30. An analyst determined that the sample mean and variance for a normal distribution are 42 and 9, respectively. The  99% confidence interval for this random variable is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">15.0 to 69.0. </choice>
		<choice id="B">18.8 to 65.2. </choice>
		<choice id="C">34.3 to 49.7. </choice>
		<choice id="D">39.0 to 45.0. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Common Probability Distributions," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 392-393  Study Session 2-9-g  construct and interpret a confidence interval for a normally distributed random variable, and determine the probability  that a normally distributed random variable lies inside a given confidence interval  The 99% confidence interval for a normally distributed random variable is equal to the sample mean +- 2.58 x sample  standard deviation. In this case, the 99% confidence interval = 42 +- (2.58 x 90.5) = 42 +- (2.58 x 3) = 42 +- 7.74 ? 34.3 to  49.7. </comments>
</problem>

<problem>
	<question>31. According to the central limit theorem, a sampling distribution of the sample mean will be approximately normal only  if the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">sample size n is large. </choice>
		<choice id="B">underlying distribution is normally distributed. </choice>
		<choice id="C">variance of the underlying distribution is known. </choice>
		<choice id="D">population mean of the underlying distribution is known. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Sampling and Estimation," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 428-429  Study Session 2-10-d  interpret the central limit theorem and describe its importance  According to the central limit theorem, the sample mean of a population described by any probability distribution can be  determined if the sample size n is sufficiently large, e.g., equal to or greater than 30. This process is used to estimate the  population mean and standard deviation, which usually are unknown. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>32. Which of the following is NOT a desirable property of an estimator?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Efficiency. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Reliability. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Consistency. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Unbiasedness. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Sampling and Estimation," Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 432-433  Study Session 2-10-g  identify and describe the desirable properties of an estimator  The three desirable properties of an estimator are unbiasedness, efficiency, and consistency. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>33. The nature of competitive environment to which the game of Prisoners' Dilemma applies and the solution offered by  Nash equilibrium, respectively, are:    Nature of competitive environment Solution from Nash equilibrium 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">oligopoly both prisoners deny </choice>
		<choice id="B">oligopoly both prisoners confess </choice>
		<choice id="C">monopolistic competition both prisoners deny </choice>
		<choice id="D">monopolistic competition both prisoners confess                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Monopolistic Competition and Oligopoly," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 225-228  Study Session 5-20-a, d  describe the characteristics of monopolistic competition and oligopoly;  explain the kinked demand curve model and the dominant firm model, and describe oligopoly games  including the Prisoners' Dilemma  The game of Prisoners' Dilemma applies to oligopoly and the solution from Nash equilibrium is that both  prisoners would confess to the crime.  </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>34. The tax division between buyers and sellers with respect to products with perfectly elastic and perfectly inelastic  demand, respectively, are:    Perfectly elastic demand Perfectly inelastic demand 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">buyers pay the entire tax. buyers pay the entire tax. </choice>
		<choice id="B">buyers pay the entire tax. sellers pay the entire tax. </choice>
		<choice id="C">sellers pay the entire tax. buyers pay the entire tax. </choice>
		<choice id="D">sellers pay the entire tax. sellers pay the entire tax.                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Markets in Action," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 74-75  Study Session 4-15-c  explain the impact of taxes on supply, demand, and market equilibrium, and describe tax incidence and its  relation to demand and supply elasticity  In the extreme cases of products with perfectly elastic and perfectly inelastic demand, the sellers and  buyers, respectively, pay the entire tax. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>35. Venkat Reddy is very fond of mango fruits. If mangoes cost 10 rupees each, Reddy spends his budget on fruits that he  values more highly than mangoes. However, at 4 rupees each Reddy buys 20 mangoes for devouring over a one-week  period. The total consumer surplus in rupees for Venkat would be closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">13. </choice>
		<choice id="B">26. </choice>
		<choice id="C">60. </choice>
		<choice id="D">120. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Efficiency and Equity," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 38-41  Study Session 4-14-b  distinguish between the price and the value of a product and explain the demand curve and consumer surplus  The consumer surplus is the value of the good minus the price paid for it (10-4) = 6, summed over the quantity bought.  The total consumer surplus is the consumer surplus on each mango that Reddy buys and added together. It is the area of  the right triangle = (base x height) / 2 as in Figure 3 on p. 40, with base equal to 20 mangoes a week and the height equal  to 6, the consumer surplus on each mango. Thus the total consumer surplus = (20 x 6) / 2 = Rs.60 (see example on p. 41). </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>36.  The Laffer curve depicts a relationship between which of the following sets of two economic variables and its  proponents belong to which group of economists?    Two economic variables Proponents belong to 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Tax rate and tax revenues Monetarists </choice>
		<choice id="B">Tax rate and tax revenues Supply-siders </choice>
		<choice id="C">Inflation and unemployment Monetarists </choice>
		<choice id="D">Inflation and unemployment Supply-siders                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Fiscal Policy," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 439-440  Study Session 6-27-a  explain supply-side effects on employment, potential GDP, and aggregate supply, including the income tax and taxes on  expenditure, and describe the Laffer curve and its relation to supply-side economics  The relationship between the tax rate and the amount of tax revenue collected is called the Laffer curve, named after  Arthur B. Laffer, a supply-side economist and a member of President Reagan's economic policy advisory board. They  argued that tax cuts would increase tax revenues and decrease the budget deficit. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>37. Choice Malts Breweries has compiled the following information in order to determine its economic profit for the  year:  Total revenue $300,000  Value of buildings and machinery         - At the beginning of the year $300,000       - At the end of the year $280,000  Cost of raw materials $100,000  Wages paid during the year $ 50,000  Normal profit for the year $ 40,000                      What is the economic profit of Choice Malts Breweries closest to?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$90,000 </choice>
		<choice id="B">$110,000 </choice>
		<choice id="C">$130,000 </choice>
		<choice id="D">$150,000 </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Organizing Production," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 92-95  Study Session 4-16-a  explain the types of opportunity cost and their relation to economic profit, and calculate economic profit   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>38. Which of the following provides the best description of the effect of subsidies on the prices of goods and the  relationship between marginal cost and marginal benefit?    Effect on prices  Relationship between marginal cost  and marginal benefit 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Price falls Marginal benefit exceeds marginal cost </choice>
		<choice id="B">Price falls Marginal cost exceeds marginal benefit </choice>
		<choice id="C">Price increases Marginal benefit exceeds marginal cost </choice>
		<choice id="D">Price increases Marginal cost exceeds marginal benefit                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>is</answer>
	<comments>"Markets in Action," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 79-80  Study Session 4-15-d  discuss the impact of subsidies, quotas, and markets for illegal goods on demand, supply, and market equilibrium  Upon introduction of a subsidy, the equilibrium level of supply increases and the price falls. In the new equilibrium,  marginal cost (on the supply curve) exceeds marginal benefit (on the demand curve) and a deadweight loss arises due to  overproduction (Figure 13 on p. 79). </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>39. The Okun gap and the inflationary gap, respectively, occur under which of the following economic conditions?    Okun gap Inflationary gap 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Below full-employment equilibrium Below full-employment equilibrium </choice>
		<choice id="B">Below full-employment equilibrium Above full-employment equilibrium </choice>
		<choice id="C">Above full-employment equilibrium Below full-employment equilibrium </choice>
		<choice id="D">Above full-employment equilibrium Above full-employment equilibrium                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Aggregate Demand and Aggregate Supply," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 327-328  Study Session 5-23-c  differentiate between short-run and long-run macroeconomic equilibrium, and explain how economic growth, inflation,  and changes in aggregate demand and supply influence the macroeconomic equilibrium and the business cycle  A below full-employment equilibrium is a macro-economic equilibrium in which potential GDP exceeds real GDP. The  amount by which potential GDP exceeds real GDP is called the Okun gap. An above full-employment equilibrium is a  macro-economic equilibrium in which real GDP exceeds potential GDP. The amount by which real GDP exceeds  potential GDP is called an inflationary gap.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>40. In response to the influx of tourists, the demand for guest rooms in Sun-n-Surf, a resort hotel on a south pacific island,  went up from 100 to 150 rooms. As a result, Sun-n-Surf management has decided to increase the tariff from $150 to  $200 a night per room. The elasticity of supply of rooms in Sun-n-Surf is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">0.67. </choice>
		<choice id="B">0.72. </choice>
		<choice id="C">1.40. </choice>
		<choice id="D">1.50. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Elasticity," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 24-25  Study Session 4-13-a  calculate and interpret the elasticities of demand (price elasticity, cross elasticity, income elasticity) and the elasticity of  supply, and discuss the factors that influence each measure  The elasticity of supply equals the percent change in quantity relative to the average quantity divided by the percent  change in demand relative to the average demand:  The average quantity = (100 + 150) / 2 = 125, the % change in quantity = 50 / 125 = 40;   The average price = (150 + 200) / 2 = 175, the % change in price = 50 / 175 = 28.6  Elasticity of supply = 40 / 28.6 = 1.40 </comments>
</problem>

<problem>
	<question>41. Budget type  Impact on  private saving  A deficit budget increase  B deficit budget decrease  C surplus budget increase  D surplus budget decrease  The type of government budget that leads to crowding-out, and its impact on private saving, respectively, are:    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Fiscal Policy," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 444-445  Study Session 6-27-b  discuss the sources of investment finance and the influence of fiscal policy on capital markets, including the  crowding-out effect  A deficit budget leads to an increase in interest rates, a decrease in investment, and an increase in private saving.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>42. The type of natural resource market to which the Hotelling principle applies, and the relationship expressed in it,  respectively, are:     Type of natural  resource market  Relationship expressed in the Hotelling principle  A renewable the price of the resource rises at a rate equal to the interest rate  B renewable the price of the resource rises at a rate equal to the inflation rate C non-renewable the price of the resource rises at a rate equal to the interest rate  D non-renewable the price of the resource rises at a rate equal to the inflation rate                   Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B</choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C</choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D</choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Demand and Supply in Factor Markets," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 271-274  Study Session 5-21-g  differentiate between renewable and non-renewable natural resources and describe the supply curve for each  The Hotelling principle applies to non-renewable natural resources characterized by perfectly elastic flow supply.  According to the Hotelling principle, the price of resource is expected to rise at a rate equal to the interest rate (p. 274).   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>43. The most accurate description of the effect of a price decrease on total revenue for goods that have an elastic and  inelastic demand, respectively, are:    Elastic demand Inelastic demand  A total revenue declines total revenue declines  B total revenue declines total revenue increases  C total revenue increases total revenue declines  D total revenue increases total revenue increases                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Elasticity," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 15-16  Study Session 4-13-b  calculate elasticities on a straight-line demand curve, differentiate among elastic, inelastic, and unit elastic demand and  describe the relation between price elasticity of demand and total revenue  When demand is elastic, a decrease in price by 1% increases the quantity sold by more than 1% and it results in an  increase in total revenue. But when demand is inelastic, a decrease in price by 1% increases the quantity sold by less than  1% and it results in a decrease in total revenue.     </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>44. The three indicators of the state of the labor market that the U.S. Census Bureau calculates include all of the  following, except:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">the unemployment rate. </choice>
		<choice id="B">the total labor compensation. </choice>
		<choice id="C">the labor force participation rate. </choice>
		<choice id="D">the employment-to-population ratio. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Monitoring Cycles, Jobs, and the Price Level," Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 288-289  Study Session 5-22-a  describe the phases of the business cycle, define an unemployed person, and interpret the main labor  market indicators and their relation to the business cycle  The three indicators of the state of the labor market that the U.S. Census Bureau calculates are:  the unemployment rate, the labor force participation rate, and the employment-to-population ratio.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>45. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.    A company's cash conversion cycle is most likely to decrease if that company experiences a(n):  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increase in the payables turnover ratio. </choice>
		<choice id="B">decrease in the inventory turnover ratio. </choice>
		<choice id="C">increase in the receivables turnover ratio. </choice>
		<choice id="D">decrease in the payables payment period. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Financial Analysis Techniques," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael  A. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 590-592  "Working Capital Management," Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 89-92  Study Session 10-41-d, 11-46-a  calculate and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios;  calculate and interpret liquidity measures using selected financial ratios for a company and compare it  with peer companies   An increase in receivables turnover would indicate that receivables were outstanding for a shorter period  of time, decreasing the cash conversion cycle.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>46. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst prepared common-size balance sheets for two companies operating in the same industry. The analyst            noted that both companies had the same proportion of current liabilities, long-term liabilities, and shareholders' equity,  and the following ratios:    Company 1 Company 2  Current ratio 2.0 2.0  Cash ratio 0.3 0.3  Quick ratio 0.5 0.8                The most reasonable conclusion is that, compared with Company 2, Company 1 had a:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">higher percentage of assets associated with inventory. </choice>
		<choice id="B">higher percentage of assets associated with accounts receivable. </choice>
		<choice id="C">lower percentage of assets associated with marketable securities. </choice>
		<choice id="D">higher percentage of assets associated with marketable securities. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Financial Analysis Techniques," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael  A. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 574-575, 590-592  "Working Capital Management," Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 89-90  Study Session 10-41-a, d, 11-46-a  evaluate and compare companies using ratio analysis, common-size financial statements, and charts in  financial analysis;  calculate and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios;  calculate and interpret liquidity measures using selected financial ratios for a company and compare it  with peer companies   The current ratio includes inventory but the quick ratio does not. (Current ratio is higher than quick ratio  and quick ratio is higher than cash ratio.) The quick ratio includes accounts receivable but the cash ratio  does not. The denominator for all three ratios is current liabilities, which are the same proportion for both  companies. The difference in ratios is therefore created by inventory and accounts receivable. Company 1  has the higher percentage of inventory because the difference between the current ratio and quick ratio is  greater for that company. Company 2 had the higher percentage of accounts receivable because the  difference between the quick ratio and the cash ratio is greater for Company 2.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>47. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following information for a company:  Ratios 2005 2004 2003  Inventory turnover  5 6 7  Total asset turnover 6 5 3  Accounts payable turnover 9 9 8  Accounts receivable turnover 11 12 15                    All other factors being equal, which of the following is the best conclusion with respect to the information above? From  2003 to 2005, the company's:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">fixed asset turnover increased. </choice>
		<choice id="B">credit policies became more strict. </choice>
		<choice id="C">cash conversion cycle became shorter. </choice>
		<choice id="D">average inventory processing time decreased. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Financial Analysis Techniques," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael  A. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 583-590  "Working Capital Management," Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 89-90  Study Sessions 10-41-d, 11-46-a  calculate and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios;  calculate and interpret liquidity measures using selected financial ratios for a company and compare it  with peer companies   Total asset turnover increased over the period, but turnovers related to the cash conversion cycle  decreased or remained relatively stable. The fixed asset turnover had to have increased to offset the  decline in inventory and accounts receivable turnovers.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>48. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  If a company has a current ratio of 2.0, that company's repayment of $150,000 in short-term borrowing obtained from a  bank would most likely decrease:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">the company's current ratio, but not the company's cash flow from operations. </choice>
		<choice id="B">the company's cash flow from operations, but not the company's current ratio. </choice>
		<choice id="C">both the company's current ratio and the company's cash flow from operations. </choice>
		<choice id="D">neither the company's current ratio nor the company's cash flow from operations. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Cash Flow Statement," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry,  and Michael A. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 251-252  "Financial Analysis Techniques," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael  A. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 591  Study Sessions 8-34-a, 10-41-d  compare and contrast cash flows from operating, investing, and financing activities, and classify cash flow  items as relating to one of these three categories, given a description of the items;  calculate and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios  The current ratio is above 1.0, so the payment of short-term borrowing would increase the current ratio; it  would reduce both the numerator and denominator by the same amount. The repayment of short-term debt  would reduce cash flow from financing, not cash flow from operations.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>49. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  At the end of the year, a company sold equipment for $30,000 cash. The company paid $110,000 for the equipment  several years ago and had accumulated depreciation of $70,000 for the equipment at the time of sale. All else equal, the  equipment sale will result in the company's cash flow from:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">investing activities decreasing by $10,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">investing activities increasing by $30,000. </choice>
		<choice id="C">operating activities being $10,000 less than net income. </choice>
		<choice id="D">operating activities being $30,000 more than net income. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Cash Flow Statement," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A.  Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 251-252, 271-272, 275-276  Study Session 8-34-a, f  compare and contrast cash flows from operating, investing, and financing activities, and classify cash flow items as  relating to one of these three categories, given a description of the items;  demonstrate the steps in the preparation of direct and indirect cash flow statements, including how cash flows can be  computed using income statement and balance sheet data  The book value of the equipment would have been $110,000 - $70,000 = $40,000 at the time of sale, so a loss of $10,000  for financial statement purposes would be realized. The net loss would reduce net income and would be adjusted in the  statement of cash flows by adding the net loss to net income. The total amount of the proceeds ($30,000) would be shown  as a cash inflow from investing activities.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>50. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  In 2007, a company reported net income of $130 million and cash flow from operations of $120 million. All else equal,  the most likely explanation for the difference between net income and cash flow from operations in 2007 is that the  company:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">tightened credit policies and increased collection efforts during the year. </choice>
		<choice id="B">purchased new property, plant, and equipment at the beginning of the year. </choice>
		<choice id="C">sold a long-term investment for an amount equal to book value at the end of the year. </choice>
		<choice id="D">increased raw materials inventory in anticipation of increased sales at the end of the year.  </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Cash Flow Statement," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A.  Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 267-271, 276-277  Study Session 8-34-h  analyze and interpret a cash flow statement using both total currency amounts and common-size cash flow statements   The increase in inventory (working capital investment) would reduce cash flow from operations relative to net income.  </comments>
</problem>

<problem>
	<question>51. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following annual information ($ millions) about a company that pays no dividends and has no  debt:                        Net income 45.8  Depreciation 18.2  Loss on sale of equipment 1.6  Decrease in accounts receivable 4.2  Increase in inventories 3.4  Increase in accounts payable 2.5  Capital expenditures 7.3  Proceeds from sale of stock 8.5    The company's annual free cash flow to equity ($ millions) is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">53.1. </choice>
		<choice id="B">58.4. </choice>
		<choice id="C">61.6. </choice>
		<choice id="D">64.0. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Cash Flow Statement," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A.  Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 275-278, 287-288  Study Session 8-34-i  explain and calculate free cash flow to the firm, free cash flow to equity, and other cash flow ratios  Free cash flow to equity in a company without any debt is equal to cash flow from operations (CFO) less capital  expenditures. CFO = net income + depreciation + loss on sale of equipment + decrease in accounts receivable - increase  in inventories + increase in accounts payable. (The loss on sale of equipment is added back when calculating CFO. It  would have been deducted in the calculation of net income but the loss is not the cash impact of the transaction (the  proceeds received, if any, would be the cash effect) and cash flows related to equipment transactions are investing  activities, not operating activities.)  CFO = 45.8 + 18.2 + 1.6 + 4.2 - 3.4 + 2.5 = $68.9 million  $68.9 - $7.3 = $61.6 million free cash flow to equity.  </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>52. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Which of the following statements best describes the level of accuracy provided by a standard audit report?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">There is full assurance that the financial statements are fairly presented. </choice>
		<choice id="B">There is reasonable assurance that the financial statements contain no errors. </choice>
		<choice id="C">There is full assurance that the financial statements are free of material errors. </choice>
		<choice id="D">There is reasonable assurance that the financial statements are fairly presented. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Financial Statement Analysis: An Introduction," Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and  Michael A. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 21  Study Session 7-29-d  discuss the objective of audits of financial statements, the types of audit reports, and the importance of effective internal  controls  Audits provide reasonable assurance that the financial statements are fairly presented, meaning that there is a high degree  of probability that they are free of material error, fraud or illegal acts. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>53. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Making any necessary adjustments to the financial statements to facilitate comparison with respect to accounting  choices is done in which step of the financial statement analysis framework?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Collect data </choice>
		<choice id="B">Process data </choice>
		<choice id="C">Analyze/interpret the processed data </choice>
		<choice id="D">Develop and communicate conclusions  </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Financial Statement Analysis: An Introduction," Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and  Michael A. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 26-30  Study Session 7-29-f  describe the steps in the financial statement analysis framework  Making any adjustments is part of the processing data step. Commonly used data bases (part of the collection phase) do  not make adjustments for differences in accounting choices. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>54. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  During 2007 Nagano Incorporated, a manufacturing company, reported the following items on their income statement:  Loss on disposal of fixed assets $50,000  Interest expense $62,500    The correct classification of each of these items on the income statement would be as a(n):                     Loss on disposal  of fixed assets  Interest expense 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">operating item operating item </choice>
		<choice id="B">operating item nonoperating item </choice>
		<choice id="C">nonoperating item operating item </choice>
		<choice id="D">nonoperating item nonoperating item    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Income Statement," Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A.  Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 169-171  Study Session 8-32-f  distinguish between the operating and nonoperating components of the income statement  The loss on the disposal of fixed assets is an unusual or infrequent item but it is still part of normal operating activities.  The interest expense is the result of financing activities and would be classified as a nonoperating expense by  nonfinancial service companies. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>55. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  The following information was available from the accounting records of a company as at December 31, 2007:  Accounts payable $20,000 Accounts receivable 82,000 Bank loan, due on demand 44,000 Cash 12,500 Income taxes payable 5,000 Inventory 47,400 Investments accounted for by the equity method 112,000 Loan payable, due June 30, 2009 50,000 Deposits from customers for deliveries in 2008 8,000                         The working capital for the company is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$14,900. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$64,900. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$72,900. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$176,900. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Balance Sheet," Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 201-207  Study Session 8-33-a, d  illustrate and interpret the components of the assets, liabilities, and equity sections of the balance sheet, and discuss the  uses of the balance sheet in financial analysis;   compare and contrast current and noncurrent assets and liabilities  Working capital = current assets - current liabilities.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>56. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  During late December 2007 Popular Publishing Inc. acquired a small competitor, Max's Magazines. In the evaluation  of the acquisition it was determined that the customer lists of Max's Magazines had a fair value of $50,000. Popular  Publishing had spent $15,000 during the year updating and maintaining its own customer lists. What is the correct  amount and asset account that will be recorded by Popular Publishing for the year-ended December 31, 2007, related to  customer lists?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$50,000 identifiable intangible asset </choice>
		<choice id="B">$65,000 identifiable intangible asset </choice>
		<choice id="C">$50,000 unidentifiable intangible asset </choice>
		<choice id="D">$65,000 unidentifiable intangible asset </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Balance Sheet," Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 218-220  "Analysis of Long-Lived Assets: Part I - The Capitalization Decision," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov  Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 354-355  Study Sessions 8-33-e, 9-36-b  explain the measurement bases (e.g., historical cost and fair value) of assets and liabilities, including current assets,  current liabilities, tangible assets, and intangible assets;  determine which intangible assets, including software development costs and research and development costs, should be  capitalized, according to U.S. GAAP and international accounting standards  The purchased customer list is an identifiable intangible because it can be sold separately from the company and it would  be recorded at its fair market value, the amount paid for it in the acquisition, $50,000. The amount spent by Popular on its  own lists, $15,000, would have to be expensed because internally generated intangibles are not capitalized.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>57. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Melbourne Manufacturing has equipment with an original cost of $850,000, accumulated amortization of $300,000 and  5 years of estimated remaining useful life. Due to a change in market conditions Melbourne now estimates that the  equipment will only generate cash flows of $80,000 per year over its remaining useful life. The company's incremental  borrowing rate is 8%. What is the amount of the impairment loss closest to and what would be the effect on the  company's return on assets (ROA) in future periods?     Impairment  Loss  Effect on ROA in  future periods 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$150,000 Increase </choice>
		<choice id="B">$150,000 Decrease </choice>
		<choice id="C">$230,583 Increase </choice>
		<choice id="D">$230,583 Decrease  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Income Statement," Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 169  "Analysis of Long-Lived Assets: Part II - Analysis of Depreciation and Impairment,"   Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 403-404   Study Session 9-37-d  explain and illustrate the use of impairment charges on long-lived assets, and analyze the effects of taking such  impairment charges on a company's financial statements and ratios  The equipment is impaired. NBV = $550,000, which is greater than the sum of the undiscounted cash flows 5 years x  $80,000 = $400,000. The amount of the impairment is 550,000 - PV of the cash flows = 550,000 - 319,417 (PMT =  80,000, N = 5, i = 8%) = 230,583. The company's ROA will increase. There will be lower depreciation charges in the  future, which will increase net income, and a lower carrying value of assets, which decreases total assets. Both factors  would increase any future ROA. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>58. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Which of the following factors is an analyst least likely to consider when determining if a company's deferred tax  liabilities should be treated as a liability or equity?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">The growth rate of the firm. </choice>
		<choice id="B">The average discount rate of liabilities. </choice>
		<choice id="C">The expectation that temporary differences will reverse. </choice>
		<choice id="D">The use of accelerated depreciation methods for tax purposes. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Analysis of Income Taxes," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 439-440  Study Session 9-38-d  explain the factors that determine whether a company's deferred tax liabilities should be treated as a liability or as equity  for purposes of financial analysis  The classification of deferred taxes as liabilities or equity depends on the likelihood, or expectation, of reversal. For  growing firms and those using accelerated methods of depreciation, the temporary differences tend not to reverse. If the  analyst determined the deferred tax liabilities were likely to reverse, and hence should be classified as liabilities, then it  would be appropriate to discount them at the company's average discount rate. But the discount rate is not a factor in  determining if reversal is likely. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>59. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  On January 1, 2007, Peoria Products Inc. entered into a lease agreement to lease a piece of machinery as the lessor. The  annual lease payments are $50,000, due December 31, the lease term is for 5 years, the machine has an estimated  useful life of 6 years, and Peoria currently records the machine on its balance sheet at its cost of $160,000. The  incremental rate of the lease is 8% and they are reasonably assured of the collection of the lease payments. Which of  the following best describes the classification and effect of the lease on Peoria's income statement for 2007 ? Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Operating lease. Rental revenue of $50,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Direct financing lease. Interest income of $15,971. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Sales type lease. Gross profit of $39,635 plus interest income of $15,971. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Direct financing lease. Gross profit of $39,635 plus interest income of $15,971. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Leases and Off-Balance-Sheet Debt," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 545-551.   Study Session 9-40-d  distinguish between sales-type leases and direct financing leases and explain the effects of these types of leases on the  financial statements of lessors  It is a sales type lease: the lease period covers more than 75% of its useful life (5/6) and the asset is on their books at less  than the present value of the lease payments ($199,635) (PMT = $50,000, N=5, i=8%). They must have acquired or  manufactured the asset if it is recorded at less than the present value of the lease payments. As a sales type lease they will  recognize gross profit for the difference of the present value and the cost (199,635 - 160,000 = 39,635) and then interest  income on the net investment in the lease (0.08 x 199,635 = 15,971). </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>60. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Which of the following would be the most useful to an analyst trying to assess the credit worthiness of a company?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Return measures related to net income. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Return measures related to operating cash flow. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Information related to the scale and diversity of a company's operations. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Information related to operational efficiency of the company's operations. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Financial Statement Analysis: Applications," Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and  Michael A. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 649-650  Study Session 10-42-c  describe the role of financial statement analysis in assessing the credit quality of a potential debt investment  Credit analysis is concerned with a company's debt-paying ability. Returns to creditors are normally paid in cash, so the  company's ability to generate cash internally is the most important factor in credit analysis. </comments>
</problem>



<problem>
	<question>61. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  All else equal, the net profit margin for a company will be highest if, for new depreciable assets, that company uses:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">low salvage value estimates and long average lives. </choice>
		<choice id="B">high salvage value estimates and long average lives. </choice>
		<choice id="C">low salvage value estimates and short average lives. </choice>
		<choice id="D">high salvage value estimates and short average lives. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Analysis of Long-Lived Assets: Part II - Analysis of Depreciation and Impairment," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C.  Sondhi, and Dov Fried   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 394-397  Study Session 9-37-b  demonstrate how modifying the depreciation method, the estimated useful life and/or the salvage value used in  accounting for long-lived assets affect financial statements and ratios  A high salvage value estimate reduces the depreciable base and thus depreciation expense; long average lives reduce the  annual depreciation expense for any given depreciable base. The combination of the two would result in the lowest  depreciation expense, which leads to the highest net income and profit margins. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>62. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following information about a company ($ millions):                  2007 2006  Sales 283.5 234.9  Year-end inventory (LIFO inventory method) 81.4 53.7  LIFO reserve 36.4 21.8  Cost of goods sold (LIFO) 203.9 167.3    If the company used the FIFO inventory method instead of LIFO, the company's 2007 gross profit margin would be  closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">22.9%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">28.1%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">29.8%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">33.2%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Analysis of Inventories," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 312-314  Study Session 9-35-c, d  compare and contrast the effect of the different methods on cost of goods sold and inventory balances, and discuss how a  company's choice of inventory accounting method affects other financial items such as income cash flow, and working  capital;  compare and contrast the effects of the choice of inventory method on profitability, liquidity, activity, and solvency ratios  COGS on a FIFO basis will equal COGS LIFO - Change in the LIFO reserve. The change in the LIFO reserve is 36.4 -  21.8 = 14.6; FIFO COGS will be 203.9 - 14.6 = 189.3. Gross profit will be 283.5 - 189.3 = 94.2. The gross margin will be  94.2 / 283.5 = 33.23%. (The gross margin for LIFO is 28.1%.) </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>63. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following information about a company that uses the LIFO method:  LIFO reserve as of 31 December 2006 $420,000 LIFO reserve as of 31 December 2007 $450,000 Marginal tax rate 30%           If the company had used the FIFO method instead of LIFO, the company's 2007 net income would most likely have been:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$21,000 lower. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$9,000 lower. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$9,000 higher. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$21,000 higher. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Analysis of Inventories," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 315-320  Study Session 9-35-c, e  compare and contrast the effect of the different methods on cost of goods sold and inventory balances, and discuss how a  company's choice of inventory accounting method affects other financial items such as income cash flow, and working  capital;  indicate the reasons that a LIFO reserve might decline during a given period and evaluate the implications of such a  decline for financial analysis  The LIFO reserve increased by $30,000. If an increase in the LIFO reserve occurs, LIFO cost of goods sold will be higher  than FIFO by the amount of the increase and net income would be lower than FIFO by $30,000(1 - 0.30) = $21,000.  After-tax FIFO net income would be $21,000 higher.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>64. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Greene Corporation uses the LIFO inventory method, but most of the other companies in Greene's industry use FIFO.  Which of the following best describes one of the adjustments that would be made to Greene's financial statements to  compare that company with other companies in the industry? To adjust Greene's ending inventory to the FIFO method,  the amount reported for Greene's ending inventory should be:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increased by the ending balance in Greene's LIFO reserve. </choice>
		<choice id="B">decreased by the ending balance in Greene's LIFO reserve. </choice>
		<choice id="C">increased by the change in Greene's LIFO reserve for that period. </choice>
		<choice id="D">decreased by the change in Greene's LIFO reserve for that period. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Analysis of Inventories," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 312  Study Session 9-35-c, d  compare and contrast the effect of the different methods on cost of goods sold and inventory balances, and discuss how a  company's choice of inventory accounting method affects other financial items such as income cash flow, and working  capital;  compare and contrast the effects of the choice of inventory method on profitability, liquidity, activity, and solvency ratios  Adding the ending balance in the LIFO reserve to the LIFO inventory would equal the ending balance for inventory on a  FIFO basis.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>65. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following information about a company:  Average market price per share of common stock during the year $40 Exercise price per share for options on 50,000 common shares $50 Exercise price per share for warrants on 20,000 common shares $30         Using the treasury stock method, the number of incremental shares that should be used to compute diluted earnings per  share is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">5,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">12,500. </choice>
		<choice id="C">15,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">17,500. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding the Income Statement," Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A.  Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 177-178  Study Session 8-32-h  describe the components of earnings per share and calculate a company's earnings per share (both basic and diluted  earnings per share) for both a simple and complex capital structure  Diluted EPS is calculated using the treasury stock method that considers what would be the effect if the options or  warrants had been exercised. Only options or warrants that are in-the-money are included, as out-of-the-money options  would not be exercised. Therefore, only the warrants are dilutive; the exercise price is below the average market price of  the stock. Using the treasury stock method:  20,000($30) = $600,000 in proceeds. $600,000 / $40 = 15,000 shares treasury stock. Incremental shares using the  treasury stock method = 20,000 - 15,000 = 5,000.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>66. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  At the beginning of the year, a lessee company entered into a new capital lease agreement. The lease payments are  $100,000 annually and are due at the end of each year for five years. The appropriate discount rate is 12%.  Depreciation is on a straight-line basis with zero salvage value. With respect to the effect of the lease on the company's  financial statements in the first year of the lease, which of the following is most accurate? The reduction in the  company's:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">pretax income is $72,096. </choice>
		<choice id="B">cash flow from financing is $56,742. </choice>
		<choice id="C">cash flow from operations is $72,096.  </choice>
		<choice id="D">cash flow from operations is $115,353. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Leases and Off-Balance Sheet Debt," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 521-524  Study Session 9-40-b  contrast the effects of capital and operating leases on the financial statements and ratios of the lessees and lessors  The present value of the lease is $360,477.62.   (n = 5, I = 12%, PMT = $100,000)  12% of the original PV is $43,257.31 and represents the interest component of the payment in the first year. The  difference between the annual payment and the interest is the amortization of the lease obligation and is included in cash  flow from financing. $100,000 - 43,257.31 = $56,742.69.  Depreciation is $360,477.62 / 5 or $72,095.52, so the total reduction in pretax income would be interest plus depreciation  or $115,352.83. Cash flow from operations would be reduced by the amount of the interest only because the depreciation  would be added back to determine cash flow from operations.     </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>67. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  The following information relates to a profitable company that offered a warranty on a new product introduced in  2007:  Actual expenditures for repairs under the warranty in 2007 $200,000 Accrued warranty expenses for the warranty in 2007 $300,000       If the company's tax rate is 35%, which of the following most accurately describes the deferred tax that should have been  recorded in 2007 with respect to that new product warranty?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Deferred tax asset of $35,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Deferred tax asset of $65,000. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Deferred tax liability of $35,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Deferred tax liability of $65,000. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Analysis of Income Taxes," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 423-424, 427  Study Session 9-38-f  calculate and interpret income tax expense, income taxes payable, deferred tax assets and deferred tax  liabilities  For financial statement purposes, the company overestimated the warranty expense that was actually  incurred in 2007; income for tax purposes was higher than income for financial statement purposes. Tax  expense on the financial statements will be less than taxes payable to the government by $100,000 (0.35)  = $35,000. The $35,000 represents a deferred tax asset.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>68. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  At the beginning of the year, a company issued a $1,000 face value bond. Interest on that bond is paid semiannually,  the annual coupon rate on the bond is 9%, and the bond matures in ten years. The market rate of interest at the time the  bond was issued was 10% on an annual basis. The amount of the initial liability recorded for this bond was closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$938. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$961. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$1,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$1,065. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Analysis of Financing Liabilities," Gerald I. White, Ashwinpaul C. Sondhi, and Dov Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 466-471  Study Session 9-39-b  determine the effects of debt issuance and amortization of bond discounts and premiums on the financial statements and  ratios  The liability and interest expense recorded are both based on market rates of interest when the bond was issued, not the  coupon rate on the bond. The market value of the bond at issuance was $937.68. (FV=1000, PMT=45, N=20, I/Y=5.0).      </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>69. An analyst gathered the following information about the cost and availability of raising new capital for a company:  Amount of new debt Cost of debt Amount of new Cost of  (in millions) (after tax) equity (in millions) equity  New debt ? EUR4.0  EUR4.0  new debt  4%  5%  New equity ? EUR5.0  EUR5.0  new equity  13%  15%              The company's target capital structure is 60% equity and 40% debt. If the company raises EUR9.5 million in new  financing, the marginal cost of capital for the last dollar raised is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">9.4%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">9.8%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">10.6%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">11.0%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Cost of Capital," Yves Courtois, Gene C. Lai, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 64-67  Study Session 11-45-j  describe the marginal cost of capital schedule, explain why it may be upward-sloping with respect to additional capital,  and calculate and interpret its break-points  The breakpoints for debt and equity are EUR10 million (EUR4.0 million / 0.40) and EUR8.33 million (EUR5.0 million / 0.60),  respectively. The cost of debt and equity if the firm raises EUR9.5 million in new financing will be 4% and 15%,  respectively, because EUR9.5 million is below the debt breakpoint and above the equity breakpoint. The marginal cost of  capital = 0.40 x 4% + 0.60 x 15% = 10.6%.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>70. An analyst gathered the following information about a company and the industry:  Liquidity measure Company Industry  Quick ratio  Current ratio  Days sales outstanding  Days payables outstanding  0.7  1.1  38.5  28.4  1.3  1.7  30.2  22.0                  Based only on the data above, the measure that should most concern the analyst regarding the company's working capital  management is the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">quick ratio. </choice>
		<choice id="B">current ratio. </choice>
		<choice id="C">days sales outstanding. </choice>
		<choice id="D">days payables outstanding. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Working Capital Management," Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 89-95  Study Session 11-46-a  calculate and interpret liquidity measures using selected financial ratios for a company and compare it with peer  companies  The company's days sales outstanding is considerably higher than the industry's, which means the company is slower in  collecting its receivables than the average firm. This is a concern because the longer receivables are outstanding, the  greater the probability they will not be collected and will have to be charged off, thereby adversely affecting earnings.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>71. An analyst gathered the following information for a company:  Liquidity measure Company  Inventory turnover  Accounts payable turnover  Accounts receivable turnover  20.7  14.1  12.5            Based only on the data above, the company's operating cycle is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">19.1 days. </choice>
		<choice id="B">20.9 days. </choice>
		<choice id="C">33.2 days. </choice>
		<choice id="D">46.8 days. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Working Capital Management," Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 89-95  Study Session 11-46-a, b  calculate and interpret liquidity measures using selected financial ratios for a company and compare it with peer  companies;  evaluate overall working capital effectiveness of a company, using the operating and cash conversion cycles, and  compare its effectiveness with other peer companies  Operating cycle = days inventory outstanding + days receivables outstanding  Days inventory outstanding = 365 / inventory turnover = 17.63 days  Days receivables outstanding = 365 / accounts receivable turnover = 29.2 days  Operating cycle = 17.63 days + 29.2 days = 46.8 days   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>72. Afton Inc. is offered trade credit terms of 2/10, net 45. Afton's implicit cost of failing to take the discount and instead  paying the account in 45 days is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">17.10%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">21.28%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">23.10%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">23.45%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Working Capital Management," Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 120-121  Study Session 11-46-f  evaluate the performance of a company's accounts receivable, inventory management, and accounts payable functions  against historical figures and comparable peer company values  The cost of trade credit if paid on day 45 = (1 + 2 / 98)365/35 - 1 = 23.45%.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>73. The cash manager for Thomas Industries plans to issue EUR2,500,000 (face value) of commercial paper for one month.  She is quoted a rate of 5.88% with a dealer's commission of 1/8% and a backup line cost of 25 basis points, both of which  will be assessed on the face value. The effective cost of the financing is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">5.91%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">6.03%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">6.16%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">6.29%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Working Capital Management," Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 126-128  Study Session 11-46-g  evaluate the choices of short-term funding available to a company and recommend a financing method  CP cost = [(interest + dealer's commissions + back-up costs) / net proceeds] x 12  Net proceeds = EUR2,500,000 - (0.0588 x EUR2,500,000 x 1/12) = EUR2,487,750  Interest + dealer's commissions + back-up costs = (0.0588 + 0.00125 + 0.0025) x EUR2,500,000 x 1/12 = 0.6255 x  EUR2,500,000 x 1/12 = EUR13,031  CP cost = (13,031 / 2,487,750) x 12 = 6.29%   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>74. Regarding corporate governance, which of the following most likely would be a reason for concern when evaluating a  board member's qualifications? The board member:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">has served on the board for 14 years. </choice>
		<choice id="B">owns 1000 shares of the corporation's equity. </choice>
		<choice id="C">is a college professor and a certified public accountant. </choice>
		<choice id="D">has formerly served on the boards of several successful companies. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"The Corporate Governance of Listed Companies: A Manual for Investors" (CFA Institute, 2005)  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 166-167  Study Session 11-48-d  identify factors that indicate a board and its members possess the experience required to govern the company for the  benefit of its shareowners  Such long-term participation may enhance the individual board member's knowledge of the company, but it also may  cause the board member to develop a cooperative relationship with management that could impair his/her willingness to  act in the best interests of shareowners.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>75. Which of the following is least likely to concern an investor that is evaluating a corporation's shareowner rights  provisions?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Shareowners may nominate board members. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Shareowners must attend the annual meeting to vote their shares. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Shares held by the founding family have supernormal voting rights. </choice>
		<choice id="D">To ensure accuracy, company officials tabulate and verify shareowner voting. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"The Corporate Governance of Listed Companies: A Manual for Investors" (CFA Institute, 2005)  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 182-187  Study Session 11-48-g  evaluate, from a shareowner's perspective, company policies related to voting rules, shareowner sponsored proposals,  common stock classes and takeover defenses  The ability to nominate one or more individuals to the board can prevent erosion of shareowner value. Shareowners may  be able to force the board or management to take steps to address shareowner concerns.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>76. Which of the following is least likely classified as an opportunity cost?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:     	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">The market value of vacant land used for a distribution center. </choice>
		<choice id="B">The cash savings related to adopting a new production process. </choice>
		<choice id="C">The cash flows generated by an old machine that is to be replaced. </choice>
		<choice id="D">The rent that could be received on a building if it were not used for a project.   </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Capital Budgeting," John D. Stowe and Jacques R. Gagne  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 10-12  Study Session 11-44-b  discuss the basic principles of capital budgeting, including the choice of the proper cash flows and determining the proper  discount rate  The cash savings related to adopting a new production process is an incremental cash flow, not an opportunity cost.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>77. An analyst determined the following cash flows for a capital project:  Year 0 1 2 3 4 5  Cash flow (EUR) -100 30 40 40 30 20     The required rate of return for the project is 13%. The internal rate of return (IRR) and the discounted payback period for  the project, respectively, are closest to:    IRR  Discounted payback  period 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">14.85% 2.75 </choice>
		<choice id="B">14.85% 3.78 </choice>
		<choice id="C">19.25% 2.75 </choice>
		<choice id="D">19.25% 3.78                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D.  </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Capital Budgeting," John D. Stowe and Jacques R. Gagne  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 12-19  Study Session 11-44-d  calculate and interpret the results using each of the following methods to evaluate a single capital project: net present  value (NPV), internal rate of return (IRR), payback period, discounted payback period, average accounting rate of return  (AAR), and profitability index (PI)  Using a calculator, the IRR is 19.25%.  The discounted payback period is the number of years (and fractional part of a year) that it takes to recover the initial  investment in terms of discounted future cash flows discounted at the project's required rate of return. The discounted  cash flows for the first four years are: EUR26.55, EUR31.33, EUR27.72, and EUR18.40. The cumulative sum through year three is  EUR85.60. The portion of year four required to recover the initial investment is EUR14.40 / EUR18.40 = 0.7828 ? 0.78. Therefore,  the discounted payback period is 3.78 years.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>78. Two mutually exclusive projects have conventional cash flows, but one project has a larger NPV while the other  project has a higher IRR. Which of the following is least likely responsible for this conflict?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Reinvestment rate assumption. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Timing of the projects' cash flows. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Size of the projects' initial investments. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Risk of the projects as reflected in the required rate of return.  </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Capital Budgeting," John D. Stowe and Jacques R. Gagne  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 19-25  Study Session 11-44-e  explain the NPV profile, compare and contrast the NPV and IRR methods when evaluating independent and  mutually-exclusive projects, and describe the problems that can arise when using an IRR  Conflicting decision rules based on the NPV and IRR methods are related to the reinvestment rate assumption, the timing  of the cash flows, or the scale of the projects. Differing required rates of return are not related to conflicting NPV and  IRR decisions.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>79. Value Line Index and Nikkei-Dow Jones Average use which of the following methods in the computation of the  holding period returns of underlying stocks, respectively?    Value Line Index Nikkei-Dow Jones Index 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Arithmetic mean Arithmetic mean </choice>
		<choice id="B">Arithmetic mean Geometric mean </choice>
		<choice id="C">Geometric mean Arithmetic mean </choice>
		<choice id="D">Geometric mean Geometric mean                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Security-Market Indexes," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 42-46  Study Session 13-53-a  compare and contrast the characteristics of, and discuss the source and direction of bias exhibited by, each of the three  predominant weighting schemes used in constructing stock market indexes, and compute a price-weighted,  value-weighted, and un-weighted index series for three stocks;  The Value Line Index, an un-weighted index, uses the geometric mean return approach where as the Nikkei-Dow Jones  Average, a price-weighted index, uses the arithmetic mean approach.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>80.  The four firms in the Internet search engine industry have the following market shares:  Company Market Share  Gigloo 50%  Ohooho 25%  MySearch 15%  Foxnet 10%          The Herfindahl Index and the "Equivalent Number" of firms in this industry, respectively, are closest to:    Herfindahl Index  "Equivalent Number"  of firms 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">0.345 4.00 </choice>
		<choice id="B">0.345 2.90 </choice>
		<choice id="C">0.478 2.09 </choice>
		<choice id="D">0.478 4.00                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Equity: Concepts and Techniques," Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 138-139  Study Session 14-58-d, e  discuss the specific advantages of both the concentration ratio and the Herfindahl index;  discuss, with respect to global industry analysis, the elements related to risk, and describe the basic forces that determine  industry competition  Herfindahl Index = 0.52 + 0.252 + 0.152 + 0.12 = 0.25 + 0.0625 + 0.0225 + 0.01 = 0.345  "Equivalent Number" of firms = 1 / 0.345 = 2.8986 ? 2.90    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>81. Chu Wang, CFA, gathered the following data to estimate the implied growth rate of dividends for Shenghai Toys Co.  to use as an input for valuing the company's common stock.  Return on Assets        10%  Profit Margin        5%  Total Assists       CNY 50 million  Debt Ration       40%  Payout Ration       25%  Wang's estimate of Shenghai Toys' implied growth rate would be closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">4.17%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">6.25%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">12.50%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">18.75%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"An Introduction to Security Valuation: Part II," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 196-198  Study Session 14-60-e  estimate the implied dividend growth rate, given the components of the required return on equity and incorporating the  earnings retention rate and current stock price  g = RR x ROE  RR = (1 - Payout Ratio) = 1 - 0.25 = 0.75  Financial Leverage = TA / Equity  Debt = TA x Debt Ratio = CNY 50 m x 0.4 = CNY 20 m  Equity = CNY 50 m - CNY 20 m = CNY 30 m  ROE = ROA x Financial Leverage; ROE = 10% x (50/30) = 16.67%  g = 0.75 x 16.67 = 12.50%    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>82. Which of the following is the least accurate statement about the short sale of stocks?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">The short seller must pay any dividends due to the lender of shares. </choice>
		<choice id="B">A stop buy order would enable a short seller to minimize potential losses. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Short sales involve time limits for returning the shares borrowed to the lender. </choice>
		<choice id="D">A short sale can be made only on an uptick or a zero uptick trade if the previous trade was an uptick trade. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Organization and Functioning of Securities Markets," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 24-26  Study Session 13-52-f  describe the process of selling a stock short and discuss an investor's likely motivation for selling short  Short sales have no time limits. However, if the lender of shares decides to sell them, the broker must find another  investor willing to lend the shares.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>83. The appropriate measures of free cash flow and discount rate to use when estimating the total value of a firm,  respectively, are:    Measure of free cash flow Discount rate 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A"> operating cash flow before interest  payments on debt  cost of equity </choice>
		<choice id="B"> operating cash flow before interest  payments on debt  weighted average  cost of capital </choice>
		<choice id="C"> operating cash flow before interest payments on  debt but after deducting base capital  expenditures  cost of equity </choice>
		<choice id="D"> operating cash flow before interest payments on  debt but after deducting base capital  expenditures  weighted average  cost of capital                              Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"An Introduction to Security Valuation: Part II," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 184-185  Study Session 14-60-f  describe a process for developing estimated inputs to be used in the DDM, including the required rate of return and  expected growth rate of dividends  In estimating the value of total firm, the free cash flow available to both stockholders and bondholders should be used.  Therefore, operating cash flow before debt related costs and after subtracting the required capital expenditures is the  appropriate measure of free cash flow. As the value of the total firm includes the value of equity and the value of debt, the  weighted average cost of capital is the relevant discount rate.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>84. On January 1, 2008, Abel Moreno, CFO of Monterrey Mining Metals (MMM), gathered the following data to  determine the attractiveness of the company's common stock:  Dividends per share in 2001 2 pesos  Dividends per share in 2007 3 pesos  Expected return on the market 17%  Expected nominal risk-free return 9%  MMM's beta 1.8  MMM share price, January 1, 2008 19 pesos            Based on the information gathered, MMM stock's intrinsic value and its attractiveness on January 1, 2008, respectively,  were:     Stock's intrinsic value  closest to:  Stock's attractiveness 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">18.29 pesos Over-valued </choice>
		<choice id="B">18.29 pesos Under-valued </choice>
		<choice id="C">19.57 pesos Over-valued </choice>
		<choice id="D">19.57 pesos Under-valued                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"The Time Value of Money," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavy, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 199-200  "Cost of Capital," Yves Courtois, Gene C. Lai, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 50  "An Introduction to Security Valuation: Part II," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 176-181, 198  Study Sessions 2-5-d; 4-45-h; 14-60-b, e  Calculate and interpret the future value (FV) and present value (PV) of a single sum of money, an ordinary annuity, an  annuity due, a perpetuity (PV only) and a series of unequal cash flows;  calculate and interpret the cost of equity capital using the capital asset pricing model approach, the dividend discount  model approach, and the bond-yield-plus risk-premium approach;   calculate and interpret the value both of a preferred stock and a common stock using the dividend discount model (DDM);  estimate the implied dividend growth rate, given the components of the required return on equity and incorporating the  earnings retention rate and current stock price  g = growth rate of dividends = 7% [(3 / 2)1 / 6]; k = 9 + 1.8 (17 - 9) = 23.4%  V = 3(1.07) / (0.234 - 0.07) = 19.57 pesos;  The stock's intrinsic value > price, so it is undervalued.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>85. Strongsville Fabricators Inc. uses the FIFO method of inventory valuation. Assuming a rising costs environment and  other factors held constant, Strongsville's price-to-earnings and price-to-book multiples relative to those for another  company that uses the LIFO method of inventory valuation would be:    Price-to-earnings multiple Price-to-book multiple 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">overstated overstated </choice>
		<choice id="B">overstated understated </choice>
		<choice id="C">understated overstated </choice>
		<choice id="D">understated understated                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Introduction to Price Multiples," John D. Stowe, Thomas R. Robinson, Jerald E. Pinto, and Dennis W. McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 208-209, 216-217  Study Session 14-61-b  calculate and interpret P/E, P/BV, P/S, and P/CF  In a rising costs environment, FIFO would result in higher earnings, higher ending inventory, as well as higher book  value of equity. Thus, both P/E and P/BV tend to be understated relative to a comparable firm that uses LIFO method.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>86. The behavior of investors in which they put more money into a failure that they feel responsible for rather than into a  success, is explained by which of the following behavioral biases?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Escalation bias </choice>
		<choice id="B">Confirmation bias </choice>
		<choice id="C">Overconfidence bias </choice>
		<choice id="D">Fusion investing bias </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Efficient Capital Markets," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 83-84  Study Session 14-54-d  define behavioral finance and describe overconfidence bias, confirmation bias, and escalation bias  Escalation bias refers to the investor behavior of putting more money into a failure that they feel responsible for rather  than into a success. This leads to the practice of "averaging down" by viewing the additional purchase as a "bargain"  rather than considering the initial purchase as a mistake and selling the stock.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>87. Jim Klein, CFA, gathered the following data about India Garments Company in an effort to determine the growth rate  of dividends and the payout ratio implied in the company's stock price:  Stock price $40  Stock's required return 12%  Consensus estimate of next year's dividend $2.00  Company's return on equity 10%        The company's dividend  growth rate according to the Gordon model and the payout ratio, respectively, are closest to:                     Dividend growth rate Payout ratio 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">5% 50% </choice>
		<choice id="B">5% 58% </choice>
		<choice id="C">7% 30% </choice>
		<choice id="D">7% 42%  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Cost of Capital," Yves Courtois, Gene C. Lai, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 54-55  "An Introduction to Security Valuation: Part II," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 196-197   Study Sessions 11-45-h, 14-60-e   calculate and interpret the cost of equity capital using the capital asset pricing model approach, the dividend discount  model approach, and the bond-yield-plus risk-premium approach;  estimate the implied dividend growth rate, given the components of the required return on equity and incorporating the  earnings retention rate and current stock price   V0 = D1 / (k - g); $40 = $2 / (0.12 - g); g = 7%; g = ROE x RR; RR = 7 / 10 = 0.70;  Payout Ratio = 1 - RR = 1 - 0.70 = 0.30 = 30%.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>88. Which of the following is the attribute that is most closely associated with the liquidity of a securities market?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Low transaction costs </choice>
		<choice id="B">Timely and accurate information </choice>
		<choice id="C">Price continuity and market depth </choice>
		<choice id="D">Rapid adjustment of prices to new information </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Organization and Functioning of Securities Markets," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 7-8  Study Session 13-52-a  describe the characteristics of a well-functioning securities market  Liquidity refers to the ability to buy or sell an asset quickly and at a known price. Price continuity is a component of  liquidity which in turn requires market depth. The distracters in A, B, and D are characteristics of a good market, just as  liquidity, but not most closely associated with, or as components of, liquidity.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>89. The most accurate characterization of the nature of abnormal returns relating to an anomaly and a source of  unreliability of an anomaly, respectively, are:                89 Correct answer is B    Nature of abnormal returns  Source of unreliability of  an anomaly 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Persistent Behavioral bias </choice>
		<choice id="B">Persistent Survivorship bias </choice>
		<choice id="C">Momentary Behavioral bias </choice>
		<choice id="D"></choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>  Nature of abnormal returns  Source of unreliability of  an anomaly  A. Persistent Behavioral bias  B. Persistent Survivorship bias  C. Momentary Behavioral bias  D. Momentary Survivorship bias  "Market Efficiency and Anomalies," Vijay Singal  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 100-107   Study Session 13-55-d  explain why a mispricing may persist and why valid anomalies may not be profitable  The persistent realization of abnormal returns is referred to as an anomaly and survivorship bias is a  source of unreliability of an anomaly. </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>90. Robert Wu, CFA, gathered the following data on Westminster Property Developers Inc:   Earnings per share - most recent year $2.00  Expected growth rate of dividends 5.10%  Dividend payout ratio 60%  Stock's beta 1.50  Market risk premium 5.60%  Risk-free rate 4.2%  Company's weighted average cost of capital 12%                      Wu's best estimate for the company's price per share would be closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$16.00. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$16.82. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$17.39. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$18.28. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"An Introduction to Asset Pricing Models," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 263-265  "An Introduction to Security Valuation: Part II," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 180-181  Study Sessions 12-51-e, 14-60-b  calculate, using the SML, the expected return on a security and evaluate whether the security is overvalued, undervalued,  or properly valued;   calculate and interpret the value both of a preferred stock and a common stock using the dividend discount model (DDM)  Most recent dividend = 2.00 (0.6) = 1.20  ks = 4.20 + 5.60(1.50) = 12.60%;  V = 1.20(1.051) / (0.126 - 0.051) = $16.82    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>91. A series of interest rate put options that expire on different dates but have the same exercise rate is best characterized  as a(n):  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">zero-cost collar. </choice>
		<choice id="B">interest rate cap. </choice>
		<choice id="C">interest rate floor. </choice>
		<choice id="D">interest rate collar. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Option Markets and Contracts", Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 90-93  Study Session 17-73-d  define interest rate caps, and floors, and collars  An interest rate floor is a series of put options on an interest rate, with each option expiring at the date on which the  floating loan rate will be reset, and with each option having the same exercise rate.    </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>92. The party making the fixed-rate payment under a swap contract could also have to make the variable payment on that  contract if the payments are related to a(n):  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">equity swap. </choice>
		<choice id="B">currency swap. </choice>
		<choice id="C">interest rate swap. </choice>
		<choice id="D">plain vanilla swap. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Swap Markets and Contracts," Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 130-141  Study Session 17-74-b  define and give examples of currency swaps, plain vanilla interest rate swaps, and equity swaps and calculate and  interpret the payments on each  If the value of the index on which the swap is based declines, the resulting negative return would have to be paid by the  party making the fixed-rate payment. This characteristic is one of the distinguishing features of equity swaps.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>93. An investor establishes a short position in a futures contract on Day 0 when the price per contract is $100. The  investor deposits $5 per contract to meet the initial margin requirement. The maintenance margin requirement per  contract is $3. The Day 1 settlement price that would require the investor deposit additional funds on Day 2 equal to $4  per contract is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$96.00. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$97.00. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$103.00. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$104.00. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Futures Markets and Contracts," Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 55-60  Study Session 17-72-c  describe price limits and the process of marking to market, and compute and interpret the margin balance, given the  previous day's balance and the change in the futures price  The investor has a short position and will experience a margin call only if the price increases. Additional margin must be  deposited to bring the ending balance up to the initial margin requirement. The investor must deposit $4; therefore, the  margin balance on Day 1 is -$4, which would result if the price of the contract was $104.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>94. Two parties agree to a forward contract to deliver the SP 500 Index at a price of $375,000 in 2 months time. When  the forward contract expires, the price of the SP 500 Index is $350,000 but the long party is unable to pay the cash  settlement. The short party is most likely obligated to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">default on the forward contract. </choice>
		<choice id="B">do nothing until the long makes payment. </choice>
		<choice id="C">accept delivery of SP 500 stocks from the long. </choice>
		<choice id="D">deliver the portfolio of SP 500 stocks to the long. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Forward Markets and Contracts," Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 32-33  Study Session 17-71-a  differentiate between the positions held by the long and short parties to a forward contract in terms of delivery/settlement  and default risk  Given a forward contract cash settlement, only the net payment is required. The long owes the short $25,000.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>95. If the coupon rate of a bond is higher than its yield to maturity, the price of a bond forward on the coupon date of this  coupon-bearing bond will be equal to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">par value. </choice>
		<choice id="B">spot value. </choice>
		<choice id="C">less than par value. </choice>
		<choice id="D">more than par value. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Forward Markets and Contracts," Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 39-40  Study Session 17-71-d  describe the characteristics of equity forward contracts and forward contracts on zero-coupon and coupon bonds  When the coupon rate of a bond is greater than the yield to maturity, the bond trades at a premium. This is accurate for  bond forward contracts.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>96. An investor goes long an FRA that expires in 30 days for which the underlying is 90-day LIBOR for a notional of $10  million. A dealer quotes this instrument at 4.5%. At expiration, 60-day LIBOR is 3.5% and 90-day LIBOR is 4%. The  payment made at expiration is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$12,376 from the investor to the dealer. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$12,376 from the dealer to the investor. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$16,570 from the investor to the dealer. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$16,570 from the dealer to the investor. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Forward Markets and Contracts," Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 40-43  Study Session 17-71-g  calculate and interpret the payoff of an FRA and explain each of the component terms   The underlying of an FRA is an interest payment. The investor is long the rate and will benefit if rates increase. Since  rates decreased, the investor must pay the dealer:       </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>97. The spread between the yields on a Ginnie Mae passthrough security and a comparable Treasury security is best  explained by:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">credit risk. </choice>
		<choice id="B">the coupon rate. </choice>
		<choice id="C">prepayment risk. </choice>
		<choice id="D">reinvestment risk. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding Yield Spreads," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 357-358  Study Session 15-65-g  identify how embedded options affect yield spreads  Mortgage-backed securities expose an investor to prepayment risk.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>98. According to the Liquidity Preference Theory, is the term structure of interest rates most likely related to:     Expectations about  future rates?  Interest rate risk? 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No No </choice>
		<choice id="B">No Yes </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes No </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes Yes                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding Yield Spreads," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 350  Study Session 15-65-c  explain the basic theories of the term structure of interest rates and describe the implications of each theory for the shape  of the yield curve  The Liquidity Preference Theory asserts that market participants want to be compensated for the interest rate risk  associated with holding long-term bonds. The longer the maturity, the greater the price volatility when interest rates  change and investors want to be compensated for this risk. According to the Liquidity Preference Theory, the term  structure of interest rates is determined by expectations about future rates and a yield premium for interest rate risk.  Because interest rate risk increases with maturity, The Liquidity Preference Theory asserts that the yield premium  increases with maturity.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>99. An annual-pay bond has a yield to maturity of 5.00%. The bond-equivalent yield of the annual-pay bond is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.50%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">4.94%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">5.00%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">5.06%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Yield Measures, Spot Rates, and Forward Rates," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 431  Study Session 16-68-d  compute and interpret the bond equivalent yield of an annual-pay bond and the annual-pay yield of a semiannual-pay  bond  The bond-equivalent yield of an annual-pay bond = 2 x [(1 + yield on annual-pay bond)0.5 - 1] = 2 x [(1 + 0.05)0.5 - 1] =  0.0494 = 4.94%   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>100. An analyst gathered the following information:  Periods Year  Annual Par Yield  to Maturity  Theoretical  Spot rate  Six-month  Forward Rates      BEY (%) BEY (%) BEY (%)  1 0.5 3.00 3.00 3.00  2 1.0 3.30 3.30 3.61  3 1.5 3.50 3.51 3.91  4 2.0 3.90 3.92 5.15                      The value of a single, default-free cash flow of $50,000 at the end of Period 4 is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$45,222. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$46,265. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$46,299. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$46,316. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Yield Measures, Spot Rates, and Forward Rates," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 440-445, 453-456  Study Session 16-68-e  describe the methodology for computing the theoretical Treasury spot rate curve, and compute the value of a bond using  spot rates  The theoretical spot rates for Treasury securities represent the appropriate set of interest rates that should be used to value  default-free cash flows. Therefore:  $50,000 / (1 + 0.0392/2)4 = $46,264.80 ? $46,265.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>101. The zero-volatility spread (Z-spread) is a measure of the spread off:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">all points on the spot curve. </choice>
		<choice id="B">one point on the spot curve. </choice>
		<choice id="C">all points on the Treasury yield curve. </choice>
		<choice id="D">one point on the Treasury yield curve. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Yield Measures, Spot Rates, and Forward Rates," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 446-449  Study Session 16-68-f  differentiate between the nominal spread, the zero-volatility spread, and the option-adjusted spread  The zero-volatility spread is a measure of the spread that the investor would realize over the entire Treasury spot rate  curve if the bond is held to maturity.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>102. The difference between nominal spread and zero-volatility spread will most likely be greater for a:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">zero coupon Treasury security. </choice>
		<choice id="B">mortgage-backed security in flat yield curve environment. </choice>
		<choice id="C">U.S. Treasury security with short maturity in a flat yield curve environment. </choice>
		<choice id="D">mortgage-backed security in a steep upward-sloping yield curve environment. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Yield Measures, Spot Rates, and Forward Rates," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 449-450  Study Session 16-68-f  differentiate between the nominal spread, the zero-volatility spread, and the option-adjusted spread  The difference between the Z-spread and the nominal spread is greater for issues in which the principal is repaid over  time rather than only at maturity. In addition, the difference between the Z-spread and the nominal spread is greater in a  steep yield curve environment.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>103. The option adjusted spread (OAS) is best described as the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Z-spread minus the option cost. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Z-spread plus the cost of the option. </choice>
		<choice id="C">value of the security's embedded option. </choice>
		<choice id="D">effect of changes in interest rates on the value of the security. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Yield Measures, Spot Rates, and Forward Rates," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 451-452  Study Session 16-68-g  describe how the option-adjusted spread accounts for the option cost in a bond with an embedded option  The Z-spread is the sum of the OAS and the option cost.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>104. If interest rates are expected to decline, an investor can earn a higher coupon interest rate by purchasing a(n):  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">callable bond. </choice>
		<choice id="B">inverse floater. </choice>
		<choice id="C">floater with a cap. </choice>
		<choice id="D">mortgage-backed security. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Features of Debt Securities," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 242-245  Study Session 15-62-b, e  describe the basic features of a bond, the various coupon rate structures, and the structure of floating-rate securities;  identify the common options embedded in a bond issue, explain the importance of embedded options, and state whether  such options benefit the issuer or the bondholder  Inverse floaters have a coupon formula such that the coupon rate increases when the reference rate decreases and  decreases when reference rate increases. The coupon rate moves in the opposite direction from the change in the  reference rate.     </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>105. The duration of a fixed-income portfolio is best interpreted as the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">first derivative of the price function for the bonds in the portfolio. </choice>
		<choice id="B">total number of years to receive the present value of the portfolio's cash flows. </choice>
		<choice id="C">percentage change in the portfolio's value if interest rates change by 100 basis points. </choice>
		<choice id="D">weighted average number of years to receive the present value of the portfolio's cash flows. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Introduction to the Measurement of the Interest Rate Risk," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 498-499  Study Session 16-69-e  distinguish among the alternative definitions of duration, and explain why effective duration is the most appropriate  measure of interest rate risk for bonds with embedded options;  Users of this interest rate risk measure are interested in what it tells them about the price sensitivity of a bond or a  portfolio to change in interest rates.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>106. An analyst gathered the following information about the market prices of two option-free bonds, and their expected  prices given a 50 basis point increase or decrease in yield.      Expected Price for  Bond.  Market  Price  50 bp  Increase  50 bp  decrease  A 102.00 101.04 102.97  B 88.69 83.81 94.07          The effective durations of Bond A and Bond B are closest to:    Bond A Bond B 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">0.95 5.78 </choice>
		<choice id="B">0.95 11.57 </choice>
		<choice id="C">1.89 5.78 </choice>
		<choice id="D">1.89 11.57                        Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Introduction to the Measurement of the Interest Rate Risk," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 488-489  Study Session 16-69-d  compute and interpret the effective duration of a bond, given information about how the bond's price will increase and  decrease for given changes in interest rates, and compute the approximate percentage price change for a bond, given the  bond's effective duration and a specified change in yield  Effective duration = (V_ - V+ ) / (2 x Vo x ?y)  Duration for Bond A = (102.97 - 101.04) / (2 x 102.00 x 0.005) = 1.89Duration for Bond B = (94.07 - 83.81) / (2 x 88.69  x 0.005) = 11.57   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>107. A U.S. investor has purchased a tax-exempt 5-year municipal bond at a yield of 3.86%, which is 100 basis points  less than the yield on a 5-year option-free U.S. Treasury. If the investor's marginal tax rate is 32%, then the  taxable-equivalent yield and the yield ratio are closest to:     Taxable Equivalent  Yield  Yield Ratio 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.62 0.79 </choice>
		<choice id="B">2.62 1.26 </choice>
		<choice id="C">5.68 0.79 </choice>
		<choice id="D">5.68 1.26                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Understanding Yield Spread," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 352-355, 359-361  Study Session 16-65-e, i  compute, compare, and contrast the various yield spread measures;  compute the after-tax yield of a taxable security and the tax-equivalent yield   of a tax-exempt security  Taxable equivalent yield = (tax-exempt yield) / (1 - marginal tax rate) =       3.86 / (1 - 0.32) = 5.68%    Yield ratio = (yield on tax-exempt bond) / (yield of US Treasury) =       3.86 / (3.86 + 100bp) = 3.86 / 4.86 = 0.79   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>108. An analyst gathered the following information about a portfolio comprised of three bonds:  Bond Price ($)  Par Amount  Owned  Duration  A 102,000 $7 million 1.89  B 94.356 $5 million 7.70  C 88.688 $3 million 11.55                  Assuming there is no accrued interest, then the portfolio duration is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">5.55 years. </choice>
		<choice id="B">5.76 years. </choice>
		<choice id="C">6.82 years. </choice>
		<choice id="D">7.05 years. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Introduction to the Measurement of the Interest Rate Risk," Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 500-501  Study Session 16-69-f  compute the duration of a portfolio, given the duration of the bonds comprising the portfolio, and explain the limitations  of portfolio duration  Portfolio value = (1.02 x 7 mil) + (0.94356 x 5 mil) + (0.88688 x 3 mil) = 14,518,440  Weight, Bond A = 7,140,000 / 14,518,440 = 0.492  Weight, Bond B = 4,717,800 / 14,518,440 = 0.325  Weight, Bond C = 2,660,640 / 14,518,440 = 0.183  Portfolio duration = (0.492 x 1.89) + (0.325 x 7.70) + (0.183 x 11.55) = 5.55   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>109. Which of the following statements is least accurate with respect to the advantages of open-end exchange traded  funds (ETFs)? Open-end ETFs:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">tend to trade closer to their net asset values than close-end index funds. </choice>
		<choice id="B">provide for more immediate reinvestment of dividends than index mutual funds. </choice>
		<choice id="C">provide a more cost-effective way for large institutions to invest in emerging markets. </choice>
		<choice id="D">provide lower exposure to capital gains distribution taxes than traditional mutual funds.  </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Alternative Investments," Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 184-185   Study Session 18-76-c  explain the advantages and risks of ETFs  Some sector and international ETFs have large bid-ask spreads and substantial expense ratios compared to managed  portfolios, which may provide a more cost-efficient alternative to ETFs, particularly for large institutional investors.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>110. A real estate investment has the following characteristics:  Annual rental income $1,800,000 Annual operating expenses $1,200,000 Available mortgage rate 6% Financing percentage 90% Required rate of return  15% Estimated holding period 5 years Investor's tax rate 25%                     Based on the income approach, the value of the investment is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$4,000,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$5,455,000. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$6,133,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$8,696,000. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Alternative Investments," Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 193-194  Study Session 18-76-f  calculate the net operating income (NOI) from a real estate investment, the value of a property using the sales comparison  and income approaches, and the after-tax cash flows, net present value, and yield of a real estate investment  Using the income approach:  ($1,800,000 - $1,200,000) / 0.15 = $4,000,000   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>111. Which real estate valuation approach is most likely to require specific information about an investor to estimate the  value of a property?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Cost approach </choice>
		<choice id="B">Income approach </choice>
		<choice id="C">Sales comparison approach </choice>
		<choice id="D">Discounted after-tax cash flow approach </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"Alternative Investments," Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 190-198  Study Session 18-76-e  describe the various approaches to the valuation of real estate  The after-tax cash flow approach requires specific information about the investor's marginal tax rate. The value of the  property is dependent on the investor's marginal tax rate.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>112. Do hedge funds typically have a(n):    focus on relative returns? option-like fee structure? 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No No </choice>
		<choice id="B">No Yes </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes No </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes Yes                  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Alternative Investments," Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 209-210  Study Session 18-76-i  discuss the descriptive accuracy of the term "hedge fund," define hedge fund in terms of objectives, legal structure, and  fee structure, and describe the various classifications of hedge funds   Hedge funds focus on absolute returns and place specific bets in the search for positive alphas. Because the fee structure  includes a small base fee plus an incentive fee proportional to profits, hedge funds have an option-like fee structure.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>113. An analyst compared the performance of a hedge fund index with the performance of a major stock index over the  past eight years. She noted that the hedge fund index (created from a database) had a higher average return, higher  standard deviation, and higher Sharpe ratio than the stock index. All the successful funds that have been in the hedge  fund database continued to accept new money over the eight-year period. Are the average return and the standard  deviation, respectively, for the hedge fund index most likely overstated or understated?     Average return for the  hedge fund index  Standard deviation for the  hedge fund index 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Overstated Overstated </choice>
		<choice id="B">Overstated Understated </choice>
		<choice id="C">Understated Overstated </choice>
		<choice id="D">Understated Understated                    Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Answer A.  B. Answer B.  C. Answer C.  D. Answer D. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Alternative Investments," Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 220-222  Study Session 18-76-l  discuss the performance of hedge funds, the biases present in hedge fund performance measurement, and explain the  effect of survivorship bias on the reported return and risk measures for a hedge fund database  Survivorship bias affects both the returns and the risk (standard deviation) reported for the hedge funds. Hedge funds with  low or negative returns will be excluded from the index as will funds with high volatility; those funds will not survive for  eight years. If only the successful funds remain in the index, the returns are overstated and the risk is understated.  Overstated returns and understated risk will tend to overstate the Sharpe ratio.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>114. An analyst estimates that an initial investment of GBP500,000 in a venture capital project will pay GBP6 million at the end  of five years if the project succeeds and that the probability the project survives to the end of the fifth year is 25%. The  required rate of return for the project is 19%. The expected net present value of the venture capital investment is closest  to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">GBP4,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">GBP128,000. </choice>
		<choice id="C">GBP1,125,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">GBP2,014,000. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Alternative Investments," Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 205-206  Study Session 18-76-h  calculate the net present value (NPV) of a venture capital project, given the project's possible payoff and conditional  failure probabilities   The probability that the venture will pay GBP6 million at the end of five years is 25%. The probability of failure is 75%. The  expected NPV if the project succeeds is GBP2,014,296 using FV = 6,000,000, I = 19%, n = 5 for a present value of  2,514,296 - 500,000 = 2,014,296  The NPV of the project is 0.25(2,014,296) + 0.75(-500,000) = 128,574  The investment has a positive NPV and should be accepted.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>115. In the context of capital market theory and the capital asset pricing model (CAPM), the average investor is least  likely to be compensated for assuming risk that can be:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">reduced by diversification. </choice>
		<choice id="B">related to interest rate volatility. </choice>
		<choice id="C">related to changes in macroeconomic variables. </choice>
		<choice id="D">measured by the standard deviation of returns of the market portfolio. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"An Introduction to Asset Pricing Models," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 259-262  Study Session 12-51-c  define systematic and unsystematic risk, and explain why an investor should not expect to receive additional return for  assuming unsystematic risk  Unsystematic risk (risk that can be diversified away) is not rewarded. Systematic risk is the risk for which investors are  compensated. Systematic risk is that part of total risk that is correlated with the market and related to changes in  macroeconomic variables (such as changes in interest rate volatility). Standard deviation of returns of the market portfolio  is a measurement of systematic risk.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>116. As an investor assumes more risk and moves upward on the efficient frontier, the slope of the efficient frontier curve  most likely:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increases and expected return per unit of risk increases. </choice>
		<choice id="B">increases and expected return per unit of risk decreases. </choice>
		<choice id="C">decreases and expected return per unit of risk increases. </choice>
		<choice id="D">decreases and expected return per unit of risk decreases. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>"An Introduction to Portfolio Management," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 248-249  Study Session 12-50-f  describe the efficient frontier, and explain the implications for incremental returns as an investor assumes more risk  The efficient frontier is curved. As an investor moves up the curve, risk increases and the slope decreases. The decreasing  slope means that adding equal increments of risk provide diminishing increments of expected return.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>117. Which of the following statements about the relation between covariance and correlation is least accurate? If the  covariance of returns between two assets is positive, the correlation coefficient for those two assets:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">must also be positive. </choice>
		<choice id="B">could be a negative number. </choice>
		<choice id="C">could indicate a strong positive relation if both return series were stable. </choice>
		<choice id="D">could indicate a weak positive relation if both return series were volatile. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"An Introduction to Portfolio Management," by Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 232-237  Study Session 12-50-d  compute and interpret the covariance of rates of return, and show how it is related to the correlation coefficient  If the covariance of returns between two assets is a positive number, the correlation coefficient for those two assets  cannot be negative. The correlation coefficient is equal to the covariance standardized by the product of the individual  standard deviations (which are always positive).   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>118. The risk-free rate of return is 3%, the market risk premium is 9%, and the market is in equilibrium. If a common  stock with a beta of 1.2 is properly valued, then the stock's estimated rate of return is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">10.2%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">10.8%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">13.8%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">14.4%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"An Introduction to Asset Pricing Models," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 264-266  Study Session 12-51-e  calculate, using the SML, the expected return on a security, and evaluate whether the security is overvalued, undervalued,  or properly valued  In equilibrium the estimated rate of return is equal to the required return. The CAPM required rate of return = 3% + (1.2 x  9%) = 13.8%.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>119. Regarding an individual's investment policy statement, which of the following is least appropriate as the investment  objective? The portfolio seeks:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">current income in the form of dividends and interest. </choice>
		<choice id="B">12% annual returns with above-average market risk. </choice>
		<choice id="C">to match the performance and risk characteristics of the SP 500 Index. </choice>
		<choice id="D">long-term capital appreciation with market risk comparable to the MSCI EAFE Index.   </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"The Asset Allocation Decision," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 202-210  Study Session 12-49-a, b, c  describe the steps in the portfolio management process, and explain the reasons for a policy statement;  explain why investment objectives should be expressed in terms of risk and return, and list the factors that may affect an  investor's risk tolerance;  describe the return objectives of capital preservation, capital appreciation, current income, and total return  The investment objective must be expressed in terms of both risk and return and current income from dividends and  interest represents only the investor's return objective. It does not include any reference to risk tolerance or risk limits as  provided in the other alternatives.   </comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>120. An analyst gathered the following information about a common stock:  Probability Possible Rate of Return  0.35 8%  0.30 10%  0.25 15%  0.10 20%                    The expected return and expected standard deviation of returns, respectively, for the common stock are closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">12% and 3.9%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">12% and 15.3%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">14% and 3.9%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">14% and 15.3%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"An Introduction to Portfolio Management," Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 230-232  Study Session 12-50-c  compute and interpret the expected return, variance, and standard deviation for an individual investment and the expected  return and standard deviation for a portfolio  The expected return of an asset is the weighted average of the possible returns = (0.35 x 8) + (0.30 x 10) + (0.25 x 16) +  (0.10 x 20) = 11.8%.  The expected standard deviation is calculated as follows:  ?2 = 0.35 x (8 - 11.8)2 + 0.30 x (10 - 11.8)2 + 0.25 x (15 - 11.8)2 + 0.10 x (20 - 11.8)2  = 15.31  s = (15.31)0.5 = 3.91%   </comments>
</problem>
