

<problem>
	<question>1. Which of the following least likely reflects the two primary principles of the CFA Institute Rules of Procedure for Proceedings Related to Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Confidentiality of proceedings</choice>

		<choice id="B">Fair process to the member and candidate</choice>

		<choice id="C">Public disclosure of disciplinary sanctions</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct,&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 8 Study Session 1-1-a Describe the structure of the CFA Institute Professional Conduct Program and the process for the enforcement of the Code and Standards. C is correct because the two principles of the Rules of Procedure for Proceedings Related to Professional Conduct are confidentiality of proceedings and fair process to the member and candidate.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>2. Fundamental Asset Managers claims compliance with the CFA Institute Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS ) and manages both discretionary and non-discretionary accounts. When constructing a single composite for Fundamental, Juma Dzuya includes all discretionary, fee-paying accounts with both value and growth strategies. Does the composite constructed by Dzuya most likely meet GIPS criteria?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Yes</choice>

		<choice id="B">No, because of non-similar investment strategies</choice>

		<choice id="C">No, because non-discretionary accounts are not included</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Introduction to the Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS®),&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 173 Study Session 1-3-b Explain the construction and purpose of composites in performance reporting. B is correct because a composite must include all actual, fee-paying, discretionary portfolios managed in accordance with the same investment mandate, objective, or strategy (Standards IV Composites). By including both value and growth portfolios, the composite is made up of portfolios with different investment mandates or strategies. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>3. Adira Badawi, CFA, who owns a research and consulting company, is an independent board member of a leading cement manufacturer in a small local market. Because of Badawi&apos;s expertise in the cement industry, a foreign cement manufacturer looking to enter the local market has hired him to undertake a feasibility study. Under what circumstances can Badawi most likely undertake the assignment without violating the CFA Institute Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct? If he:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">makes full disclosure to both companies.</choice>

		<choice id="B">receives written permission from the local company.</choice>

		<choice id="C">signs confidentiality agreements with both companies.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Guidance for Standards I—VII,&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 123-125 Study Session 1-2-c Recommend practices and procedures designed to prevent violations of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct. A is correct because making full and fair disclosure of all matters that could reasonably be expected to impair one&apos;s independence and objectivity or interfere with respective duties to one&apos;s clients is required by Standard VI Conflicts of Interest of the CFA Institute Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>4. Noor Mawar, CFA, manages a trust fund with the beneficiary being an orphaned 18-year-old student. The investment policy dictates that trust assets are expected to provide the student with a stable low risk source of income until she reaches the age of 30 years. Based on information from an internet blog, the student asks Mawar to invest in a new business venture she expects will provide high returns over the next 5 years. Mawar ignores the request, instead securing conservative investments to provide sufficient income. Did Mawar most likely violate the CFA Institute Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Yes</choice>

		<choice id="B">No, because the client&apos;s objectives were met</choice>

		<choice id="C">No, because the investment time frame does not match the investment horizon</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Guidance for Standards I—VII,&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 78—80 Study Session 1-2-b Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. B is correct because the client is the trust/trustees, not the beneficiary. Mawar followed Standard III (C) Suitability by managing the trust assets in a way that would likely result in a By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. stable source of income while keeping the risk profile Iow, thereby complying with the investment objectives of the trust.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>5. Vishal Chandarana, an unemployed research analyst, recently registered for the CFA Level I exam. After two months of intense interviewing, he accepts a job with a stock brokerage company in a different region of the country. Chandarana posts on a social media blog how being a CFA candidate really helped him get a job. He also notes how relieved he was when his new employer didn&apos;t ask him about being fired from his former employer. Which CFA Institute Code of Ethics or Standards of Professional Conduct did Chandarana least likely violate?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Misconduct</choice>

		<choice id="B">Loyalty to Employers</choice>

		<choice id="C">Reference to the CFA Program</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Guidance for Standards I-VII,&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 46-47, 90-91, 144-146 Study Session 1-2-a, b Demonstrate and explain the application of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. C is correct because there is no evidence Chandarana violated Standard VII (B) with regard to his being a CFA candidate. Specifically, Chandarana does not overstate his competency or imply he will achieve superior performance as a result of his CFA designation. It does appear Chandarana did not act with integrity when he hid information that could potentially harm his new employer&apos;s reputation, thus violating Standard I (D) Professionalism (Misconduct) and Standard IV (A) Duty to Employers (Loyalty).</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>6. Kam Bergeron, CFA, is an equity portfolio manager who often takes time off in the afternoon to play golf with important clients. Today, Bergeron is on the golf course when his game is interrupted by a phone call from his office. The call is from Bergeron&apos;s assistant, who notifies him of a steep and accelerating market decline. Bergeron, eager to get back to his golf game, tells his assistant to raise cash by selling 15% of all clients&apos; holdings. Bergeron instructs his assistant to first sell the most liquid stocks in each client&apos;s portfolio and then do the same for his personal account. Bergeron is least likely to be in violation of which of the CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Suitability</choice>

		<choice id="B">Priority of transactions</choice>

		<choice id="C">Diligence and reasonable basis</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. CFA institute Standards 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 78-79, 107-108, 131 Study Session 1-2-b Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. B is correct, as there is no indication a violation of Standard Vi (B) Priority of Transactions occurred. The Standard concerns transactions for clients having priority over employees&apos; transactions and is not applicable in this case because the manager gives instructions to sell his personal holdings after those of his clients. 7. ileana Inkster, CFA, was recently offered a senior management position within the trust department at a regional bank. The department is new, but the bank has plans to expand it significantly over the next few months. Inkster has been told she will be expected to help grow the client base of the trust department. She is informed the trust department plans to conduct educational seminars and pursue the attendees as new clients. Inkster notices recent seminar advertisements prepared by the bank&apos;s marketing department do not mention investment products will be for sale at the seminar. The ads indicate attendees can &quot;learn how to immediately add $100,000 to their net worth.&quot; What should Inkster most likely do to avoid violating any CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct? A. Decline to accept the new position B. Accept the position and revise the marketing material C. Accept the position and inform senior management of inadequate compliance procedures Answer = A CFA Institute Standards 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 101-102 Study Session 1-2-c Recommend practices and procedures designed to prevent violations of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct. A is correct because the prospective supervisor&apos;s first step should be to not take the position. Accepting the position with inadequate procedures in place or improper marketing material would leave Inkster at risk of incurring a violation of the Code and Standards—Standard IV (C) Responsibilities of Supervisors. She could agree to be hired as an interim consultant with the bank in order to implement adequate procedures before taking on any supervisory role. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>8. Molly Burnett, CFA, is a portfolio manager for a fund that only invests in environmentally friendly companies. A multinational utility company recently acquired one of the fund&apos;s best performing investments, a wind power company. The wind power company&apos;s shareholders received utility company shares as part of the merger agreement. The utility has one of the worst environmental records in the industry, but its shares have been one of the top performers over the past 12 months. Because the utility pays a high dividend every three months, Burnett holds the utility shares until the remaining two dividends are paid for the year then sells the shares. Burnett most likely violated the CFA Institute Standard of Professional Conduct concerning:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">suitability.</choice>

		<choice id="B">disclosure of conflicts.</choice>

		<choice id="C">independence and objectivity.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>CFA Institute Standards 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 27-29, 78-81, 123-125 Study Session 1-2-b Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. A is correct because the utility is not a suitable investment for a fund that only invests in companies with good environmental records. Continuing to hold this investment, therefore, was a violation of Standard Ill (C) Suitability.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>9. Pia Nilsson is a sole proprietor investment advisor. The economic recession has reduced the number of clients she advises and caused revenues to decline. As a result, Nilsson has not paid her CFA Institute membership dues for the past two years. When a national financial publication recently interviewed Nilsson, she indicated that up until two years ago she had been a CFA charterholder and a CFA Institute member in good standing. In addition, she stated the completion of the CFA Program enhanced her portfolio management skills and enabled her to achieve superior returns on behalf of her clients. Which of Nilsson&apos;s following actions most likely violated the CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Nonpayment of CFA Institute membership dues</choice>

		<choice id="B">Attributing her superior returns to participation in the CFA Program</choice>

		<choice id="C">Indicating that being a CFA charterholder has enhanced her portfolio management skills</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>CFA Institute Standards 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 144-145 Study Session 1-2-b Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. B is correct because it is a violation of Standard VII (B) Responsibilities as a CFA Institute Member or CFA Candidate to claim the CFA charter helped her to achieve superior returns.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>10. Which of the following distinct entities can least likely claim compliance with the Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS)?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">A multi-national financial services holding company</choice>

		<choice id="B">An investment management division of a regional commercial bank</choice>

		<choice id="C">A locally incorporated subsidiary undertaking investment management services</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS),&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 184 Study Session 2-4-b Describe the scope of the GIPS standards with respect to an investment firm&apos;s definition and historical performance record. A is correct because the Global Investment Performance Standards require that firms be defined as an investment firm, subsidiary, or division held out to clients or prospective clients as a distinct business entity (0.A.12). A multi-national financial services holding company is unlikely to be solely operating as an investment firm, and the scope of the business could also make it more difficult to claim compliance on a firm-wide basis.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>11. For periods beginning on or after 1 January 2011, the aggregate fair value of total firm assets most likely includes all:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">fee-paying discretionary accounts.</choice>

		<choice id="B">fee- and non-fee-paying discretionary accounts.</choice>

		<choice id="C">fee- and non-fee-paying discretionary and non-discretionary accounts.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS),&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 184 Study Session 2-4-a Describe the key features of the GIPS standards and the fundamentals of compliance. C is correct because for periods beginning on or after 1 January 2011, total firm assets must include the aggregate fair value of all discretionary and non-discretionary assets managed by the firm. This includes both fee-paying and non-fee-paying portfolios (0.A.13). By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 12. in countries where new local laws relating to calculation and presentation of investment performance conflict with GiPS standards, firms who have claimed GiPS compliance should most likely: A. stop claiming GiPS compliance. B. follow local laws, continue to claim GiPS compliance, and disclose conflicts. C. continue to claim GiPS compliance, disclosing non-compliance with new laws. Answer = B &quot;Global investment Performance Standards (GiPS),&quot; CFA institute 2012 Modular Level i, Vol. 1, p. 180 Study Session 2-4-c Explain how the GiPS standards are implemented in countries with existing standards for performance reporting, and describe the appropriate response when the GiPS standards and local regulations conflict. B is correct because where local laws and regulations regarding calculation and presentation conflict with GiPS standards, firms must abide by the local laws and regulations. They are still allowed to claim GiPS compliance but must disclose areas where the local requirements conflict with those of the GiPS standards.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>13. Firms claiming GiPS compliance must make every reasonable effort to provide a compliant presentation to which of the following?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Existing clients</choice>

		<choice id="B">Prospective clients</choice>

		<choice id="C">Both existing and prospective clients</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Global investment Performance Standards (GiPS),&quot; CFA institute 2012 Modular Level i, Vol. 1, p. 184 Study Session 2-4-a, d Describe the key features of the GiPS standards and the fundamentals of compliance. Describe the nine major sections of the GiPS standards. B is correct because GiPS standards (0.A.9) state &quot;firms must make every reasonable effort to provide a compliant presentation to all prospective clients. As long as a prospective client has received a compliant presentation within the previous 12 months, the firm has met this requirement. it is a GiPS recommendation, not a requirement, that all clients receive a compliant presentation on an annual basis (0.B.4). By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>14. James Simone, CFA, the CFO of a publicly listed company, seeks to improve the quality of his company&apos;s communication with institutional fund managers. He holds an investor briefing with this group the evening before the company earnings are announced. The company&apos;s quarterly earnings are broadcast in a press release the next day before the market opens. The earnings information in the investor briefing is identical to that in the press release. Did Simone most likely violate the CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Yes</choice>

		<choice id="B">No, because investor briefing and press release information are identical</choice>

		<choice id="C">No, because the company releases information while the market is closed</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Guidance for Standards I—VII,&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 49-51 Study Session 1-2-b Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. A is correct because Simone violated Standard II (A) Material Nonpublic Information by giving institutional fund managers access to material nonpublic information prior to public dissemination (i.e., the press release). By releasing earnings results to a select group of institutional fund managers prior to a public press release, Simone allows the institutional fund managers a time advantage over other investors not invited to the investor briefing.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>15. Beth Kozniak, a CFA candidate, is an independent licensed real estate broker and a well-known property investor. She is currently brokering the sale of a commercial property on behalf of a client in financial distress. If the client&apos;s building is not sold within 30 days, he will lose the building to the bank. A year earlier, another client of Kozniak&apos;s had expressed interest in purchasing this same property. However, she is unable to contact this client, nor has she discovered any other potential buyers. Given her distressed client&apos;s limited time frame, Kozniak purchases the property herself and foregoes any sales commission. Six months later, she sells the property for a nice profit to the client who had earlier expressed interest in the property. Does Kozniak most likely violate the CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No</choice>

		<choice id="B">Yes, she did not disclose her potential conflicts of interest to either client.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Yes, she profited on the real estate to the detriment of her financially stressed client.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Guidance for Standards I—VII,&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 63—64, 123—125 Study Session 1-2-a Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. A is correct because Kozniak does not appear to have violated any CFA institute Standards of Professional Conduct. Because she is known in the market for investing and brokering property and both parties have worked with Kozniak in the past, both parties would know of her interests. in addition, in both cases she acts for her own account as a primary investor, not as a broker. She buys the property for her own portfolio and then sells the property from her own portfolio. Therefore, Kozniak did not violate Standard Vi (A) Disclosure of Conflicts. When she purchased the property for her portfolio, she saved her client from losing the building to the bank and did not charge a sales commission. Because the sale of the property to her other client did not take place until six months after her purchase and she was unable to contact the client who had earlier expressed interest prior to her purchase, she cannot be accused of violating any loyalty, prudence, or care to either client (Standard iii (A) Loyalty, Prudence, and Care).</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>16. Prudence Charmaine, a CFA charterholder, was recently accused in writing of cheating on a professional accounting exam. She denied cheating and successfully defended herself against the allegation. As part of her defense and as evidence of her character, Charmaine stated she is a CFA charterholder and upholds the CFA institute Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct. On her next annual Professional Conduct Statement, Charmaine does not report this allegation to CFA institute. Did Charmaine most likely violate the CFA institute Code of Ethics or Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No</choice>

		<choice id="B">Yes, she improperly used the CFA institute Code and Standards to defend herself.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Yes, she did not report the allegation on her annual Professional Conduct Statement.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct,&quot; CFA institute 2012 Modular Level i, Vol. 1, pp. 8, 15, 18 Study Session 1-1-c Explain the ethical responsibilities required by the Code and Standards, including the multiple sub-sections of each Standard. C is correct because Charmaine should have reported the cheating allegation when making her annual Professional Conduct Statement. Even though she successfully defended herself against the charges and the charges were dropped, she has a responsibility to report the written complaint involving her integrity. The Code of Ethics requires CFA charterholders to practice and encourage others to practice in a professional and ethical manner that will reflect credit on themselves and the profession. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>17. Margie Germainne, CFA, is a risk management consultant who has been asked by a small investment bank to recommend policies to prevent bank employees from front running client orders. These clients generally invest in one or more of the bank&apos;s large cap equity unit trusts. To ensure compliance with the CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct, Germainne should least likely recommend which of the following? Employees should be restricted from trading:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">equity related securities.</choice>

		<choice id="B">without prior permission.</choice>

		<choice id="C">during established time periods.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Guidance for Standards I-VII,&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 54, 131-134 Study Session 1-2-c Recommend practices and procedures designed to prevent violations of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct. A is correct because while Standard VI (B) Priority of Transactions is designed to prevent any potential conflict of interest or the appearance of a conflict of interest with respect to personal transactions, it does not ban employees from trading securities. A ban on all equity related securities could be excessively restrictive to employees and unnecessary if appropriate personal transaction policies and procedures are in place.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>18. Johannes Meir, CFA, is a compliance officer for Family Estate Planning, LLC, a private-wealth consulting firm. Many of his colleagues have family members who have started their own retail businesses. Some of Meir&apos;s colleagues have been asked by relatives to serve as non-executive directors or advisors to their companies. Meir should most likely recommend which of the following policies to ensure compliance with the CFA Institute Standards?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Prohibit employees from becoming directors or advisors</choice>

		<choice id="B">Require employees to declare all income sources annually</choice>

		<choice id="C">Require employees to declare all outside business interests</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Guidance for Standards I-VII,&quot; CFA Institute 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 99, 123-125, 136 Study Session 1-2-c Recommend practices and procedures designed to prevent violations of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct. C is correct because the Standards require the disclosure of conflicts (Standard VI (A)). For Meir to understand what potential conflicts of interest employees may have with the firm and with their clients, he would need to know the outside interests of each staff member. The staff By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. members themselves may not know enough about the company and its clients to disclose those interests that would present a potential conflict. Therefore, it may be best to have all employees declare their outside business interests on an annual basis so Meir can make the determination as to what outside business interests need to be disclosed to clients. Questions 19 through 32 relate to Quantitative Methods</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>19. If the stated annual interest rate is 20% and the frequency of compounding is monthly, the effective annual rate (EAR) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">20%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">21%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">22%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;The Time Value of Money,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 266-267 Study Session 2-5-c Calculate and interpret the effective annual rate, given the stated annual interest rate and the frequency of compounding. C is correct. The effective annual rate (EAR) is (1 + Periodic interest rate)&quot; - 1. In this case, the periodic interest rate is 0.20/12 = 0.01667 and the EAR is (1.01667)12 - 1 = 0.21939 = 22%.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>20. For a positively skewed unimodal distribution, which of the following measures is most accurately described as the largest?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Mode</choice>

		<choice id="B">Mean</choice>

		<choice id="C">Median</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 399 Study Session 2-7-j, k Explain skewness and the meaning of a positively or negatively skewed return distribution. Describe the relative locations of the mean, median, and mode for a unimodal, nonsymmetrical distribution. B is correct. For the positively skewed unimodal distribution, the mode is less than the median, which is less than the mean. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>21. A project offers the following incremental after-tax cash flows: Year 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 Cash flow (€) -12,500 2,000 4,000 5,000 2,000 1,000 500 The IRR of the project is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.4%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">4.4%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">5.5%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Discounted Cash Flow Applications,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 314-317 &quot;Capital Budgeting,&quot; John Stowe and Jacques R. Gagne 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 11-13 Study Session 2-6-a, 11-36-d Calculate and interpret the net present value (NPV) and the internal rate of return (IRR) of an investment. Calculate and interpret the results using each of the following methods to evaluate a single capital project: net present value (NPV), internal rate of return (IRR), payback period, discounted payback period, and profitability index (PI). C is correct. Enter the given cash flows into a financial calculator and solve for IRR. CF0 = -12,500, CFi = 2,000, CF2 = 4,000, CF3 = 5,000, CF4 = 2,000, CF5 = 1,000, and CF6 = 500. Compute i. The IRR is 5.46867%. Alternatively, find the NPV of the given cash flows using the three possible answers. Rate NPV 2.4% €1,065.28 4.4% €355.75 5.5% -€10.20 5.5% is closest to 0 and is thus closest to the IRR of the project.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>22. Over a four-year period, a portfolio has returns of 10%, -2%, 18%, and -12%. The geometric mean return across the period is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.9%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">3.5%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">8.1%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &quot;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 370-373 Study Session 2-7-e Calculate and interpret measures of central tendency, including the population mean, sample mean, arithmetic mean, weighted average or mean (including a portfolio return viewed as a weighted mean), geometric mean, harmonic mean, median, and mode. A is correct. The geometric mean return is calculated as [(1 + 0.10) x (1 - 0.02) x (1 + 0.18) x (1 - 0.12)]0&apos;25 - 1 = 0.0286 ~ 2.9%.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>23. The following sample of 10 items is selected from a population. The population variance is unknown. 10 20 -8 2 -9 5 0 -8 2 3 The standard error of the sample mean is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">3.4.</choice>

		<choice id="B">3.6.</choice>

		<choice id="C">10.8.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Sampling and Estimation,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 557 Study Session 3-10-f Calculate and interpret the standard error of the sample mean. A is correct. When the population variance is unknown, the standard error of the sample mean is calculated as « = A where s is the sample standard deviation and n is the size of the sample. The sample standard deviation is s = [ If=i (Xi-X) 2 + (n — 1)] 0.5 In this problem, X = (10 + 20 - 8 + 2 - 9 + 5 + 0 - 8 + 3 + 21) 4 10 = 3.6. s2 = [(10 - 3.6)2 + (20 - 3.6)2 + (-8 - 3.6)2 + (2 - 3.6)2 + (-9 - 3.6)2 + (5 - 3.6)2 + (0 - 3.6)2 + (-8 - 3.6)2 + (3 - 3.6)2 + (21 - 3.6)2] 4 9 = 117.6 and s = 10.844. The standard error of the sample mean is, therefore, 10.844 4 10a5 = 3.429. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>24. A subset of a population is best described as a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">sample.</choice>

		<choice id="B">statistic.</choice>

		<choice id="C">conditional distribution.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 343 Study Session 2-7-a, b Distinguish between descriptive statistics and inferential statistics, between a population and a sample, and among the types of measurement scales. Define a parameter, a sample statistic, and a frequency distribution. A is correct. A sample is a subset of a population.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>25. An analyst collects data relating to five commonly used measures of use of debt (leverage) and interest coverage for a randomly chosen sample of 300 firms. The data comes from those firms&apos; fiscal year 2011 annual reports. This data is best characterized as:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">time-series data.</choice>

		<choice id="B">longitudinal data.</choice>

		<choice id="C">cross-sectional data.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Sampling and Estimation,&quot; Richard A. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 553-556 Study Session 3-10-d Distinguish between time-series and cross-sectional data. C is correct. Data on some characteristics of companies at a single point in time are cross¬ sectional data.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>26. A financial contract offers to pay €1,200 per month for five years with the first payment made today. Assuming an annual discount rate of 6.5%, compounded monthly, the present value of the contract is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">€61,330.</choice>

		<choice id="B">€61,663.</choice>

		<choice id="C">€63,731.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &quot;The Time Value of Money,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 274-278 Study Session 2-5-d, e Solve time value of money problems for different frequencies of compounding. Calculate and interpret the future value (FV) and present value (PV) of a single sum of money, an ordinary annuity, an annuity due, a perpetuity (PV only), and a series of unequal cash flows. B is correct. Enter the following into a financial calculator: number of periods (5 x 12), N = 60; the discount rate, I/Y = (6.5/12) = 0.54166667; payment, PMT = 1,200. Calculate the present value, PV, using &quot;Begin&quot; mode because this is an annuity due (the first payment is to be made immediately). The solution is 61,662.62. Two alternate approaches are also available. 1) Find the PV of an ordinary annuity of 59 periods (60,462.62) and add 1,200 (the time zero first payment) to that value. 2) Find the PV of a 60-period ordinary annuity and multiply that value by one plus the monthly periodic interest rate (1.0054166667).</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>27. A two-tailed t-test of the null hypothesis that the population mean differs from zero has a p- value of 0.0275. Using a significance level of 5%, the most appropriate conclusion is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">reject the null hypothesis.</choice>

		<choice id="B">accept the null hypothesis.</choice>

		<choice id="C">the chosen significance level is too high.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Hypothesis Testing,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 599-600 Study Session 3-11-e Explain and interpret the p-value as it relates to hypothesis testing. A is correct. The p-value is the smallest level of significance at which the null hypothesis can be rejected. In this case, the given p-value is less than the given level of significance and we reject the null hypothesis. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>28. An analyst collects the following data related to paired observations for Sample A and Sample B. Assume that both samples are drawn from normally distributed populations and that the population variances are not known. Paired Observation Sample A Value Sample B Value 1 25 18 2 12 9 3 -5 -8 4 6 3 5 -8 1 The t-statistic to test the hypothesis that the mean difference is equal to zero is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A"></choice>

		<choice id="B"> An analyst collects the following data related to paired observations for Sample A and Sample B. Assume that both samples are drawn from normally distributed populations and that the population variances are not known. Paired Observation Sample A Value Sample B Value 1 25 18 2 12 9 3 -5 -8 4 6 3 5 -8 1 The t-statistic to test the hypothesis that the mean difference is equal to zero is closest to: A. 0.23. B. 0.27.</choice>

		<choice id="C">0.52.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Hypothesis Testing,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 612-616 Study Session 3-11-h Identify the appropriate test statistic and interpret the results for a hypothesis test concerning the mean difference of two normally distributed populations. C is correct. First, calculate the mean difference: Then, calculate the sample variance and the standard error of the mean difference: 2 Z(di-d)2 Sd = —-i- n — 1 sd Sd Then, calculate the t-statistic: t d M-dO^d In this case, the mean difference is 1.4. The sample variance is 36.8. The standard error of the mean difference is 2.712932. The t-statistic is 0.51605. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Paired Observation Sample A Value Sample B Value Differences Differences Minus the Mean Difference, Then Squared 1 25 18 7 (7 - 1.4)2 = 31.36 2 12 9 3 (3 - 1.4)2 = 2.56 3 -5 -8 3 (3 - 1.4)2 = 2.56 4 6 3 3 (3 - 1.4)2 = 2.56 5 -8 1 -9 (-9 - 1.4)2 = 108.16 Sum = 7 7 4 5 = Mean of 1.4 Sum of squared differences = 147.2 Sample variance: 147.2 4 4 = 36.8 Standard error: 2.712932 = V36.8 ^ 5 t-Statistic: 0.51605 = (1.4 - 0) 4 2.712932</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>29. An investor deposits £2,000 into an account that pays continuously compounded interest of 6% (nominal annual rate). The value of the account at the end of four years is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">£2,525.</choice>

		<choice id="B">£2,542.</choice>

		<choice id="C">£2,854.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;The Time Value of Money,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle &quot;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 265-266, 524-525 Study Session 2-5-d, e, 3-9-p Solve time value of money problems for different frequencies of compounding. Calculate and interpret the future value (FV) and present value (PV) of a single sum of money, an ordinary annuity, an annuity due, a perpetuity (PV only), and a series of unequal cash flows. Distinguish between discretely and continuously compounded rates of return, and calculate and interpret a continuously compounded rate of return, given a specific holding period return. B is correct. The future value of a given lump sum, calculated using continuous compounding, is FV = PV x ert. In this case, 2000 x e&apos;06x4 = 2,542.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>30. A graphic depiction of a continuous distribution that shows the left tail to be longer than the right tail is best described as having:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">lepto-kurtosis.</choice>

		<choice id="B">positive skewness.</choice>

		<choice id="C">negative skewness. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 401 Study Session 2-7-j Explain skewness and the meaning of a positively or negatively skewed return distribution. C is correct. A negatively skewed distribution appears as if the left tail has been pulled away from the mean.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>31. When an analyst is unsure of the underlying population distribution, which of the following is least likely to increase the reliability of parameter estimates?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Increase in the sample size</choice>

		<choice id="B">Use of point estimates rather than confidence intervals</choice>

		<choice id="C">Use of the t-distribution rather than the normal distribution to establish confidence intervals</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Sampling and Estimation,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 562-566 Study Session 3-10-h, i Distinguish between a point estimate and a confidence interval estimate of a population parameter. Describe the properties of Student&apos;s t-distribution and calculate and interpret its degrees of freedom. B is correct. Point estimates are not as reliable as confidence interval estimates. A conservative approach to confidence intervals relies on the t-distribution rather than the normal distribution, and use of the t-distribution will increase the reliability of the confidence interval. Increasing the sample size increases the reliability of the confidence interval. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>32. Consider the following 20 items. -41 -18 -17 -9 -8 -6 -5 3 3 3 5 5 7 7 11 12 20 21 21 61 The median value of the items is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">3.</choice>

		<choice id="B">4.</choice>

		<choice id="C">5.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&quot; Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 362 Study Session 2-7-e Calculate and interpret measures of central tendency, including the population mean, sample mean, arithmetic mean, weighted average or mean (including a portfolio return viewed as a weighted mean), geometric mean, harmonic mean, median, and mode. B is correct. &quot;The median is the value of the middle item of a set of items. . . . In an even sample, we define the median as the mean of the values of items occupying the n/2 and positions&quot; (p. 362). The n/2 item is the 10th item, and the (n +2)/2 item is the 11th item. the 10th item is 3; the value of the 11th item is 5. The mean of 3 and 5 is 4. Questions 33 through 44 relate to Economics</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>33. Demand for a good is most likely to be more elastic when:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">the good is a necessity.</choice>

		<choice id="B">a lesser proportion of income is spent on the good.</choice>

		<choice id="C">the adjustment to a price change takes a longer time.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Demand and Supply Analysis: Introduction,&quot; Richard V. Eastin and Gary L. Arbogast 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 48-49 Study Session 4-13-m Calculate and interpret price, income, and cross-price elasticities of demand, including factors that affect each measure. C is correct. The longer the time that has elapsed since a price change, the more elastic demand is. For example, if gas prices rise, consumers cannot quickly change their mode of transportation By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. -numbered (n +2)/2 The value of but will likely do so in the longer run.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>34. A local laundry and dry cleaner collects the following data on its workforce productivity, Workers always work in teams of two, and the laundry earns $3.00 of revenue for each shirt laundered. Quantity of Labor (L) (Workers) Total Product (TP) (Shirts Laundered per Hour) 0 0 2 20 4 36 6 50 8 62 The marginal revenue product ($ per worker) for hiring the fifth and sixth workers is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">14.</choice>

		<choice id="B">21.</choice>

		<choice id="C">42.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Demand and Supply Analysis: The Firm,&quot; Gary L. Arbogast and 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 138, 144-145 Study Session 4-15-b, j, k Calculate and interpret total, average, and marginal revenue. Calculate and interpret total, marginal, and average product of Describe the phenomenon of diminishing marginal returns and profit-maximizing utilization level of an input. B is correct. The marginal product (MP) is the amount of additional output resulting from using one more unit of input: ATP/AL, where ATP is the change in total product and AL is the change in total labor. The marginal revenue product (MRP) is the marginal product of an input times the price of the product: MP x Price = ATP/AL x Price. In this problem, the marginal product of hiring the 5th and 6th workers (AL = 2) is 14 shirts per hour/2 workers = 7 shirts per hour/worker. With each shirt resulting in $3 of revenue, the MRP is 7 shirts per hour/worker x $3/shirt = $21 per worker.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>35. First degree price discrimination is best described as pricing that allows producers to increase their economic profit while consumer surplus:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increases.</choice>

		<choice id="B">decreases.</choice>

		<choice id="C">is eliminated.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Richard V. Eastin labor. calculate and interpret the &quot;The Firm and Market Structures,&quot; Richard G. Fritz and Michele Gambera 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 196-197 Study Session 4-16-d, e Describe and determine the profit-maximizing price and output for firms under each market structure. Explain the effects of demand changes, entry and exit of firms, and other factors on long-run equilibrium under each market structure. C is correct. In the first degree price discrimination, the entire consumer surplus is captured by the producer: The consumer surplus falls to zero.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>36. Which of the following actions on the part of a central bank is most consistent with increasing the quantity of money?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Increasing reserve requirements</choice>

		<choice id="B">Selling securities on the open market</choice>

		<choice id="C">Purchasing securities on the open market</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Monetary and Fiscal Policy,&quot; Andrew Clare and Stephen Thomas 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 378-379 Study Session 5-19-f, i Describe the implementation of monetary policy. Determine whether a monetary policy is expansionary or contractionary. C is correct. When a central bank purchases securities, bank reserves increase. The banks thus have excess reserves and are able to increase their lending, increasing the money supply.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>37. If a government increases its spending on domestically produced goods by an amount that is financed by the same increase in taxes, the aggregate demand will most likely:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increase.</choice>

		<choice id="B">decrease.</choice>

		<choice id="C">remain unchanged.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Monetary and Fiscal Policy,&quot; Andrew Clare and Stephen Thomas 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 410-411 Study Session 5-19-l, n, o Describe the tools of fiscal policy, including their advantages and disadvantages. Explain the implementation of fiscal policy and the difficulties of implementation. Determine whether a fiscal policy is expansionary or contractionary. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. A is correct. Aggregate demand rises when the government increases spending by the same amount as it raises taxes because the marginal propensity to spend out of disposable income is less than 1, and hence for every dollar less in disposable income, spending only falls by c (where c is the marginal propensity to consume in dollars). Aggregate spending will fall less than the tax rise by a factor c. This additional output will, in turn, lead to further increases in income and output through the multiplier effect.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>38. In early 2011, a New Zealand traveler returned from Singapore with SGD7,500 (Singapore dollars). A foreign exchange dealer provided the traveler with the following quotes: Ratio Spot Rates USD/SGD 1.2600 NZD/USD 0.7670 USD: U.S. Dollar The amount of New Zealand dollars (NZD) that the traveler would receive for his Singapore dollars is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">4,565.</choice>

		<choice id="B">7,248.</choice>

		<choice id="C">7,761. Answer = B</choice>

		<choice id="D"></choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Currency Exchange Rates,&quot; William A. Barker, Paul D. McNelis, and Jerry Nickelsburg 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 521-525 Study Session 6-21-e Calculate and interpret currency cross-rates. B is correct. The NZD/SGD cross-rate is NZD/USD x USD/SGD = 0.7670 x 1.26 = 0.9664. The traveler will receive 0.9664 NZD per SGD; 0.9664 NZD/SGD x 7,500 SGD = 7,248 NZD. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 39. in a simple economy with no foreign sector, the following equations apply: Consumption function C = 2,500 + 0.80 x (Y - T) Investment function I = 500 + 0.30 x Y - 25 x r Government spending G = 1,000 Tax function T = -250 + 0.30 x Y Y: Aggregate income r: Real interest rate If the real interest rate is 3% and government spending increases to 2,000, the increase in aggregate income will be closest to: A. 1,000. B. 1,163. C. 7,143. Answer = C &quot;Aggregate Output, Prices, and Economic Growth,&quot; Paul R. Kutasovic and Richard G. Fritz 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 232-240 Study Session 5-17-f Explain the IS and LM curves and how they combine to generate the aggregate demand curve. C is correct. With no foreign sector, the GDP identity is Y = C + I + G. With substitution from the equations above, Y = 2,500 + 0.80 x (Y - T) + 500 + 0.30 x Y - 25 x r + 1,000 = 2,500 + 0.80 x (Y +250 - 0.30 x Y) + 500 + 0.30 x Y - 25 x r + 1,000. Y = 4,200 + 0.86 x Y - 25 x r. Y = 30,000 - 178.6 x r. At 3%, Y = 30,000 - 178.6 x 3 = 29,464. Alternatively, Y - 0.86Y = 4,200 - 25 x r 0.14Y = 4,200 - 256 x r. If government spending increased by 1,000 to 2,000, then Y = 5,200 + 0.86 x Y - 25 x r. Y = 37,142 - 178.6 x r, which at 3% would be Y = 37,142 - 178.6 x 3 = 36,607. Representing an increase of 36,607 - 29,464 = 7,143. Alternatively, at 5,200, Y - 0.86Y = 5,200 - 25 x r or 0.14 Y = 5,200 - 25 x r. Or more simply, AG 4 (1 - c) = 1,000/(1 - 0.86) = 7,143. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>40. Which of the following measures of profit is most likely necessary for a firm to stay in business in the long run?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Normal</choice>

		<choice id="B">Economic</choice>

		<choice id="C">Accounting</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Demand and Supply Analysis: The Firm,&quot; Gary L. Arbogast and Richard V. Eastin 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 101-105 Study Session 4-15-a Calculate, interpret, and compare accounting profit, economic profit, normal profit, and economic rent. A is correct. Normal profit is the level of accounting profit needed to just cover the implicit opportunity costs ignored in accounting costs. This is all that a firm needs to earn in the long run to remain in business. Failing to earn normal profits over the long run has a debilitating impact on the firm&apos;s ability to access capital and to function properly as a business enterprise.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>41. A small country has a comparative advantage in the production of pencils. The government establishes an export subsidy for pencils to promote economic growth. Which of the following will be the most likely result of this policy?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">As new domestic producers enter the pencils market, supply will increase and domestic prices will decline.</choice>

		<choice id="B">The increase in the domestic producer surplus will exceed the sum of the subsidy and the decrease in the domestic consumer surplus.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Although domestic producers will receive a net benefit, the policy will give rise to inefficiencies that cause a deadweight loss to the national welfare.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;International Trade and Capital Flows,&quot; Usha Nair-Reichert and Daniel Robert Witschi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 456-457 Study Session 6-20-d Compare types of trade and capital restrictions and their economic implications. C is correct. Export subsidies interfere with the functioning of the free market and result in a deadweight loss to society. The deadweight loss arises on the producer side as the higher subsidized price causes inefficient producers to remain in the market; on the consumer side, the higher price causes those that would have purchased at the lower price to be shut out of the market. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>42. Assuming its trading partner does not retaliate, which of the following conditions must hold in order for a large country to increase its national welfare by imposing a tariff?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">It must have a comparative advantage in the production of the imported good.</choice>

		<choice id="B">The deadweight loss must be smaller than the benefit of its improving terms of trade.</choice>

		<choice id="C">It must auction the import licenses for a fee to offset the decline in the consumer surplus.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;International Trade and Capital Flows,&quot; Usha Nair-Reichert and Daniel Robert Witschi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 452-456 Study Session 6-20-d Compare types of trade and capital restrictions and their economic implications. B is correct. The large country is able to cause the foreign exporter to reduce price in order to retain market share. In the large country, domestic producers gain from higher volume and the government gains from collecting the tariff. The sum of these two gains must exceed the deadweight loss to domestic consumers to achieve a national welfare gain. The change in terms of trade causes income redistribution from the foreign exporter to the domestic producer.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>43. A country having a current account deficit most likely will still be able to consume more output than it produces by:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increasing its net foreign liabilities.</choice>

		<choice id="B">restricting foreign direct investment.</choice>

		<choice id="C">adjusting interest rates to stimulate higher domestic savings. Answer = A &quot;International Trade and Capital Flows,&quot; Usha Nair-Reichert and Daniel Robert Witschi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p. 475-476</choice>

		<choice id="D"></choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;International Trade and Capital Flows,&quot; Usha Nair-Reichert and Daniel Robert Witschi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p. 475-476 &quot;Currency Exchange Rates,&quot; William A. Barker, Paul D. McNelis, and Jerry Nickelsburg 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p. 545 Study Session 6-20-f, 6-21-j Describe the balance of payments accounts, including their components. Explain the impact of exchange rates on countries&apos; international trade and capital flows. A is correct. A current account deficit must be offset by a capital account surplus. Only by borrowing money from foreigners can a country have a current account deficit and consume more output than it produces (p. 475). An increase in net foreign liabilities is the result of borrowing from foreigners. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 44. in the classification of currency regimes, a currency board system (CBS) most likely differs from a fixed-rate parity system in that: A. a CBS has a discretionary target level of foreign exchange reserves. B. a CBS can peg to a basket of currencies but a fixed-rate system cannot. C. the monetary authority within a CBS does not act as a traditional lender of last resort. Answer = C &quot;Currency Exchange Rates,&quot; William A. Barker, Paul D. McNelis, and Jerry Nickelsburg 2012 Modular Level i, Vol. 2, pp. 539-540 Study Session 6-21-i Describe exchange rate regimes. C is correct. in a CBS, the monetary authority has an obligation to maintain 100% foreign currency reserves against the monetary base. it thus cannot lend to troubled financial institutions. As long as the country under a fixed-parity regime maintains its exchange peg, the central bank can serve as a lender of last resort. Questions 45 through 68 relate to Financial Statement Analysis</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>45. Which of the following statements is most accurate about the responsibilities of an auditor for a publicly traded firm in the United States? The auditor:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">assures the reader that the financial statements are free from error, fraud, or illegal acts.</choice>

		<choice id="B">must express an opinion about the effectiveness of the company&apos;s internal control systems.</choice>

		<choice id="C">must state that he prepared the financial statements according to generally accepted accounting principles.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Statement Analysis: An introduction,&quot; Elaine Henry and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level i, Vol. 3, pp. 28-31 Study Session 7-22-d Describe the objective of audits of financial statements, the types of audit reports, and the importance of effective internal controls. B is correct. For a publicly traded firm in the United States, the auditor must express an opinion as to whether the company&apos;s internal control system is in accordance with the Public Company Accounting Oversight Board, under the Sarbanes-Oxley Act. This is done either as a final paragraph in the auditor&apos;s report or as a separate opinion. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 46. in accrual accounting, if an adjusting entry results in the reduction of an asset and the recording of an expense, the originating entry recorded was most likely a(n): A. prepaid expense. B. accrued expense. C. deferred revenue. Answer = A &quot;Financial Reporting Mechanics,&quot; Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, Karen O&apos;Connor Rubsam, Elaine Henry, and Michael A. Broihahn 2012 Modular Level i, Vol. 3, pp. 71-73 Study Session 7-23-d Explain the need for accruals and other adjustments in preparing financial statements. A is correct. The adjusting entry to record the expiry of a prepaid expense is the reduction of an asset (the prepaid) and the recognition of the expense.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>47. At the beginning of the year, a company had total shareholders&apos; equity consisting of ¥200,000 in common share capital and ¥50,000 in retained earnings. During the year, the following events occurred: ¥ Net income reported 42,000 Dividends paid 7,000 Unrealized loss on available-for-sale investments 3,000 Repurchase of company stock, to be held as Treasury stock 6,000 The total shareholders&apos; equity at the end of the year is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">¥276,000.</choice>

		<choice id="B">¥279,000.</choice>

		<choice id="C">¥282,000.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Understanding Balance Sheets,&quot; Elaine Henry and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level i, Vol. 3, pp. 241-244, 247-250 Study Session 8-26-e, f, g Describe different types of assets and liabilities and the measurement bases of each. Describe the components of shareholders&apos; equity. Analyze balance sheets and statements of changes in equity. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. A is correct Shareholders&apos; Equity (¥) Start-of-year share capital 200,000 Less Treasury stock (6,000) Beginning retained earnings 50,000 Plus net income 42,000 Less dividends paid (7.000) Ending retained earnings 85,000 85,000 Accumulated other comprehensive income Unrealized loss on available-for-sale investments (3,000) End-of-year shareholders&apos; equity 276,000</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>48. Selected information from a company&apos;s comparative income statements and balance sheets is presented below. Selected Income Statement Data for the year ended August 31st (US$ thousands) 2011 2010 Sales revenue $100,000 $ 95,000 Cost of goods sold 47,000 47,500 Depreciation expense 4,000 3,500 Net income $ 11,122 $ 4,556 Selected Balance Sheet Data as of August 31st (US$ thousands) Current Assets 2011 2010 Cash &amp; investments $ 21,122 $ 25,000 Accounts receivable 25,000 13,500 Inventories 13,000 8,500 Total current assets $ 59,122 $ 47,000 Current Liabilities Accounts payable $ 15,000 $ 15,000 Other current liabilities 7,000 9,000 Total current liabilities $ 22,000 $ 24,000 The cash collected from customers in 2011 is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$88,500.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$96,100.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$111,500. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Understanding Cash Flow Statements,&quot; Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, and Michael A. Broihahn 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 291-292 Study Session 8-27-e, f Describe how the cash flow statement is linked to the income statement and the balance sheet. Describe the steps in the preparation of direct and indirect cash flow statements, including how cash flows can be computed using income statement and balance sheet data. A is correct. Cash collected from customers = Revenues - Increase in accounts receivable = $100 - (25 - 13.5) = 88.5. 49. Selected information for a company and the common size data for its industry are provided below. Company (£) Common Size Industry Data (% of sales) EBIT 76,000 28.0 Pretax profit 66,400 19.6 Net income 44,500 13.1 Sales 400,000 100.0 Total assets 524,488 140.0 Total equity 296,488 74.0 ROE 15.0% 17.7% Which of the following is most likely a contributor to the company&apos;s inferior ROE compared to that of the industry? The company&apos;s: A. tax burden ratio. B. interest burden ratio. C. financial leverage ratio. Answer = C &quot;Financial Analysis Techniques,&quot; Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik van Greuning 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 374-379 Study Session 8-28-c, d, &quot;Financial Statement Analysis,&quot; Pamela Peterson Drake 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 213-215 Study Session 11-41 Describe the relationships among ratios and evaluate a company using ratio analysis. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Demonstrate the application of the DuPont analysis of the return on equity, and calculate and interpret the effect of changes in its components. C is correct. Calculation Company Industry Tax burden ratio Net Inc/EBT 44,500/66,400 = 0.67 13.1/19.6 = 0.67 Financial leverage Total assets/Equity 524,488/296,488 = 1.77 140/74 = 1.89 Interest burden ratio EBT/EBIT 66,400/76,000 = 0.87 19.6/28.0 = 0.70 The company has a lower financial leverage ratio relative to the industry, which is one of the causes of the company&apos;s lower relative ROE performance. The tax burden ratio is the same as the industry and the interest burden ratio is higher, which would increase ROE. EBT: Pretax profit (earnings before tax) Net Inc: Net income</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>50. Which of the following is least likely to be a general feature underlying the preparation of financial statements within the IFRS Conceptual Framework?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Matching</choice>

		<choice id="B">Materiality</choice>

		<choice id="C">Accrual basis</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Reporting Standards,&quot; Elaine Henry, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 128-129 &quot;Understanding Income Statements,&quot; Elaine Henry and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 171 Study Session 7-24-e, 8-25-d Describe general requirements for financial statements under IFRS. Describe the general principles of expense recognition, specific expense recognition applications, and the implications of expense recognition choices for financial analysis. A is correct. The IFRS Conceptual Framework specifies a number of general features underlying the preparation of financial statements, including materiality and accrual basis. Matching is not one of those general features; it is a general principle of expense recognition.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>51. A company suffered a substantial loss when its production facility was destroyed in an earthquake against which it was not insured. Geological scientists were surprised by the earthquake as there was no evidence that one had ever occurred in that area in the past. Which of the following statements is most accurate? The company should report the loss on its income statement:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">net of taxes if it reports under U.S. GAAP.</choice>

		<choice id="B">as an extraordinary item if it reports under IFRS.</choice>

		<choice id="C">as an unusual item if it reports under U.S. GAAP. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Understanding Income Statements,&quot; Elaine Henry and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 182-183 Study Session 8-25-e Describe the financial reporting treatment and analysis of non-recurring items (including discontinued operations, extraordinary items, and unusual or infrequent items) and changes in accounting standards. A is correct. To qualify as an extraordinary item, an item must be both unusual in nature and infrequent in occurrence: The description of the earthquake meets these criteria. Extraordinary items are only allowed under U.S. GAAP and are reported on the income statement net of tax.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>52. The following information is available about a company: (all figures in $ thousands) 2011 2010 Deferred tax assets 200 160 Deferred tax liabilities (450) (360) Net deferred tax liabilities (250) (200) Earnings before taxes 4,000 3,800 Income taxes at the statutory rate 1,200 1,140 Current income tax expense 1,000 900 The company&apos;s 2011 income tax expense (in thousands) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$1,000.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$1,050.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$1,250.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Income Taxes,&quot; Elbie Antonites and Michael A. Broihahn 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 491-493, 512-517 Study Session 9-31-d, i Calculate income tax expense, income taxes payable, deferred tax assets, and deferred tax liabilities, and calculate and interpret the adjustment to the financial statements related to a change in the income tax rate. Analyze disclosures relating to deferred tax items and the effective tax rate reconciliation, and explain how information included in these disclosures affects a company&apos;s financial statements and financial ratios. B is correct. Income tax expense reported on the income statement = Income tax payable + Net changes in the deferred tax assets and deferred tax liabilities. The change in the net deferred tax liability is a $50 increase (indicating that the income tax expense is $50 in excess of the income By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. tax payable [or current income tax expense] and representing an increase in the expense). Therefore, the income tax expense = 1,000 + 50 = 1,050, 53, Which of the following inventory valuation methods best matches the actual historical cost of the inventory items to their physical flow? A, FIFO B, LIFO C, Specific identification Answer = C &quot;Inventories,&quot; Michael A, Broihahn 2012 Modular Level I, Vol, 3, p, 411 Study Session 9-29-b Describe different inventory valuation methods (cost formulas), C is correct, Specific identification best matches the physical flow of the inventory items because it tracks the actual units that are sold, 54, A company has announced that it is going to distribute a group of long-lived assets to its owners in a spin-off, The most appropriate way to account for the assets until the distribution occurs is to classify them as: A, held for sale with no depreciation taken, B, held for use until disposal with no deprecation taken, C, held for use until disposal with depreciation continuing to be taken, Answer = C &quot;Long-Lived Assets,&quot; Elaine Henry and Elizabeth A, Gordon 2012 Modular Level I, Vol, 3, pp, 467, 480 Study Session 9-30-i Explain the derecognition of property, plant and equipment, and intangible assets, C is correct, Long-lived assets that will be disposed of other than by sale, such as a spin-off, an exchange for other assets, or abandonment, are classified as held for use until disposal and continue to be depreciated until that time, By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>55. The following information is available from a company&apos;s 2011 financial statements: Note 6: Employee costs (in thousands) 2011 2010 Wages and salaries $21,000 $18,500 Share-based payment costs 600 425 Defined contribution pension plan 1,525 1,462 Retirement benefit obligations (note 17) 728 620 Other employee costs 3,233 3,080 Total employee costs $27,086 $24,087 Note 17: Retirement benefit obligations Amounts recognized in the income statement for the year (in thousands) 2011 2010 Current service cost $ 692 $ 588 Interest cost on pension obligation 80 65 Expected return on plan assets (50) (45) Past service costs recognized in the year 6 12 Total income statement charge $ 728 $ 620 The pension expense (in thousands) reported in 2011 is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$1,525.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$2,217.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$2,253.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Non-Current (Long-Term) Liabilities,&quot; Elizabeth A. Gordon and Elaine Henry 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 570-573 Study Session 9-32-j, k Describe defined contribution and defined benefit pension plans. Compare the presentation and disclosure of defined contribution and defined benefit pension plans. C is correct. The pension expense would be the sum of the expense for the defined contribution plan and the defined benefit plan (retirement benefit obligation): 1,525 + 728 = 2,253.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>56. An analyst is assessing a company&apos;s quality of earnings by looking at the cash flow earnings index (operating cash flow divided by net income). Potential problems would most likely be indicated if the ratio were consistently:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">equal to 1.0.</choice>

		<choice id="B">less than 1.0.</choice>

		<choice id="C">greater than 1.0. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Reporting Quality: Red Flags and Accounting Warning Signs,&quot; Thomas R. Robinson and Paul Munter 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 594 Study Session 10-33-d Describe common accounting warning signs and methods for detecting each. B is correct. A cash flow earnings index consistently below 1.0 could indicate potential problems in a company&apos;s quality of earnings.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>57. A retail company that leases the majority of its space has: • total assets of $4,500 million, • total long-term debt of $2,125 million, and • average interest rate on debt of 12%. Note 8 to the 2011 financial statements contains the following information about the company&apos;s future beginning of year lease commitments: Note 8: Operating leases Year Millions 2012 $ 200 2013 200 2014 200 2015 200 2016 200 Total $ 1,000 After adjustment for the off-balance-sheet financing, the debt-to-total-assets ratio for the company is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">55%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">57%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">65%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Non-Current (Long-Term) Liabilities,&quot; Elizabeth A. Gordon and Elaine Henry 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 574 &quot;Financial Statement Analysis: Applications,&quot; Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and Michael A. Broihahn 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 652-658 Study Session 9-32-l, 10-35-e Calculate and interpret leverage and coverage ratios. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Explain appropriate analyst adjustments to a company&apos;s financial statements to facilitate comparison with another company. A is correct. The present value of the operating leases should be added to both the total debt and the total assets. The present value of an annuity due of $200 for 5 years at 12% = $807.5. (N = 5; I = 12; PMT = 200; Mode = Begin) Adjusted debt to total assets = (2,125 + 807.5) 4 (4,500 + 807.5) = 55.3%.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>58. The financial statement that would be most helpful to an analyst in understanding the changes that have occurred in a company&apos;s retained earnings over a year is the statement of:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">changes in equity.</choice>

		<choice id="B">financial position.</choice>

		<choice id="C">comprehensive income.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Statement Analysis: An Introduction,&quot; Elaine Henry and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 21-22 Study Session 7-22-b Describe the roles of the key financial statements (statement of financial position, statement of comprehensive income, statement of changes in equity, and statement of cash flows) in evaluating a company&apos;s performance and position. A is correct. The statement of changes in equity reports the changes in the components of shareholders&apos; equity over the year, which would include the retained earnings account.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>59. Under the IASB Conceptual Framework, one of the qualitative characteristics of useful financial information is that different knowledgeable users would agree that the information is a faithful representation of the economic events that it is intended to represent. This characteristic is best described as:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">verifiability.</choice>

		<choice id="B">comparability.</choice>

		<choice id="C">understandability.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Reporting Standards,&quot; Elaine Henry, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 123 Study Session 7-24-d Describe the International Accounting Standards Board&apos;s Conceptual Framework, including the objective and qualitative characteristics of financial statements, required reporting elements, and constraints and assumptions in preparing financial statements. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. A is correct. Under the international Accounting Standards Board&apos;s Conceptual Framework, verifiability is the qualitative characteristic that means that different knowledgeable and independent users would agree that the information presented faithfully represents the economic events that it is intended to represent.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>60. Under U.S. GAAP, interest paid is most likely included in which of the following cash flow activities?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Operating only</choice>

		<choice id="B">Financing only</choice>

		<choice id="C">Either operating or financing</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Understanding Cash Flow Statements,&quot; Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, and Michael A. Broihahn 2012 Modular Level i, Vol. 3, pp. 273-276 Study Session 8-27-a, c Compare cash flows from operating, investing, and financing activities, and classify cash flow items as relating to one of those three categories given a description of the items. Contrast cash flow statements prepared under international Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) and U.S generally accepted accounting principles (U.S. GAAP). A is correct. interest paid must be categorized as an operating cash flow activity under U.S. GAAP, although it can be categorized as either an operating or financing cash flow activity under IFRS.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>61. The following information is available: Income Statement Items ($) Sales 421,000 Cost of goods sold (COGS) 315,000 Balance Sheet Items Cash 30,000 Accounts receivable 40,000 inventories 36,000 Accounts payable 33,000 The company&apos;s cash conversion cycle (in days) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">38.2.</choice>

		<choice id="B">45.2.</choice>

		<choice id="C">76.4. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Analysis Techniques,&quot; Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik van Greuning 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 351-352, 356, 359-362 &quot;Working Capital Management,&quot; Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela Peterson Drake 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 163-167 Study Session 8-28-b, 11-40-c Classify, calculate, and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios. Evaluate working capital effectiveness of a company, based on its operating and cash conversion cycles, and compare the company&apos;s effectiveness with that of peer companies. A is correct. Cash conversion cycle = DOH + DSO - Days of payables Formula Calculation Days DOH: Days of inventory on hand 365 365 41.7 Inventory turnover 8.75 Inventory turnover = COGS Inventory 315,000 = 8.75 36,000 DSO: Days of sales outstanding 365 365 34.7 Receivables turnover 10.53 Receivables turnover = Sales 421,000 1 r\ co Accts receivable = 10.53 40,000 Number of days of payables: 365 365 -38.2 Payables turnover 9.55 Payables turnover = COGS* Accts payable 315,000 = 9 55 33,000 . * When purchases are not available (as in this case), the COGS can be used to estimate payables turnover (p. 356). Cash conversion cycle 38.2 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>62. An analyst has calculated the following ratios for a company: Operating Profit Margin 17.5% Net Profit Margin 11.7% Total Asset Turnover 0.89 times Return on Assets 10.4% Financial Leverage 1.46 Debt to Equity 0.46 The company&apos;s return on equity (ROE) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">4.8%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">15.2%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">22.7%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Analysis Techniques,&quot; Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik van Greuning 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 374-375 Study Session 8-28-d Demonstrate the application of the DuPont analysis of return on equity, and calculate and interpret the effects of changes in its components. B is correct. Using DuPont analysis, there are two ways to calculate ROE from the information provided: ROE = Net profit margin x Asset turnover x Financial leverage 11.7 x 0.89 x 1.46 ROE = ROA x Financial leverage 10.4 x 1.46</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>63. According to International Financial Reporting Standards, which of the following conditions should be satisfied in order to report revenue on the income statement?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Payment has been received.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Costs can be reliably measured.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Goods have been delivered to the customer.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Understanding Income Statements,&quot; Elaine Henry and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 158-159 Study Session 8-25-b Describe the general principles of revenue recognition and accrual accounting, specific revenue recognition applications (including accounting for long-term contracts, installment sales, barter transactions, and gross and net reporting of revenue), and the implications of revenue recognition principles for financial analysis. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 15.2 15.2 B is correct. The IFRS conditions that should be met include that the costs incurred can be reliably measured, and it is likely that the economic benefits will flow to the entity, not the actual receipt of any payment, and that the significant risks and rewards of ownership have been transferred, which is normally when the goods have been delivered, but not always.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>64. A company entered into a three-year construction project with a total contract price of $10.6 million and an expected total cost of $8.8 million. The following table provides cash flow information relating to the contract: All figures in millions Year 1 Year 2 Year 3 Costs incurred and paid $1.2 $6.0 $1.6 Amounts billed and payments received $2.4 $5.6 $2.6 If the company uses the percentage-of-completion method, the amount of revenue recognized (in millions) in Year 2 is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$3.5.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$5.6.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$7.2.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Understanding Income Statements,&quot; Elaine Henry and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 162-164 Study Session 8-25-b Describe the general principles of revenue recognition and accrual accounting, specific revenue recognition applications (including accounting for long-term contracts, installment sales, barter transactions, and gross and net reporting of revenue), and the implications of revenue recognition principles for financial analysis. C is correct. The revenue reported is equal to the percentage of the contract that is completed in that period, where percentage completion is based on costs. In Year 2: (6.0 4- 8.8) x 10.6 = 7.2. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>65. A company recently purchased a warehouse property and related equipment (shelving, forklifts, etc.) for €50 million, which were valued by an appraiser as follows: Land €10 million, building €35 million, and equipment €5 million. The company incurred the following additional costs in getting the warehouse ready to use: • €2.0 million for repairs to the building&apos;s roof and windows • €0.5 million to modify the interior layout to meet their needs (moving walls and doors, inserting and removing partitions, etc.) • €0.1 million on an orientation and training session for employees to familiarize them with the facility The cost to be capitalized to the building account (in millions) for accounting purposes is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">€37.0.</choice>

		<choice id="B">€37.5.</choice>

		<choice id="C">€38.5.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Long-Lived Assets,&quot; Elaine Henry and Elizabeth A. Gordon 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 444-446 Study Session 9-30-a Distinguish between costs that are capitalized and costs that are expensed in the period in which they are incurred. B is correct. The capitalized cost of the building would include the other costs that are directly attributable to the building and are involved in extending its life or getting it ready to use: Initial cost Repairs to roof and windows Modifications to interiors Total cost €35.00 2.00 0.50 €37.5 million By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>66. On 1 January 2009, a company that prepares its financial statements according to IFRS issued bonds with the following features: • Face value £20,000,000 • Term 5 years • Coupon rate 6% paid annually on December 31 • Market rate at issue 4% The company did not elect to carry the bonds at fair value. In December 2011 the market rate on similar bonds had increased to 5% and the company decided to buy back (retire) the bonds after the coupon payment on December 31. As a result, the gain on retirement reported on the 2011 statement of income is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">£340,410.</choice>

		<choice id="B">£371,882.</choice>

		<choice id="C">£382,556.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Non-Current (Long-Term) Liabilities,&quot; Elizabeth A. Gordon and Elaine Henry 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 537, 539-540, 544 Study Session 9-32-c Explain the derecognition of debt. C is correct. Gain = Book value of debt - Market value both at time of retirement, calculations 20,754,438 - 20,371,882 = 382,556 below The market value of debt at retirement can be determined by discounting the future cash flows at the current market rate (5%) using a financial calculator: FV = 20,000,000; i = 5%; PMT = 1,200,000; N = 2; Compute PV = 20,371,882 The book value after the third interest payment (two payments remaining) can be found either using a financial calculator and the market rate at the time of issue (4%) or an amortization table (shown below). FV = 20,000,000; i = 4%; PMT = 1,200,000; N = 2; Compute PV = 20,754,438. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. The bond&apos;s initial value (required for amortization) can be found using a financial calculator: FV = 20,000,000; i = 4%; PMT = 1,200,000; N = 5; Compute PV = 21,780,729. Interest Principal value at expense Discount beginning of year 4% Coupon 6% amortization 2009 21,780,729 871,229 1,200,000 328,771 2010 21,451,958 858,078 1,200,000 341,922 2011 21,110,036 844,401 1,200,000 355,599 Book value at end of 2011 20,754,438</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>67. Providing information about the performance of a company, its financial position, and changes in financial position that is useful to a wide range of users is most accurately described as the role of:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">financial reporting.</choice>

		<choice id="B">the auditor&apos;s report.</choice>

		<choice id="C">financial statement analysis.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Statement Analysis: An Introduction,&quot; Elaine Henry and Thomas R. Robinson 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 6-7, 28-29 Study Session 7-22-a, d Describe the roles of financial reporting and financial statement analysis. Describe the objective of audits of financial statements, the types of audit reports, and the importance of effective internal controls. A is correct. The role of financial reporting is to provide information about the performance of a company, its financial position, and changes in financial position that is useful to a wide range of users in making economic decisions.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>68. Which of the following is most likely a reason that a lessor can offer attractive lease terms and lower cost financing to a lessee? Because the:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">lessor retains the tax benefits of ownership.</choice>

		<choice id="B">lessor avoids reporting the liability on its balance sheet.</choice>

		<choice id="C">lessee is better able to resell the asset at the end of the lease.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Non-Current (Long-Term) Liabilities,&quot; Elizabeth A. Gordon and Elaine Henry 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 551-552 Study Session 9-32-f Explain the motivations for leasing assets instead of purchasing them. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. A is correct. The lessor often retains the tax benefits of ownership of the leased asset, which allows the lessor to pass those savings along to the lessee in the form of lower financing costs or other attractive terms. Questions 69 through 78 relate to Corporate Finance</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>69. When computing the cash flows for a capital project, which of the following is least likely to be included?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Tax effects</choice>

		<choice id="B">Financing costs</choice>

		<choice id="C">Opportunity costs Answer = B</choice>

		<choice id="D"></choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Capital Budgeting,&quot; John D. Stowe and Jacques R. Gagne 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 8 Study Session 11-36-b Describe the basic principles of capital budgeting, including cash flow estimation. B is correct. Financing costs are not included in a cash flow calculation but are considered in the calculation of the discount rate.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>70. A company has an equity beta of 1.4 and is 60% funded with debt. Assuming a tax rate of 35%, the company&apos;s asset beta is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">0.71.</choice>

		<choice id="B">0.98.</choice>

		<choice id="C">1.01.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Cost of Capital,&quot; Yves Courtois, Gene C. Lai, and Pamela Peterson Drake 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 60-61 Study Session 11-37-i Calculate and interpret the beta and cost of capital for a project. A is correct. Note: 60% debt financing is equivalent to a D/E ratio of 1.50 = 0.60/(1 - 0.60). Posset = Peq x [1 * (1 + [1 - t] D/E) )] = 1.4 * (1 + (1 - 0.35) x 1.5) = 0.7089. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>71. A company&apos;s taxable income is 17.1% of sales. Assuming taxes of 42% and a dividend payout of 50%, the net profit margin is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">5.0%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">7.2%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">9.9%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Financial Statement Analysis,&quot; Pamela Peterson Drake 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 217-225 Study Session 11-41 The candidate should be able to demonstrate the use of pro forma income and balance sheet statements. C is correct. Net profit margin = Net income 4 Sales = [Earnings before tax x (1 - Tax rate)] 4 Sales _ (0.171 x Sales) x (1-0.42) Sales = 0.171 x (1 - 0.42) = 9.92%.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>72. A project has the following annual cash flows: Year 0 Year 1 Year 2 Year 3 Year 4 -$75,000 $21,600 $23,328 $37,791 $40,815 With a discount rate of 8%, the discounted payback period (in years) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.8.</choice>

		<choice id="B">3.0.</choice>

		<choice id="C">3.2. Answer = C</choice>

		<choice id="D"></choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Capital Budgeting,&quot; John D. Stowe and Jacques R. Gagne 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 15 Study Session 11-36-d Calculate and interpret the results using each of the following methods to evaluate a single capital project: net present value (NPV), internal rate of return (IRR), payback period, discounted payback period, and profitability index (PI). By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. C is correct. Year Cash Flow PV (Cash Flow) @ 8% CF„ 4 (1.08)n Amount to Pay Back [CF0 - Cumulative PV cash flows] 0 -75,000 -75,000 75,000 1 21,600 20,000 55,000 2 23,328 * 20,000 35,000 3 37,791 30,000 5,000 4 40,814 30,000 The first three cash flows recover $70,000 (in present value terms) of the cost, making only $5,000 of the $30,000 in Year 4 necessary to completely recover the cost. Therefore, the discounted payback is 3.2 years. * For example, the PV of Year 2&apos;s cash flow is $23,328 4 [1.08]2.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>73. Using the company&apos;s income statement presented, its degree of operating leverage is closest to: Income Statement $ millions Revenues 9.8 Variable Operating Costs 7.2 Fixed Operating Costs 1.5 Operating Income 1.1 Interest 0.6 Taxable Income 0.5 Tax 0.2 Net Income 0.3	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">1.1.</choice>

		<choice id="B">1.7.</choice>

		<choice id="C">2.4.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Measures of Leverage,&quot; Pamela Peterson Drake, Raj Aggarwal, Cynthia Harrington, and Adam Kobor 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 97-99 Study Session 11-38-b Calculate and interpret the degree of operating leverage, the degree of financial leverage, and the degree of total leverage. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. C is correct, DOL = (Revenues - Variable operating costs) (Revenues - Variable operating costs - Fixed operating costs) 9.8-7.2 9.8-7.2-1.5 = 2,36, 74, Based on best practices in corporate governance procedures, it is most appropriate for a company&apos;s compensation committee to: A, include a retired executive from the firm, B, link compensation with long-term objectives, C, include a representative from the firm&apos;s external auditor, Answer = B &quot;The Corporate Governance of Listed Companies: A Manual for Investors,&quot; Kurt Schacht, James C, Allen, and Matthew Orsagh 2012 Modular Level I, Vol, 4, pp, 250-253 Study Session 11-42-e Describe the responsibilities of the audit, compensation, and nominations committees and identify factors an investor should consider when evaluating the quality of each committee, B is correct, Under appropriate corporate governance procedures, the compensation committee should link compensation with long-term objectives, 75, The following information is available for a company: • Bonds are priced at par and they have an annual coupon rate of 9,2% • Preferred stock is priced at $8,18 and it pays an annual dividend of $1,35 • Common equity has a beta of 1,3 • The risk-free rate is 4% and the market premium is 11% • Capital structure: Debt = 30%; Preferred stock = 15%; Common equity = 55% • The tax rate is 35% The weighted average cost of capital (WACC) for the company is closest to: A, 11,5%, B, 13,4%, C, 14,3%, Answer = C &quot;Cost of Capital,&quot; Yves Courtois, Gene C, Lai, and Pamela Peterson Drake 2012 Modular Level I, Vol, 4, pp, 41, 47-52 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &quot;Portfolio Risk and Return: Part II,&quot; Vijay Singal 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 418 Study Session 11-37-a, b, 12-45-g Calculate and interpret the weighted average cost of capital (WACC) of a company. Describe how taxes affect the cost of capital from different capital sources. Calculate and interpret the expected return of an asset using the CAPM. C is correct. rd = 9.2%, the yield to maturity on a par value bond is the coupon rate of the bond. Dv $1.35 r- = 7f = mi = 16&apos;5% re = RF + /3[E(Rm) - RF] = 4% + 1.3[11%] = 18.3% WACC = wdrd(1 - t) + wprp + were WACC = 30% x 9.2% x (1 - 35%) + 15% x 16.5% + 55% x 18.3% = 14.33%</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>76. Financial risk is most likely affected by:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">dividends.</choice>

		<choice id="B">long-term leases.</choice>

		<choice id="C">general and administrative costs.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Measures of Leverage,&quot; Pamela Peterson Drake, Raj Aggarwal, Cynthia Harrington, and Adam Kobor 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 103 Study Session 11-38-a Define and explain leverage, business risk, sales risk, operating risk, and financial risk, and classify a risk, given a description. B is correct. As stated on p. 103, &quot;By taking on fixed obligations, such as debt and long-term leases, the company increases its financial risk.&quot; By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>77. The following information is available for a firm; Number of shares outstanding 4 million Tax rate 40% Cost of debt (pretax) 10% Current stock price $20.00 Net income $6 million A plan to repurchase $10 million worth of shares using debt will most likely cause the earnings per share to;	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increase.</choice>

		<choice id="B">decrease.</choice>

		<choice id="C">remain unchanged.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Cost of Capital,&quot; Yves Courtois, Gene C. Lai, and Pamela Peterson Drake 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 40-43 &quot;Dividends and Share Repurchases; Basics,&quot; George Troughton and Gregory Noronha 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 142-143 Study Session 11-37-b, 11-39-d Describe how taxes affect the cost of capital from different capital sources. Calculate and compare the effects of a share repurchase on earnings per share when 1) the repurchase is financed with the company&apos;s excess cash and 2) the company uses funded debt to finance the repurchase. A is correct. Long way; Current earnings per share = $6,000,000 ^4,000,000 = $1.50 Number of shares repurchased = $10,000,000 ^ $20.00 = 500,000 shares Adjusted net income = Current net income — [debt x &quot;after tax&quot; cost of debt] = $6,000,000 — [$10,000,000 x 10% x (1 — 40%)] = $5,400,000 New earnings per share = $5,400,000 ^ [4,000,000 — 500,000] = $1.54 Short way; Current earnings per share = $6,000,000 ^4,000,000 = $1.50 Earnings yield = $1.50 ^ $20.00 = 7.5% If the after-tax cost of debt (10% x [1 - 40%] = 6%) is below the earnings yield, the earnings per share will increase. This can be derived from Example 7 on p. 142. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>78. A 30-day $10,000 U.S. Treasury bill sells for $9,932.40. The discount-basis yield (%) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">8.11.</choice>

		<choice id="B">8.17.</choice>

		<choice id="C">8.28.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Working Capital Management,&quot; Edgar Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela Peterson Drake 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 174 Study Session 11-40-e Calculate and interpret comparable yields on various securities, compare portfolio returns against a standard benchmark, and evaluate a company&apos;s short-term investment policy guidelines. A is correct. Note: The face value is greater than the purchase price because the T-bill sells at a discount. Face value — Purchase price DBY = -r-i---X&apos; Face value 360 Days to maturity $10,000 — $9,932.40 360 DBY = -„__ X — = 8.112% $10,000 30 Questions 79 through 90 relate to Equity Investments</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>79. A stop-buy order is most likely placed when a trader:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">thinks that the stock is overvalued.</choice>

		<choice id="B">wants to limit the loss on a long position.</choice>

		<choice id="C">wants to limit the loss on a short position.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Market Organization and Structure,&quot; Larry Harris 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 51-53 Study Session 13-47-g, h Compare execution, validity, and clearing instructions. Compare market orders with limit orders. C is correct. Investors who have entered into a short sale will incur losses if the stock begins to increase in value. A stop-buy order helps limit the loss on a short position because it becomes valid when the stock price rises above the specified stop price. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>80. The type of voting in board elections that is most beneficial to shareholders with a small number of shares is best described as:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">statutory voting.</choice>

		<choice id="B">voting by proxy.</choice>

		<choice id="C">cumulative voting.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;The Corporate Governance of Listed Companies: A Manual for Investors,&quot; Kurt Schacht, James C. Allen, and Matthew Orsagh 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 263-266 &quot;Overview of Equity Securities,&quot; Ryan C. Fuhrmann and Asjeet S. Lamba 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 171 Study Session 11-42-g, 14-50-b Evaluate, from a shareowner&apos;s perspective, company policies related to voting rules, shareowner-sponsored proposals, common stock classes, and takeover defenses. Describe differences in voting rights and other ownership characteristics among different equity classes. C is correct. Cumulative voting allows shareholders to direct their total voting rights to specific candidates, as opposed to having to allocate their voting rights evenly among all candidates. Thus, applying all of the votes to one candidate provides the opportunity for a higher level of representation on the board than would be allowed under statutory voting.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>81. An investor gathered the following data in order to estimate the value of the company&apos;s preferred stock: Par value of preferred stock offered at a 6% dividend rate $100 Company&apos;s sustainable growth rate 5% Yield on comparable preferred stock issues 11.5% Investor&apos;s marginal tax rate 30% The value of the company&apos;s preferred stock is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$52.17.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$74.53.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$96.92.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Equity Valuation: Concepts and Basic Tools,&quot; 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 276-277 Study Session 14-52-d Calculate the intrinsic value of a non-callable, John J. Nagorniak and Stephen E. Wilcox non-convertible preferred stock. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. A is correct. ,, „ , $100 X0.06 V0 = D0/r = -- u u/ rt i -i r $52.17.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>82. An investor gathers the following data. Year Earnings per share ($) Dividends per share ($) ROE 2011 3.20 1.92 12% 2010 3.60 1.80 17% 2009 2.44 1.71 13% 2008 2.50 1.60 15% To estimate the stock&apos;s justified forward P/E, the investor prefers to use the compounded annual earnings growth and the average of the payout ratios over the relevant period (i.e., 2008-2011). If the investor uses 11.5% as her required rate of return, the stock&apos;s justified forward P/E is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">10.</choice>

		<choice id="B">12.</choice>

		<choice id="C">21.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Equity Valuation: Concepts and Basic Tools,&quot; John J. Nagorniak and Stephen E. Wilcox 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 276, 281, 289-291 Study Session 14-52-h Calculate and interpret the following multiples: price to earnings, price to an estimate of operating cash flow, price to sales, and price to book value. C is correct. P0/E1 = p/(r - g) Earnings growth rate (g) over the period 2008-2011 = 2.50(1 + g)3 = 3.20; g = 8.6%. Payout ratio (p) computation (for example, 2011) = 1.92/3.20 = 0.60. Average payout ratio = (0.60 + 0.50 + 0.70 + 0.64)/4 = 0.61. P0/E i = p/(r - g) = 0.61/(0.115 - 0.086) = 0.61/0.029 = 21.0. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>83. An investor evaluating a company&apos;s common stock for investment has gathered the following data. Earnings per share (2012) $2.50 Dividend payout ratio (2012) 60% Dividend growth rate expected during Years 2013 and 2014 25% Dividend growth rate expected after Year 2014 5% Investors&apos; required rate of return 12% Using the two-stage dividend discount model, the value per share of this common stock in 2012 is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$28.57.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$31.57.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$38.70.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Equity Valuation: Concepts and Basic Tools,&quot; John J. Nagorniak and Stephen E. Wilcox 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 284-286 Study Session 14-52-e Calculate and interpret the intrinsic value of an equity security based on the Gordon (constant) growth dividend discount model or a two-stage dividend discount model, as appropriate. B is correct. Dividend per share (2012) = $2.50 (0.6) = $1.50. ^2012 — 1.50(1.25) + 1.50(1.25)2 + 1.50(1.25)2 (1.05) x 1 1.12 1.122 (0.12-0.05) X 1.122 = $1.67 + $1.87 + $28.03 = $31.57.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>84. Which of the following is least likely to be directly reflected in the returns on a commodity index?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Roll yield</choice>

		<choice id="B">Changes in the spot prices of underlying commodities</choice>

		<choice id="C">Changes in the futures prices of commodities in the index Answer = B</choice>

		<choice id="D"></choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Security Market Indices,&quot; Paul D. Kaplan and Dorothy C. Kelly 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 109-110 Study Session 13-48-j Discuss indices representing alternative investments. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. B is correct. Commodity index returns reflect the changes in future prices and the roll yield. Changes in the underlying commodity spot prices are not reflected in a commodity index.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>85. A trader who has bought a stock at $30 is concerned about a downside movement in the stock and would like to place an order that guarantees selling it at $25. Which of the following will most likely help the trader achieve her objective? (GTC = Good-till-cancelled)	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">&quot;GTC, stop 25, market sell&quot; order</choice>

		<choice id="B">&quot;GTC, stop 25, limit 25 sell&quot; order</choice>

		<choice id="C">&quot;put option buy&quot; market order with a strike price of 25</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Market Organization and Structure,&quot; Larry E. Harris 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 51-52 &quot;Option Markets and Contracts,&quot; Don M. Chance 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 82-85 Study Session 13-47-g, h, 17-63-a Compare execution, validity, and clearing instructions. Compare market orders with limit orders. Describe call and put options. C is correct. Option contracts can be viewed as limit orders for which execution is guaranteed at the strike price. Therefore, a &quot;put buy&quot; order at a strike price of 25 will guarantee selling the stock at 25.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>86. A trader who buys a stock priced at $64 on margin with a leverage ratio of 2.5 and a maintenance margin of 30% will most likely receive a margin call when the stock price is at or falls just below:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$36.57.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$44.80.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$54.86.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Market Organization and Structure,&quot; Larry E. Harris 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 43-46 Study Session 13-47-f Calculate and interpret the leverage ratio, the rate of return on a margin transaction, and the security price at which the investor would receive a margin call. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. C is correct. 1 1 — = 0.4; Initial equity = $64 x 0.4 = $25.60 Equity = Leverage ratio 2.5 Critical &quot;P&quot; for margin call = Equity Price $25.60 + P — $64 = 30%; P = $54.86 share share P Alternate solution: Debit balance 64 x 0.6 1 — maintenance margin % 1 — 0.3 = $54.86 87, Compared to its market-value-weighted counterpart, a fundamentally weighted index will least likely have a: A, value tilt, B, contrarian &quot;effect,&quot; C, momentum &quot;effect,&quot; Answer = C &quot;Security Market Indices,&quot; Paul D, Kaplan and Dorothy C, Kelly 2012 Modular Level I, Vol, 5, p, 98 Study Session 13-48-d Compare the different weighting methods used in index construction, C is correct, Momentum &quot;effect&quot; is a characteristic of a market-value-weighted index, not a fundamentally weighted index, 88, A U.S. institutional money manager prefers to invest in depository instruments of non-domestic equity securities that are privately placed in the U,S, and not subject to the foreign ownership and capital flow restrictions, The type of security that is most appropriate for this investor is: A, global registered shares, B, global depository receipts, C, American depository shares, Answer = B &quot;Overview of Equity Securities,&quot; Ryan C, Fuhrmann and Asjeet S, Lamba 2012 Modular Level I, Vol, 5, pp, 182-184 Study Session 14-50-c, d Distinguish between public and private equity securities, Describe methods for investing in non-domestic equity securities, By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. B is correct. Global depository receipts (GDRs) meet the investor preferences. They are not subject to the foreign ownership and capital flow restrictions that may be imposed by the issuing company&apos;s home country because they are sold outside of that country. GDRs cannot be listed on U.S. exchanges, but they can be privately placed with the institutional investors based in the United States.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>89. An equity analyst follows two industries with the following characteristics. Industry 1: A few companies with proprietary technologies; products with unique features; high switching costs; and minimal regulatory influences. Industry 2: A few companies producing relatively similar products; sales varying with disposable income and employment levels; high capital costs and investment in physical plants; rapid shifts in market shares of competing firms; and minimal regulatory influences. Based on the above information, the analyst will most appropriately conclude that compared to the firms in Industry 2, those in Industry 1 would potentially have:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">larger economic profits.</choice>

		<choice id="B">over-capacity problems.</choice>

		<choice id="C">high bargaining power of customers.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Introduction to Industry and Company Analysis,&quot; Patrick W. Dorsey, Anthony M. Fiore, and Ian Rossa O&apos;Reilly 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 208, 223-233 Study Session 14-51-e, h, i Describe the elements that need to be covered in a thorough industry analysis. Explain effects of industry concentration, ease of entry, and capacity on return on invested capital and pricing power. Describe the principles of strategic analysis of an industry. A is correct. The economic profit (the spread between the return on invested capital and the cost of capital) tends to be larger in industries with differentiated products, greater pricing power, and high switching costs to customers. Industry 1 has these features. Firms in Industry 2, on the other hand, have little pricing power (undifferentiated products and rapid shifts in market shares indicating intense rivalry), which is indicative of potentially smaller economic profits. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>90. The Gordon growth model is most appropriate for valuing the common stock of a dividend¬ paying company that is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">young and just entering the growth phase.</choice>

		<choice id="B">experiencing a higher than the sustainable growth rate.</choice>

		<choice id="C">mature and relatively insensitive to the economic fluctuations.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Equity Valuation: Concepts and Basic Tools,&quot; John J. Nagorniak and Stephen E. Wilcox 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 279, 285 Study Session 14-52-f Identify companies for which the constant growth or a multistage dividend discount model is appropriate. C is correct. The Gordon growth model is most appropriate for valuing common stock of a dividend-paying company that is mature and relatively insensitive to the business cycle or economic fluctuations. Questions 91 through 96 relate to Derivative Investments</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>91. Which of the following is least likely one of main purposes of derivative markets?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Reveal prices and volatility of the underlying assets</choice>

		<choice id="B">Improve market efficiency by lowering transaction costs</choice>

		<choice id="C">Enable companies to more easily practice risk management</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Derivative Markets and Instruments,&quot; Don M. Chance 2011 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 18-21 Study Session 17-60-c Describe the purposes and criticisms of derivative markets. B is correct because derivative markets improve market efficiency for the underlying assets by increasing market fairness and competitiveness, not by lowering transaction costs. Low transactions costs are a characteristic of derivative markets, not one of their purposes.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>92. A futures trader takes a long position of 10 contracts. The initial margin requirement is $10 per contract and the maintenance margin requirement is $7 per contract. She deposits the required initial margin on the trade date. On Day 3, her margin account balance is $40. What is the variation margin on Day 4?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$30</choice>

		<choice id="B">$60</choice>

		<choice id="C">$70 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Futures Markets and Contracts,&quot; Don M. Chance 2011 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 55-59 Study Session 17-62-c Distinguish between margin in the securities markets and margin in the futures markets, and explain the role of initial margin, maintenance margin, variation margin, and settlement in futures trading. B is correct because on any day when the balance in the margin account falls below the maintenance margin, the trader must deposit sufficient funds to bring the balance back up to the initial margin requirement. This additional amount is called the &quot;variation margin.&quot; Therefore, $100 - $40 = $60 variation margin.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>93. A portfolio manager enters into an equity swap with a swap dealer. The portfolio manager agrees to pay the return on the Value index and receive the return on the Growth index. The swap&apos;s notional principal is $50 million and the payments will be made semi-annually. The levels of the equity indices are as follows: Index Level at Start of Swap Level 6 Months Later Value Index 5,460 5,350 Growth Index 1,190 1,200 The net amount due to the portfolio manager after 6 months is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$587,158.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$1,007,326.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$1,427,494.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Swap Markets and Contracts,&quot; Don M. Chance 2011 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 144-147 Study Session 17-64-b Describe, calculate, and interpret the payment of currency swaps, plain vanilla interest rate swaps, and equity swaps. C is correct because the portfolio manager pays the Value index return, which had a loss, and receives the Growth index, which had a gain during the period. Therefore, the portfolio manager will receive a cash flow from the swap dealer. Value index payment = ((5350/5460) - 1) x $50,000,000 = -$1,007,326. Growth index payment = ((1200/1190) - 1) x $50,000,000 = $420,168. Net payment to portfolio manager = $420,168 - (-$1,007,326) = $1,427,494. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>94. Epsilon Inc., a U.S. based company, must pay ¥1,000,000,000 to its Japanese component supplier in 3 months. Epsilon approaches a dealer and enters into a USD/JPY currency forward contract, containing a stipulation for physical delivery, to manage the foreign exchange risk associated with the payment to its supplier. Which of these best describes Epsilon&apos;s currency forward contract?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">The dealer will deliver yen on expiration.</choice>

		<choice id="B">The amount of USD exchanged for JPY is determined at expiration.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Epsilon may receive or pay JPY, depending on the exchange rate at expiration. Answer = A &quot;Forward Markets and Contracts,&quot; Don M. Chance 2011 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 43-44 Study Session 17-61-h Describe the characteristics of currency forward contracts. A is correct because this currency forward contract requires physical delivery; therefore, Epsilon</choice>

		<choice id="D"></choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Forward Markets and Contracts,&quot; Don M. Chance 2011 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 43-44 Study Session 17-61-h Describe the characteristics of currency forward contracts. A is correct because this currency forward contract requires physical delivery; therefore, Epsilon receives 1,000,000,000 JPY from the dealer in exchange for paying USD.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>95. The greater of either zero or the present value of the exercise price minus the underlying price is most likely the lower bound on the price of a(n):	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">European put option.</choice>

		<choice id="B">American put option.</choice>

		<choice id="C">American call option.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Option Markets and Contracts,&quot; Don M. Chance 2011 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 103-107 Study Session 17-63-k Calculate and interpret the lowest prices of European and American calls and puts based on the rules for minimum values and lower bounds. A is correct because, for a European put, the exercise price must be adjusted to the present value because the option can only be exercised on expiration.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>96. An investor purchases ABC stock at $71 per share and executes a protective put strategy. The put option used in the strategy has a strike price of $66, expires in two months, and is purchased for $1.45. At expiration, the protective put strategy breaks even when the price of ABC is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$64.55.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$67.45.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$72.45. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Risk Management Applications of Option Strategies,&quot; Don M. Chance 2011 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 172-175 Study Session 17-65-b Determine the value at expiration, profit, maximum profit, maximum loss, break-even underlying price at expiration, and payoff graph of a covered call strategy and a protective put strategy, and explain the risk management application of each strategy. C is correct because to break even, the underlying stock must be at least as high as the amount expended up front to establish the position. To establish the protective put, the investor would have spent $71 + $1.45 = $72.45. Questions 97 through 108 relate to Fixed Income Investments</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>97. The table below provides a history of a fixed income security&apos;s coupon rate and the risk free rate over a five-year period. Year Risk Free Rate Coupon Rate 1 3.00% 6.00% 2 3.50% 5.00% 3 4.25% 3.50% 4 3.70% 4.60% 5 3.25% 5.50% The security is most likely a(n):	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">step-up note.</choice>

		<choice id="B">inverse floater.</choice>

		<choice id="C">deferred coupon bond.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Features of Debt Securities,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 325-330 Study Session 15-53-b Describe the basic features of a bond, the various coupon rate structures, and the structure of floating-rate securities. B is correct because the security&apos;s coupon rate moves in the opposite direction (inversely) with the risk free rate. (Specifically: Coupon rate = 12.00% - 2 x Risk free rate.) By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 98. For a 10-year floating-rate security, if market interest rates change by 1%, the change in the value of the security will most likely be: A. zero. B. related to the security&apos;s coupon reset frequency. C. similar to an otherwise identical fixed-rate security. Answer = B &quot;Risks Associated with Investing in Bonds,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 356-357 Study Session 15-54-e Explain the interest rate risk of a floating-rate security and why its price may differ from par value. B is correct because the interest rate sensitivity of a floating-rate security comes primarily from the time remaining until its next coupon reset.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>99. When a bank creates a collateralized loan obligation (CLO) to divest of commercial loans that it owns, the process is best described as a(n):	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">arbitrage transaction.</choice>

		<choice id="B">balance sheet transaction.</choice>

		<choice id="C">capital infusion transaction.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Overview of Bond Sectors and Instruments,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 426-427 Study Session 15-55-j Describe collateralized debt obligations. B is correct because a balance sheet transaction is one that removes assets from the balance sheet of the institution and is often motivated by the desire to reduce the institution&apos;s risk.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>100. Which of the following is closest to the value of a 10-year, 6% coupon, $100 par value bond with semi-annual payments assuming an annual discount rate of 7%?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$92.89</choice>

		<choice id="B">$99.07</choice>

		<choice id="C">$107.44</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Introduction to the Valuation of Debt Securities,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 496-498 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Study Session 16-57-c Calculate the value of a bond (coupon and zero coupon). A is correct because a security with 19 semi-annual payments of $3 interest and a 20th payment of $103 (interest plus return of face value) with a semi-annual discount rate of 3.5% is $92.89 or 1.03 51 1.03 52 1.03 53 1.03 54 1.03 55 1.03 56 1.03 57 1.03 58 3 3 3 3 3 3 3 1.0359 1.03510 1.03511 1.03512 1.03513 1.03514 1.0351 103 1.03516 1.03517 1.03518 1.03519 1.0352 = 92.89.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>101. Consider a $100 par value bond with a 7% coupon paid annually and 5 years to maturity. At a discount rate of 6.5%, the value of the bond today is $102.08. One day later, the discount rate rises to 7.5%. Assuming the discount rate remains at 7.5% over the remaining life of the bond, what is most likely to occur to the price of the bond between today and maturity?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Increases then decreases</choice>

		<choice id="B">Decreases then increases</choice>

		<choice id="C">Decreases then remains unchanged</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Introduction to the Valuation of Debt Securities,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 492-495 Study Session 16-57-d Explain how the price of a bond changes if the discount rate changes and as the bond approaches its maturity date. B is correct because if the discount rate rises to 7.5% from 6.5%, the price of a bond decreases. At a discount rate of 7.5%, the bond sells at a discount to face value. As a discount bond approaches maturity, it will increase in price over time until it reaches par at maturity.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>102. A fixed income security&apos;s current price is 101.45. You estimate that the price will rise to 103.28 if interest rates decrease 0.25% and fall to 100.81 if interest rates increase 0.25%. The security&apos;s effective duration is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">1.22.</choice>

		<choice id="B">4.87.</choice>

		<choice id="C">9.74.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Introduction to the Measurement of Interest Rate Risk,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 620-621 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Study Session 16-59-d Calculate and interpret the effective duration of a bond, given information about how the bond&apos;s price will increase and decrease for given changes in interest rates. B is correct because the effective duration equals (Price if rates fall - Price if rates rise)/(2 x Current price x Change in rates) = (103.28 - 100.81)/(2 x 101.45 x 0.0025) = 4.87.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>103. An analyst reviews a corporate bond indenture that contains these two covenants: 1) The borrower will pay interest semi-annually and principal at maturity. 2) The borrower will not incur additional debt if its debt/capital ratio is more than 50%. What types of covenants are these?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Both are affirmative covenants.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Covenant 1 is negative and Covenant 2 is affirmative.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Covenant 1 is affirmative and Covenant 2 is negative.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Features of Debt Securities,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 323 Study Session 15-53-a Explain the purposes of a bond&apos;s indenture and describe affirmative and negative covenants. C is correct because to pay interest and principal is one of the most common affirmative covenants. Negative covenants set forth certain limitations and restrictions on the borrower&apos;s activities. The more common restrictive covenants are those that impose limitations on the borrower&apos;s ability to incur additional debt unless certain tests are satisfied, such as a debt/capital ratio.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>104. An investor sells a bond at the quoted price of $98.00. In addition he receives accrued interest of $4.40. The clean price of the bond is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">par value plus accrued interest.</choice>

		<choice id="B">accrued interest plus agreed upon bond price.</choice>

		<choice id="C">agreed upon bond price excluding accrued interest.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Features of Debt Securities,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 330 Study Session 15-53-c Define accrued interest, full price, and clean price. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. C is correct because the agreed upon bond price without accrued interest is simply referred to as the price as well as the clean price.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>105. An investor purchases a 5% coupon bond maturing in 15 years for par value. Immediately after purchase, the yield required by the market increases. The investor would then most likely have to sell the bond at:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">par.</choice>

		<choice id="B">a discount.</choice>

		<choice id="C">a premium.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Risks Associated with Investing in Bonds,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 353 Study Session 15-54-b Identify the relations among a bond&apos;s coupon rate, the yield required by the market, and the bond&apos;s price relative to par value (i.e., discount, premium, or equal to par). B is correct because the bond would sell below par or at a discount if the yield required by the market rises above the coupon rate. Because the bond initially was purchased at par, the coupon rate equals the yield required by the market. Subsequently, if yields rise above the coupon, the bond&apos;s market price would fall below par.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>106. Given two otherwise identical bonds, when interest rates rise, the price of Bond A declines more than the price of Bond B. Compared to Bond B, Bond A most likely:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A"></choice>

		<choice id="B">n the price of Bond B. Compared to Bond B, Bond A most likely: A. is callable. B. has a lower coupon.</choice>

		<choice id="C">has a shorter maturity.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Risks Associated with Investing in Bonds,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 354-355 Study Session 15-54-c Explain how a bond&apos;s maturity, coupon, embedded options, and yield level affect its interest rate risk. B is correct because the lower the coupon rate, the greater the bond&apos;s price sensitivity to changes in interest rates. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>107. A BBB-rated corporation wishes to issue debt to finance its operations at the lowest cost possible. If it decides to sell a pool of receivables into a special purpose vehicle (SPV), its primary motivation is most likely to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">allow the corporation to retain a first lien on the assets of the SPV.</choice>

		<choice id="B">segregate the assets into a bankruptcy-remote entity for bondholders.</choice>

		<choice id="C">receive a guaranty from the SPV to improve the corporation&apos;s credit rating.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Overview of Bond Sectors and Instruments,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 424-426 Study Session 15-55-i Define an asset-backed security, describe the role of a special purpose vehicle in an asset- backed security&apos;s transaction, state the motivation for a corporation to issue an asset-backed security, and describe the types of external credit enhancements for asset-backed securities. B is correct because a key motivation for a corporation to establish a special purpose vehicle (SPV) is to separate it as a legal entity. In the case of bankruptcy for the corporation, the SPV is unaffected because it is not a subsidiary of the corporation. Given this arrangement, the SPV can achieve a rating as high as AAA and borrow at lower rates than the corporation.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>108. Which of the following is least likely a tool used by the U.S. Federal Reserve Bank to directly influence the level of interest rates?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Verbal persuasion</choice>

		<choice id="B">Open market operations</choice>

		<choice id="C">Setting the rate on 30-year bonds</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Understanding Yield Spreads,&quot; Frank J. Fabozzi 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 448-449 Study Session 15-56-a Identify the interest rate policy tools available to a central bank. C is correct because the U.S. Federal Reserve Bank (Fed) uses policy tools to directly influence short-term interest rates. It only indirectly influences long-term interest rates. The market, not the Fed, sets rates on 30-year bonds. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 109 through 114 relate to Alternative Investments</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>109. Which of the following most likely trades in the secondary markets?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Open-end funds</choice>

		<choice id="B">Closed-end funds</choice>

		<choice id="C">Unit investment trusts</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Alternative Investments,&quot; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 189-190 Study Session 18-66-a Distinguish between an open-end and a closed-end fund, and explain how net asset value of a fund is calculated and the nature of fees charged by investment companies. B is correct because closed-end funds trade in the secondary markets and do not offer a redemption feature.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>110. An analyst is evaluating an investment in an apartment complex based on the following annual data: Gross potential rental income $2,100,000 Estimated vacancy and collection expenses 3% Operating expenses $1,600,000 Depreciation 300,000 Current mortgage rate 5% Financing percentage 80% Market capitalization rate 12% Cost of equity 15% Based on the income approach, the value of the investment is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$1,141,667.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$3,641,667.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$6,242,857.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Alternative Investments,&quot; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 205-207 Study Session 18-66-g Calculate the net operating income (NOI) from a real estate investment, the value of a property using the sales comparison and income approaches, and the after-tax cash flows, net present value, and yield of a real estate investment. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. B is correct because using the income approach, ($2,100,000 - .03 x $2,100,000 - $1,600,000)/0.12 = $437,000/0.12 = $3,641,667. The property is appraised based on cash flows and is independent of the financing decision. Thus, the market capitalization rate is used rather than the lending rate. Depreciation is also not deducted because it is implicitly assumed that repairs and maintenance allow the investor to keep the building in good condition.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>111. Which of the following statements regarding biases in hedge fund performance in hedge fund databases is least likely correct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Only hedge fund managers with good track records enter the database, creating a positive bias.</choice>

		<choice id="B">The correlations between asset class returns are artificially low when underlying assets trade infrequently.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Hedge fund database administrators decide which funds to include in the database to overcome self-selection bias.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Alternative Investments,&quot; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 227-229 Study Session 18-66-m Describe the performance of hedge funds and the biases present in hedge fund performance measurement, and explain the effect of survivorship bias on the reported return and risk measures for a hedge fund database. C is correct because hedge fund managers themselves, not database administrators, decide whether they want to be included in a database. Managers who have funds with an unimpressive track record will not wish to have that information exposed.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>112. A project that requires an initial investment of €5 million is expected to pay €22 million at the end of five years if it is successful. The probabilities of failure for the project are provided below: Year 1 2 3 4 5 Failure Probability 0.25 0.20 0.15 0.15 0.15 Assuming the cost of capital for the project is 16%, the project&apos;s expected net present value is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">-€3,157,000.</choice>

		<choice id="B">-€1,140,000.</choice>

		<choice id="C">€2,017,000.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Alternative Investments,&quot; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 2012 Modular Level I, VoI. 6, pp. 216-218 Study Session 18-66-1 Calculate the net present value (NPV) of a venture capital project, given the project&apos;s possible payoff and conditional failure probabilities. B is correct because you calculate the probability of success as (1 - .25) x (1 - .20) x (1 - .15) x (1 - .15) x (1 - .15) = 0.3685. Then, calculate the NPV from success as [(22,000,000/1.165) - 5,000,000] x 0.3685 = 2,017,000. The NPV of failure is -5,000,000 x (1 - .3685) = -3,157,000. The expected NPV of the project is 2,017,000 - 3,157,000 = -1,140,000.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>113. When market participants expect the spot price of a commodity to be higher in the future, the commodity market is most likely said to be in:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">contango.</choice>

		<choice id="B">full carry.</choice>

		<choice id="C">backwardation.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Investing in Commodities,&quot; Ronald G. Layard-Liesching 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 262-264 Study Session 18-67-a Explain the relationship between spot prices and expected future prices in terms of contango and backwardation. A is correct because when a commodity market is in contango, futures prices are higher than the spot price because market participants believe the spot price will be higher in the future. When spot prices are above the futures price, the market is said to be in backwardation.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>114. Which of the following is least likely a reason for discounting the value of stock in a closely held company?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Illiquidity</choice>

		<choice id="B">Marketability</choice>

		<choice id="C">Controlling interest</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Alternative Investments,&quot; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 232-233 Study Session 18-66-o Describe alternative valuation methods for closely held companies, and distinguish among the bases for the discounts and premiums for these companies. C is a correct because company control would increase the value of the closely held company or add a premium. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 115 through 120 relate to Portfolio Management</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>115. Which of the following types of institutions is most likely to have a long investment time horizon and a higher level of risk tolerance?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">A bank</choice>

		<choice id="B">An endowment</choice>

		<choice id="C">An insurance company</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Portfolio Management: An Overview,&quot; Robert M. Conroy and Alistair Byrne 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 289-296 Study Session 12-43-b Describe types of investors and distinctive characteristics and needs of each. B is correct. Endowments have a long investment time horizon and a high level of risk tolerance. (See Exhibit 14 on pp. 295-296.)</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>116. An investor&apos;s transactions in a mutual fund and the fund&apos;s returns over a four-year period are provided in the table below: Year 1 2 3 4 New investment at the beginning of the year $2,500 $1,500 $1,000 $0 Investment return for the year -20% 65% -25% 10% Withdrawal by investor at the end of the year $0 -$500 -$500 $0 Based on these data, the money-weighted return (or internal rate of return) for the investor is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.15%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">3.96%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">7.50%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Portfolio Risk and Return Part I,&quot; Vijay Singal 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 324-330 Study Session 12-44-a Calculate and interpret major return measures and describe their appropriate uses. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. B is correct. The calculations are shown below: Year 1 2 3 4 Starting balance ($) 0.00 2,000.00 5,275.00 4,206.25 New investment at the beginning of the year ($) 2,500.00 1,500.00 1,000.00 0.00 Net balance at the beginning of year ($) 2,500.00 3,500.00 6,275.00 4,206.25 Investment return for the year -20% 65% -25% 10% Investment gain (loss) ($) -500.00 2,275.00 -1,568.75 420.63 Withdrawal by investor at the end of the year ($) 0.00 -500.00 -500.00 0.00 Balance at the end of year ($) 2,000.00 5,275.00 4,206.25 4,626.88 The money-weighted return is calculated by solving for i in the equation below: nrnn -1500 _ -500 _ 500 _ 4626.88 2500 = (1 + j)1 + (1 + i)2 + (1 + i)3 + (1 + j)4 CFO = -2,500. CF1 = -1,500 (new investment at beginning of Year 2). CF2 = -500 (withdrawal of 500 at end of Year 2, -1,000 new investment at beginning Year 3). CF3 = 500 (withdrawal of 500 at end of Year 3). CF4 = 4,626.88 (balance at end of Year 4). i = .0396.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>117. Selected information about shares of two companies is provided below: Stock Standard Deviation Correlation of Returns1 Portfolio Weights Cable Incorporated 30% 0.65 68% GPTA Company 20% 32% 1 Correlation of returns between Cable Incorporated and GPTA Company The standard deviation of returns of the portfolio formed with these two stocks is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">25.04%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">26.80%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">32.85%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Portfolio Risk and Return Part I,&quot; Vijay Singal 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 355-360 Study Session 12-44-e Calculate and interpret portfolio standard deviation. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. A is correct. Portfolio standard deviation = V(0.682)(0.32) + (0.322)(0.22) + 2(0.68)(0.32)(0.65)(0.3)(0.2) = 0.2504.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>118. Risk that can be attributed to factor(s) that impact a company or industry is best described as:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">market risk.</choice>

		<choice id="B">systematic risk.</choice>

		<choice id="C">unsystematic risk.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Portfolio Risk and Return Part II,&quot; Vijay Singal 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 410-411 Study Session 12-45-c Explain systematic and nonsystematic risk, including why an investor should not expect to receive additional return for bearing nonsystematic risk. C is correct. Risk that is due to company-specific or industry-specific factors is referred to as unsystematic risk.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>119. A stock has a correlation of 0.45 with the market and a standard deviation of returns of 12.35%. If the market has a standard deviation of returns of 8.25%, then the beta of the stock is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">0.30.</choice>

		<choice id="B">0.67.</choice>

		<choice id="C">1.50.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Portfolio Risk and Return Part II,&quot; Vijay Singal 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 415-417 Study Session 12-45-e Calculate and interpret beta. B is correct. P = o2 um 0.45 x 0.1235 x 0.0825 0.08252 0.67 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently registered CFA candidates and copying, posting to any website, e-mailing, distributing, and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
</problem> 

<problem>
	<question>120. Which of the following factors is least likely to impact an individual&apos;s ability to take risk?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Time horizon</choice>

		<choice id="B">Personality type</choice>

		<choice id="C">Expected income</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&quot;Basics of Portfolio Management and Construction,&quot; Alistair Byrne and Frank E. Smuddle 2012 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 457-458 Study Session 12-46-d Distinguish between the willingness and the ability (capacity) to take risk in analyzing an investor&apos;s financial risk tolerance. B is correct. An individual&apos;s ability to take risk is impacted by such factors as time horizon and expected income. Personality type is most likely to impact an individual&apos;s willingness to take risk.</comments>
</problem>