<problems>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Questions 1-18 Relate to Ethics1. Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Members and candidates must self-disclose on the annual Professional Conduct Statement allmatters that question their professional conduct, such as involvement in civil litigation or criminalinvestigations or being the subject of a written complaint.CFA Level I"Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct"</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Selling stock short is a management strategy and does not necessarily violate any aspect of theStandards of Professional Conduct.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard II(B)–Market Manipulation</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Kozniak does not appear to have violated any CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct.Because she is known in the market for investing and brokering property and both parties haveworked with Kozniak in the past, both parties would know of her interests. In addition, in bothcases, she acts for her own account as a primary investor, not as a broker. She buys the propertyfor her own portfolio and then sells the property from her own portfolio. Therefore, Kozniak didnot violate Standard VI(A)-Disclosure of Conflicts. When she purchased the property for herportfolio, she saved her client from losing the building to the bank and did not charge a salescommission. Because the sale of the property to her other client did not take place until six monthsafter her purchase, and she was unable to contact the client who had earlier expressed interestprior to her purchase, she cannot be accused of violating Standard III(A)-Loyalty, Prudence, andCare with either client.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard III(A)-Loyalty, Prudence, and Care, Standard VI(A)-Disclosure of Conflicts</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>The portfolio manager received permission to use his investment performance history from hisprior employer. The member violated his non-solicitation agreement by indicating his availabilityto new clients on several social media sites accessible by clients of his former employer. Thisaction is a violation of Standard IV(A)-Loyalty because he did not act for the benefit of his formeremployer. In this case, the member may cause harm to his former employer if his messages resultin clients moving to his new business from his former employer. The member also violatedStandard IV(A) by taking his employer's property, the trading software.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard IV(A)-Loyalty</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The analyst has conducted thorough research that indicates the company falsified its financialresults, and she should request the company address this issue publicly as recommended byStandard II(A)–Material Nonpublic Information. If a member or candidate determines thatinformation is material, the member or candidate should make reasonable efforts to achieve publicdissemination of the information. This effort usually entails encouraging the issuer company tomake the information public. If public dissemination is not possible, the member or candidatemust communicate the information only to the designated supervisory and compliance personnelwithin the member's or candidate's firm and must not take investment action on the basis of theinformation.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard II(A)–Material Nonpublic Information</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>The member misrepresented the returns she could realistically achieve for her clients, violatingStandard I(C)-Misrepresentation, which prohibits members and candidates from guaranteeingclients any specific return on volatile investments.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard I(C)-Misrepresentation</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Miffitt has not violated Standard III (E)-Preservation of Confidentiality, which involvesinformation about former, current, and prospective clients.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard II(A)-Material Nonpublic Information, Standard II(B)-Market Manipulation, StandardIII(E)-Preservation of Confidentiality</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Under Standard IV(C)-Responsibility of Supervisors, a member should exercise reasonablesupervision by establishing and implementing compliance procedures in place prior to thepossibility of any violation occurring, which has not been done in this case.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard IV(C)-Responsibilities of Supervisors</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The GIPS standards state that firms must make every reasonable effort to provide a compliantpresentation to all prospective clients. As long as a prospective client has received a compliantpresentation within the previous 12 months, the firm has met this requirement. It is a GIPSrecommendation, not a requirement, that all clients receive a compliant presentation on an annualbasis.CFA Level I"Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS)"GIPS Requirement 0.A.9, GIPS Recommendation O.B.4</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The utility is not a suitable investment for a fund that only invests in companies with goodenvironmental records. Continuing to hold this investment, therefore, was a violation of StandardIII(C)-Suitability.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard I(B)–Independence and Objectivity, Standard III(C)-Suitability, Standard VI(A)-Disclosure of Conflicts</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Standard VI(A)-Disclosure of Conflicts requires the disclosure of conflicts. For Meir tounderstand what potential conflicts of interest employees may have with the firm and with theirclients, he would need to know the outside interests of each staff member. The staff membersthemselves may not know enough about the company and its clients to disclose those interests thatwould present a potential conflict. Therefore, it may be best to have all employees declare theiroutside business interests on an annual basis so Meir can make the determination as to whatoutside business interests need to be disclosed to clients.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard VI(A)-Disclosure of Conflicts</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>A personal bankruptcy does not necessarily constitute a violation of Standard I(C)-Misrepresentation or Standard I(D)–Misconduct. If the circumstances of the bankruptcy involvedfraudulent or deceitful business conduct, then failing to disclose it may constitute a violation of theStandards of Professional Conduct.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard I(C)-Misrepresentation, Standard I(D)–Misconduct</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>To claim compliance, firms must meet all GIPS requirements, not just calculate their performanceaccording to GIPS requirements.CFA Level I“The GIPS Standards,” CFA InstituteSection: Provisions of the Global Investment Performance Standards</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The prospective supervisor's first step should be to not take the position. Accepting the positionwith inadequate procedures in place or improper marketing material would leave Inkster at risk ofincurring a violation of Standard IV(C)-Responsibilities of Supervisors. She could agree to behired as an interim consultant with the bank in order to implement adequate procedures beforetaking on any supervisory role.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard IV(C)-Responsibilities of Supervisors</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments />
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments />
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>By failing to adhere to the non-compete clause he agreed to abide by when signing hisemployment contract, Hasina shows a lack of professional integrity toward his employer. Thisbehavior reflects poorly on the good reputation of members and is a violation of the Code ofEthics, which states that members and candidates must act with integrity, and Standard I (D)Misconduct, which states that members and candidates must not engage in any professionalconduct involving dishonesty, fraud, or deceit or commit any act that reflects adversely on theirprofessional reputation, integrity, or competence. The Code of Ethics at times requires a memberor candidate to uphold a higher standard than that required by law, rule, or regulation or in thiscase, the strict application of the employment agreement.CFA Level I"Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct," "Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard I(A)-Knowledge of the Law, Standard I(D)-Misconduct</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>In order to avoid violating Standard III(E)-Preservation of Confidentiality, Staal should determinewhether applicable securities regulations require disclosing the records before she provides theconfidential information concerning her client's investments.CFA Level I"Guidance for Standards I-VII"Standard III(E)-Preservation of Confidentiality</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Compliance CFA levell-Mock-114Questions 19-32 Relate to Quantitative analysis19. Correct answer: B.A confidence interval for a parameter = Point estimate = Reliability factor x Standard error. Forexample, the reliability factors for confidence intervals based on the standard normal distributionare 1.65 for 90% confidence intervals and 1.96 for 95% confidence intervals. For a given pointestimate and standard error, the confidence interval will be narrower with a lower reliability factor.CFA Level I"Sampling and Estimation," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, andDavid E. RunkleSection 4.220. Correct answer: A.For a positively skewed unimodal distribution, the mode is less than the median, which is less thanthe mean.CFA Level I"Statistical Concepts and Market Returns," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E.Pinto, and David E. RunkleSection 821. Correct answer: C.Failure to reject a false null hypothesis is a Type II error.CFA Level I"Hypothesis Testing," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 222. Correct answer: C.The appropriate test statistic is a z-statistic because the sample comes from a normal distributedpopulation with known variance. A z-test does not use degrees of freedom. This test is two-sidedat the 0.05 significance level, and the rejection point conditions are z&gt; 1.960 and z&lt; -1.960.CFA Level I"Hypothesis Testing," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Correlation of returns between Asset A and B p(RA, RB), is defined as:p(R, R) = Cov (R, Rg) /o(R, )o(RG),whereR. and R, are the returns of Asset A and BCov (R,, R,) is the covariance of returns between Asset A and B) are the standard deviations of returns of Asset A and BIn this problem, the correlation is 600/ (V625 X V1, 225) = 0. 6857 = 0. 69.CFA Level I"Probability Concepts," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Given a population that has a finite variance and a large sample size, the central limit theoremestablishes that the sampling distribution of sample means will be approximately normal, thedistribution of sample mean will have a mean equal to the population mean, and will have avariance equal to the population variance divided by the sample size.CFA Level I"Sampling and Estimation," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, andDavid E. RunkleSection 3.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Resistance is defined as a price range in which selling activity is sufficient to stop the rise in price.CFA Level I"Technical Analysis," Barry M. Sine and Robert A. StrongSection 3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The p-value is the smallest level of significance at which the null hypothesis can be rejected. Inthis case, the given p-value (0.0275) is less than the given level of significance (0.05); therefore,the null hypothesis is rejected.CFA Level I"Hypothesis Testing," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>By the definition of p-value, 0.03 is the smallest level of significance at which the null hypothesiscan be rejected. An analyst cannot reject the null hypothesis at the 0.01 significance level.CFA Level I"Hypothesis Testing," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>An opportunity cost is the value that investors forgo by choosing a particular course of action.CFA Level I"The Time Value of Money," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, andDavid E. RunkleSection 2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Events are exhaustive when they cover all possible outcomes. Mutually exclusive means that onlyone event can occur at a time. Two events are dependent if the occurrence of one event does affectthe probability of occurrence of the other event. In this situation, Event A and B are both mutuallyexclusive (because they cannot occur at the same time) and dependent (because if one eventoccurs, the probability of the other becomes zero). However, the two events are not exhaustivebecause they do not cover the event that the fund will earn a return above 5%.CFA Level I"Probability Concepts," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The t-statistic for the given information (normally distributed populations, population variancesassumed equal) is calculated as:+ - (1 - ) - (1 – .)</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>5</answer>
        <comments>N RIn this case, we have:s;= 2678.05.(200 – 185,) – (0)t = -(2678. 05 2678. 051052518= 0. 93768 0. 94+18CFA Level I“Hypothesis Testing,” Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments> when the data do not meet distributional assumptions, or when the hypothesis being addresseddoes not concern a parameter.CFA Level I"Hypothesis Testing," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 5</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments> when the data do not meet distributional assumptions, or when the hypothesis being addresseddoes not concern a parameter.CFA Level I"Hypothesis Testing," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 5</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The most appropriate test statistic for the difference between two population means (unequal and= (F1 -T:) - (, – .)unknown population variances) is t = 110. 52CFA Level I"Hypothesis Testing," Richard A. DeFusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E.RunkleSection 3.2Questions 33-44 Relate to Economics</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>In first-degree price discrimination, the entire consumer surplus is captured by the producer; theconsumer surplus falls to zero.CFA Level I"The Firm and Market Structures," Richard G. Fritz and Michele GamberaSection 6.4</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Using the expenditures approach:GDP = Consumer spending on goods and services + Business gross fixed investment + Change ininventories + Government spending on goods and services + Government gross fixed investment+ Exports – Imports + Statistical discrepancyConsumer spending on goods and services875,060Business gross fixed investment286,400Change in inventories(68,500)Government spending on goods and services305,600Government gross fixed investment84,120Exports219,800Imports(250,980)Statistical discrepancy(2,850)= Gross domestic product (GDP)1,448,650CFA Level I“Aggregate Output, Prices, and Economic Growth,” Paul R. Kutasovic and Richard G. FritzSections 2.2, 2.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Cost -push inflation arises due to increases in costs associated with production: wages and rawmaterials prices.CFA Level I“Understanding Business Cycles,” Michele Gambera, Milton Ezrati, and Bolong CaoSection 4.2.4.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Prior to the price ceiling, the total surplus was d+e+f+g + h, consisting of consumer surplus off+e and producer surplus of d+ g + h. The price ceiling causes the quantity supplied to decreaseto QC and for those consumers who can find supply to gain consumer surplus of g at the expenseof producers. With the decline in supply, consumers lose consumer surplus e and producers loseproducer surplus d for a combined deadweight loss of d+e.CFA Level I"Demand and Supply Analysis: Introduction," Richard V. Eastin and Gary L. ArbogastSection 3.13</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The optimal output level is 60 units as that level produces the highest profit:OutputPriceTotalTotal Costs ($)Profit(units)($/unit)Revenue ($)($)202,80056,00010,60045,400402,600104,00032,60071,400602,400144,00066,60077,400802,200176,000112,60063,4001002,000200,000170,60029,400CFA Level I“The Firm and Market Structures,” Richard G. Fritz and Michele GamberaSections 6.1, 6.2, 6.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>The characteristics of monopolistic competition include a large number of competitors, lowpricing power, and the production of differentiated products (through advertising and othernon-price strategies), but these still result in some pricing power. The ease of entry results in zeroeconomic profits in the long run.CFA Level I"The Firm and Market Structures," Richard G. Fritz and Michele GamberaSections 2.1, 2.2, 4</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Nominal GDP is defined as the value of goods and services measured at current prices. Real GDPis not affected by price increases while nominal GDP and the GDP deflator increase with priceincreases:Real GDPcurrent year = Nominal GDPcurrent yearx100 - GDP deflatorReal GDPcurrent year = PXbase year x QXcurrent yearCFA Level I“Aggregate Output, Prices, and Economic Growth,” Paul R. Kutasovic, and Richard G. FritzSection 2.1.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>At full employment, a weaker currency reduces the purchasing power of all domestic currencydenominated assets (including the present value of current and future income). Householdsrespond by reducing general expenditures and increasing savings. This response is the wealtheffect and reflects the proportion of one's income that is saved (or spent).CFA Level I"Demand and Supply Analysis: Consumer Demand," Richard V. Eastin and Gary L. ArbogastSection 6.2"Aggregate Output, Prices, and Economic Growth," Paul R. Kutasovic and Richard G. FritzSection 3.3.1"Currency Exchange Rates," William A. Barker, Paul D. McNelis, and Jerry NickelsburgSections 5.1, 5.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>A shift in the demand curve results from a change in any variable other than the good's own price,Px. Given the demand function, a change in either Py or I would result in a shift in the demandcurve. A change in quantity demanded, which refers to a movement along the demand curve,arises when the good's own price changes.CFA Level I"Demand and Supply Analysis: Introduction," Richard V. Eastin and Gary L. ArbogastSection 3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>In a perfectly competitive market, sellers have no pricing power and thus sell their product at theprice established by demand and supply in the market – the market equilibrium price.CFA Level I"The Firm and Market Structures, " Richard G. Fritz and Michele GamberaSection 3.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments> Chain 1 earns 540Chain 1 earns 108instead of 180instead of 55If it opens for 24 hours, it will see a higher payoffregardless of what Chain 1 does.NChain 1Chain 1Open for 24 hoursCloses at 9 p.m.Opens for 24 hoursChain 2 earns 140Chain 2 earns 592instead of 290instead of 75CFA Level I“The Firm and Market Structures,” Richard G. Fritz and Michele GamberaSection 5.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments> Chain 1 earns 540Chain 1 earns 108instead of 180instead of 55If it opens for 24 hours, it will see a higher payoffregardless of what Chain 1 does.NChain 1Chain 1Open for 24 hoursCloses at 9 p.m.Opens for 24 hoursChain 2 earns 140Chain 2 earns 592instead of 290instead of 75CFA Level I“The Firm and Market Structures,” Richard G. Fritz and Michele GamberaSection 5.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The CFA levell-Mock-114Questions 45-68 Relate to Financial Statement Analysis45. Correct answer: C.A decrease in the tax rate will result in a decrease in the previously reported amounts of deferredtax assets. That is, the value of the future tax assets, based on the new lower rate, is reduced foroffsetting future tax payments.CFA Level I“Income Taxes,” Elbie Antonites and Michael A. BroihahnSection 3.346. Correct answer: C.When a long lived asset is sold only the net gain or loss is reported on the income statement. Thegain or loss on a sale = sales proceeds – carrying amount = $80,000 — $70,000 = $10,000 gain.CFA Level I"Long-lived Assets," Elaine Henry and Elizabeth A. GordonSection 6.147. Correct answer: C.The direct method of cash flow statement presentation shows the specific cash inflows andoutflows that result in reported cash flow from operating activities (e.g., cash from customers andcash to suppliers). Companies using IFRS can decide to report interest and dividend receipts aseither an investing or operating activity, whereas under US GAAP, they must report such incomeas an operating activity. The listed operating and investment activities indicate that the companyreports under IFRS using the direct method.CFA Level I"Understanding Cash Flow Statements," Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hendrik vanGreuning, and Michael A. BroihahnSections 2.3, 2.3.2, 3.2.1.548. Correct answer: C.Under US GAAP, bank overdrafts are not considered part of cash and cash equivalents and areclassified as financing cash flows.CFA Level I"Understanding Cash Flow Statements," Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hendrik vanGreuning, and Michael A. BroihahnSection 2.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Income tax expense equals income tax payable (the tax rate multiplied by the taxable income) plusthe increase in the deferred tax liabilities.(0.30 x $215,000) + ($90,650 – $82,400) = $64,500 + $8,250 = $72,750.CFA Level I“Income Taxes,” Elbie Antonites and Michael A. BroihahnSection 2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The SEC now advocates for global accounting standards through public announcements, such asits "Statement in Support of Convergence and Global Accounting Standards" (2010). In the past,the SEC had required reconciliations between IFRS and US GAAP, but these requirements werewithdrawn in 2008. The SEC now imposes no requirements on its issuers.CFA Level I"Financial Reporting Standards," Elaine Henry, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, and Thomas R.RobinsonSection 4</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>The Deferred tax asset is based on the temporary difference arising from the difference in thecarrying value for taxes vs. the financial statements = (120,000 – 100,000) x 17%= 3,400. The ratethat should be used is the rate expected when the reversal will occur which is now the lower rateof 17%.CFA "Income Taxes," Elbie Antonites and Michael A. BroihahnSection 3.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>A common-size balance sheet expresses all balance sheet accounts as a percentage of total assetsand would provide insight into what portion of a company's assets is liquid. On the other hand,cash and current ratios measure liquidity relative to current liabilities, not relative to total assets.CFA Level I“Understanding Balance Sheets,” Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonsonSections 7.1, 7.2“Financial Analysis Techniques,” Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik vanGreuningSection 3.2.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Under IFRS (International Financial Reporting Standards), first determine the recoverable amount,which is the higher of value in use (the present value of the expected future cash flows) = $32,000or fair value minus costs to sell = $34,000 — 4,000 = $30,000The recoverable amount ($32,000) is lower than the carrying value ($36,000). Therefore, the assetis impaired and should be written down to that amount.Under US GAAP, to assess impairment, the carrying value ($36,000) is compared with theundiscounted expected future cash flows ($38,000). In this case, the carrying value is lower so thepatent is not impaired.CFA Level I“Long-lived Assets,” Elaine Henry and Elizabeth A. GordonSections 5.1, 5.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>US GAAP prohibits the revaluation of PPE. Therefore, this is a source of an important differencebetween US GAAP and IFRS with respect to reporting of income taxes.CFA Level I"Income Taxes," Elbie Antonites and Michael A. BroihahnSection 8</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Because the asset is self-constructed, the costs of specifically identifiable interest during theconstruction period can be capitalized and included in the cost of the showroom.€ MillionsConstruction costs38.5Interest expense in 2012 and 2013: 0.08 x €30 x 2 years4.8Total capitalized cost43.3Straight line depreciation expense:(Capitalized cost – Residual value)/Useful life = (43.3 – 5.0)/400.9575CFA Level I“Long-lived Assets,” Elaine Henry and Elizabeth A. GordonSections 2.1, 3.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments> = 830Denominator390390390Ratio: Current2.130.350.94yearRatio: Prior 2.190.370.97yearChange in ratio-0.06–0.02–0.03CFA Level I“Understanding Balance Sheets,” Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 7.2“Financial Analysis Techniques,” Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik vanGreuningSection 4.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments> = 830Denominator390390390Ratio: Current2.130.350.94yearRatio: Prior 2.190.370.97yearChange in ratio-0.06–0.02–0.03CFA Level I“Understanding Balance Sheets,” Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 7.2“Financial Analysis Techniques,” Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik vanGreuningSection 4.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>The allowance for doubtful accounts increases by the bad debt expense recognized for the yearand decreases by the amounts written off during the year.Beginning balance allowance for doubtful£56 millionaccountsPlus bad debt expenseMinus write-offs-£84 millionEnding balance allowance for doubtful£92 millionaccountsSolve for bad debt expense = £120 million.CFA Level I“Understanding Balance Sheets,” Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 3.1.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>With accelerated amortisation, first year amortisation expense is the highest.CFA Level I“Long-lived Assets,” Elaine Henry and Elizabeth A. GordonSections 3.1, 3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Net income = Comprehensive income – Other comprehensive$193.0$105.4income$87.6millionNet income per share (EPS) =$105.4/46.5$2.27 millionNet income/Common shares outstandingP/E = Stock price/EPS$60.75/$2.2726.76CFA Level I“Understanding Income Statements,” Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 8“Financial Analysis Techniques,” Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik vanGreuningSection 5.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The CFA levell-Mock-114“Understanding Income Statements,” Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 3.2.463. Correct answer: C.Whether securities are classified as held for trading or available for sale, they are measured at theirfair value on the balance sheet. All gains/losses on held-for-trading securities are reported on theincome statements, whereas the unrealized gains/losses on available-for-sale securities arereported in equity. This treatment is the same for both IFRS and US GAAP reporting.CFA Level I"Understanding Income Statements," Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 8"Understanding Balance Sheets," Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 4.564. Correct answer: C.The revenue/expense-based approach is a measurement approach, not a standard setting approach.CFA Level I"Financial Reporting Standards," Elaine Henry, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, and Thomas R.RobinsonSections 2, 6.265. Correct answer: C.Deferred tax balances result from temporary differences between a company's income as reportedfor tax purposes and income reported for financial statement purposes. The temporary differencein this case arises from the difference between the depreciation for accounting purposes and thedepreciation for tax purposes. Because of this difference, the company would report more incometax expense than would actually be paid in taxes. The difference is a deferred tax liability.Temporary difference balance = Depreciation expense for £6,340 – £4,500£1,840accounting purposes – Depreciation for tax purposesDeferred tax balance =Temporary difference balance x Corporate tax rate£1,840 x 25%£460CFA Level I“Understanding Balance Sheets,” Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 5.2“Income Taxes,” Elbie Antonites and Michael A. BroihahnSections 2.2, 4</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>A company must disclose separate information about any operating segment which meets certainquantitative criteria—namely, the segment constitutes 10 percent or more of the combinedoperating segments’ revenue, assets, or profit. (For purposes of determining whether a segmentconstitutes 10 percent or more of combined profits or losses, the criteria is expressed in terms ofthe absolute value of the segment's profit or loss as a percentage of the greater of (i) the combinedprofits of all profitable segments and (ii) the absolute amount of the combined losses of allloss-making segments.)CFA Level I"Financial Analysis Techniques," Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik vanGreuningSection 7.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>( millions)Accounting PurposesTax PurposesRevaluation surplus(£10,000 – £6,800) = £3,200No revaluation allowed20 years5 years remainingDepreciation, straight lineStart of year balance afterrevaluation, 2013£10,000£5,000Depreciation, 2013(£10,000/20 years) = £500£1,000Net balance, end of 2013£9,500£4,000Minus revaluation surplus- £ 3,200Carrying value for purposes£6,300£4,000of deferred taxesDeferred tax liability = 0.30 X (£6,300 – £4,000) = £690Only the portion of the difference between the tax base and the carrying amount that is notthe result of the revaluation is recognized as giving rise to a deferred tax liability. The portionarising from the revaluation surplus is used to reduce the revaluation surplus in equity.CFA Level I“Income Taxes,” Elbie Antonites and Michael A. BroihahnSections 2.2, 6.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The higher the current ratio, the more liquid the company. Thus, with a current ratio of 2.6(1,800/700), the company is less liquid than the industry, which has a current ratio of 3.2.Current ratio = Current assets/Current liabilities.Current Assets£ thousandsCurrent Liabilities£ thousandsCash200Accounts payableB00Accounts receivable350Taxes payable200Inventory1,250Loan payable, first installment200Total1,800Total700CFA Level I“Understanding Balance Sheets,” Elaine Henry and Thomas R. RobinsonSection 7.2“Financial Analysis Techniques,” Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik vanGreuningSection 4.3“Working Capital Management,” Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and PamelaPeterson DrakeSections 2.2Questions 69—76 Relate to Corporate finance</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.Fixed operating cost12,000</answer>
        <comments>Operating breakeven point=.-= 1,000price- variable cost per unit| 12CFA Level I“Measures of leverage?”</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Breakeven quantity of sales,F + CQBE = -P - V= (€50 million + €30 million) - (€85 - €65) = 4.0 million units.CFA Level I“Measures of Leverage,” Pamela Peterson Drake, Raj Aggarwal, Cynthia Harrington, and AdamKoborSection 3.6</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Cost of trade credit = 1 +(365/Numbewf days beyonddiscountperiodDiscount- Discount))– 1Cost of trade credit = 1 +|(365/393%– 3%)).- 1 = 44.9%CFA Level I“Working Capital Management,” Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and PamelaPeterson DrakeSection 7.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>A reduction in inventory will increase the inventory turnover (Cost of goods sold/Averageinventory), which means that the days in inventory will be reduced (365/Inventory turnover). Thiswill lead to a reduction in the cash conversion cycle (also called net operating cycle). Cashconversion cycle consists of number of days of inventory and number of days of receivablesminus number of days of payables.CFA Level I“Financial Analysis Techniques,” Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, Elaine Henry,and Michael A. BroihahnSection 4.3.2"Working Capital Management,” Edgar A. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and PamelaPeterson DrakeSection 2.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Based on the following equation:DTL =Quantity x (Price – Variable cost)Quantity x (Price - Variable cost) – Fixed costs - Financing costs]the change to accelerated depreciation increases the fixed costs, thus making DTL increase (i.e.,the numerator does not change and the denominator decreases).CFA Level I“Measures of Leverage,” Pamela Peterson Drake, Raj Aggarwal, Cynthia Harrington, and AdamKoborSection 3.5</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Sales risk is associated with uncertainty with respect to total revenue, which, in turn, depends onprice and units sold.CFA Level I“Measures of Leverage,” Pamela Peterson Drake, Raj Aggarwal, Cynthia Harrington, and AdamKoborSection 3.1, 3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.3.6</answer>
        <comments>EBIT DFL =EBIT – Interest 3.6-1.2=1.5CFA Level I“Measures of leverage”</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments> Questions 77-88 Relate to Equity investment</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments> Questions 77-88 Relate to Equity investment</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Companies pursuing cost leadership must be able to invest in productivity-improving capitalequipment in order to be low-cost producers and maintain efficient operating systems.CFA Level I“Introduction to Industry and Company Analysis,” Patrick W. Dorsey, Anthony M. Fiore, and IanRossa O’ReillySection 6</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Net profit margin = Net earnings/SalesNet earnings = Net profit margin x Sales;Dividends per share (Dn) = (Net earnings x Payout ratio)/Number of outstanding shares;Therefore, D1 = ($180 million X 0.15 x 0.60)/8.1 million = $2.00D2 = $2.00(1 + 0.25) = $2.50D3 = $2.00(1 + 0.25)2 = $3.13D4 = $2.00(1 + 0.25)2 (1 + 0.05) = $3.28$3. 28V3 =T = $46. 68(o. 12 – 0. 05)$2.004 $2. 504 $3. 134 $46. 86 - $39. 36Vo(1 + 0. 12) * (1 + 0. 12) *(1 + 0. 12) *(1 + 0. 12)CFA Level I“Equity Valuation: Concepts and Basic Tools,” John J. Nagorniak and Stephen E. WilcoxSection 4.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Share buyback reduces equity, holding other factors (e.g., earnings) constant, thus return on equitywill be higher.CFA Level I“Financial Analysis Techniques,” Elaine Henry, Thomas R. Robinson, and Jan Hendrik vanGreuningSections 4.5.2, 6.2“Introduction to Industry and Company Analysis,” Patrick W. Dorsey, Anthony M. Fiore, and IanRossa O’ReillySection 6.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Operationally efficient markets are liquid markets in which the costs of arranging trades,commissions, bid-ask spreads, and order price impacts, are low.CFA Level I“Market Organization and Structure,” Larry HarrisSection 9</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The put option feature facilitates raising capital because the shares are more appealing to investors.As such, it provides a benefit to the issuing company. It also helps investors limit their potentiallosses because they can sell the shares back to the issuing company if the market price falls belowthe pre-specified put price. Therefore, putable common shares are beneficial to both the issuingcompany and the investors.CFA Level I“Overview of Equity Securities,” Ryan C. Fuhrmann and Asjeet S. LambaSection 3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>In an efficient market, market participants will process available information and those withopposite views will trade among each other until securities market prices fully reflect theirfundamental values. An efficient market is thus a market in which asset prices reflect all past andpresent information.CFA Level I"Market Efficiency," W. Sean Cleary, Howard J. Atkinson and Pamela Peterson DrakeSection 2.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Market indices are used as model portfolios for index funds and exchange-traded funds, but theyare not useful as model portfolios for active funds.CFA Level I"Security Market Indices," Paul D. Kaplan and Dorothy C. KellySection 4</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Because regulated markets are more informationally efficient, there are fewer arbitrageopportunities.CFA Level I"Market Organization and Structure," Larry HarrisSection 10</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Cumulative voting allows shareholders to direct their total voting rights to specific candidates, asopposed to having to allocate their voting rights evenly among all candidates. Thus, applying allof the votes to one candidate provides the opportunity for a higher level of representation on theboard than would be allowed under statutory voting.CFA Level I“The Corporate Governance of Listed Companies: A Manual for Investors,” Kurt Schacht, JamesC. Allen, and Matthew OrsaghSection: Shareowner Voting“Overview of Equity Securities,” Ryan C. Fuhrmann and Asjeet S. LambaSection 3.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>If CFA levell-Mock-114of a portfolio manager is not necessarily to beat the market, but rather to establish and manage aportfolio consistent with the portfolio’s objectives, with appropriate diversification and assetallocation, while taking into consideration the risk preferences and tax situation of the investor.CFA Level I“Market Efficiency,” W. Sean Cleary, Howard J. Atkinson, and Pamela Peterson DrakeSection 3.4.387. Correct answer: C.Putable preference shares are less risky than their callable counterparts. They give the investor theoption to put the shares back to the company. Because of the lower risk, they will provide a lowerexpected rate of return. Common shares are the most risky, whether or not they are dividendpaying, and are likely to offer the highest expected return.CFA Level I“Overview of Equity Securities,” Ryan C. Fuhrmann and Asjeet S. LambaSection 6.288. Correct answer: A.Companies with large amounts of undervalued assets (which can be sold to reduce debt) thatgenerate high levels of cash flow (which are used to make interest and principal payments on thedebt) are likely candidates for MBO transactions.CFA Level I“Overview of Equity Securities,” Ryan C. Fuhrmann and Asjeet S. LambaSection 4Questions 89–94 Relate to Derivatives</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The pricing of forwards and futures will differ if futures prices and interest rates are negativelycorrelated. A negative correlation between futures prices and interest rates makes forwards moredesirable than futures in the long position.CFA Level I"Basics of Derivative Pricing and Valuation," Don M. ChanceSection 3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>American call prices can differ from European call prices only if the underlying stock is dividendpaying. In the absence of such cash payments, European and American call options have the samevalue.CFA Level I"Basics of Derivative Pricing and Valuation," Don M. ChanceSection 4.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>A swap is a series of forward payments. Specifically, a swap is an agreement between two partiesto exchange a series of future cash flows. The corporation receives fixed interest rate paymentsand makes variable interest rate payments. Given that the contract is for one year and the floatingrate is based on three-month LIBOR, at least four payments will be made during the year.CFA Level I“Derivative Markets and Instruments,” Don M. ChanceSection 4.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments> "Basics of Derivative Pricing and Valuation," Don M. ChanceSection 3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments> "Basics of Derivative Pricing and Valuation," Don M. ChanceSection 3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Derivative markets are not necessarily more or less volatile than spot markets. Derivative marketsreveal prices and volatilities of the underlying assets and facilitate risk management.CFA Level I"Derivative Markets and Instruments," Don M. ChanceSection 5</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>Only CFA levell-Mock-114Questions 95-106 Relate to Fixed-income Analysis95. Correct answer: B.The company's interest coverage ratio can be computed as: EBITDA/Interest expense. That is:20X120X2EBITDA125.0170.0Interest expense30.038.0EBITDA/Interest expense4.174.47EBITDA = Operating profit + Depreciation and amortizationThe company's EBITDA interest coverage ratio has improved over this period. If EBIT is used tocalculate the coverage ratios you reach the same conclusion, for 20X1 the ratio is 3.33 and for20X2 it is 3.86.CFA Level I“Fundamentals of Credit Analysis”, Christopher L. GootkindSection 5.2.196. Correct answer: A.An FRN with a floor on the coupon rate prevents the coupon rate from falling below aprespecified minimum rate.CFA Level I"Fixed-Income Securities: Defining Elements," Moorad Choudhry and Stephen E. WilcoxSection 4.297. Correct answer: C.A call provision gives the issuer the right to redeem all or part of the bond before the specifiedmaturity date to protect the issuer against a decline in interest rates. Therefore, it benefits theissuer and provides a lower future funding cost.CFA Level 1"Fixed-Income Securities: Defining Elements," Moorad Choudhry and Stephen E. Wilcox, CFASection 5</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>A security with a present value of 96.47, 19 interest payments of 8, and a 20th payment ofprincipal plus interest (108) has a yield to maturity of 8.37%.CFA Level 1"Introduction to Fixed-Income Valuation," James F. Adams and Donald J. SmithSection 3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>If the discount rate increases to 7.5% from 6.5%, the price of a bond decreases. At a discount rateof 7.5%, the bond sells at a discount to face value. As a discount bond approaches maturity, it willincrease in price over time until it reaches par at maturity.CFA Level I"Introduction to Fixed-Income Valuation," James F. Adams and Donald J. SmithSection 2.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.Days.</answer>
        <comments>The price of the commercial paper per 100 of par value is: PV = FV x |1 –x DRyearwhere PV and FV are the price and face value of the money market instrument, Days is thenumber of days between settlement and maturity, Year is number of days in the year, and DR is thediscount rate stated as an annual percentage.90So, PV = 100 x 1 -x 0. 0475| = 98. 8125 The bond equivalent yield is,360AOR =YearDays- PV)PV— So, AOR =365 (100 – 98. 8125)</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>8125= 4. 874%</answer>
        <comments>90 CFA Level 1"Introduction to Fixed-Income Valuation," James F. Adams and Donald J. SmithSection 3.5</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>A sinking fund arrangement is a way to reduce credit risk by making the issuer set aside fundsover time to retire the bond issue.CFA Level 1"Fixed-Income Markets: Issuance, Trading, and Funding," Moorad Choudhry, Steven V. Mann,and Lavone F. WhitmerSection 6.3.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The yield to maturity (r) is computed by solving for r in the following equation:</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>00 = 8/(1 + r)5 + 8/(1 + r)6 + 8/(1 + r)7 + 8/(1 + r)8 + 8/(1 + r)9 + 108/(1 + r)10, which gives a</answer>
        <comments>yield to maturity of 6.0%.CFA Level 1"Introduction to Fixed-Income Valuation," James F. Adams and Donald J. Smith</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Balloon risk is the risk that the borrower will not be able to arrange for refinancing or sell theproperty to make the balloon payment typically associated with commercial loans backing CMBS.As a result, the CMBS may extend in maturity implying that balloon risk is a type of extensionrisk.CFA Level I"Introduction to Asset-Backed Securities", Frank J. FabozziSection 6.2.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>In a mortgage pass-through security the pass-through rate is less than the mortgage rate on theunderlying pool of mortgages by an amount equal to the servicing (and other administrative) fees.CFA Level I"Introduction to Asset-Backed Securities", Frank J. FabozziSection 5.1.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The value of the bond is</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>52. 5</answer>
        <comments>( 1 + 0. 12 / 2) * (1 + 0. 12 / 2) x (1 + 0. 18 / 2)</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>5</answer>
        <comments>( 1 + 0. 12 / 2) x (1 + 0. 18 / 2) x (1 + 0. 23 / 2)</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>5</answer>
        <comments>* (1 + 0. 12 / 2) x (1 + 0. 18 / 2) x (1 + 0. 23 / 2) x (1 + 0. 27 / 2)</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>5</answer>
        <comments>T (1 + 0. 12 / 2) x (1 + 0. 18 / 2) x (1 + 0. 23 / 2) x (1 + 0. 27 / 2) x (1 + 0. 30 / 2)= $106. 83CFA Level I"Introduction to Fixed-Income Valuation," James F. Adams and Donald J. SmithSection 4</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments> CFA levell-Mock-114Questions 107-110 Relate to Alternative Investments107. Correct answer: A.When a commodity market is in contango, futures prices are higher than spot prices. When spotprices are higher than the futures price, the market is said to be in backwardation.CFA Level I"Introduction to Alternative Investments," Terri Duhon, George Spentzos, and Scott D. StewartSection 6.4.1108. Correct answer: B.The Sharpe ratio and the safety-first measure use standard deviation as the measure of risk, whichignore the negative skewness in returns. The Sortino ratio uses the downside deviation as themeasure of risk, which will reflect negative skewness if present.CFA Level I"Introduction to Alternative Investments," Terri Duhon, George Spentzos, and Scott D. StewartSection 9.2109. Correct answer: B.The exclusion of returns of funds that have been liquidated is called survivorship bias. It is mostlikely that only poor performers are eliminated and thus reported returns are artificially inflated.CFA Level I"Introduction to Alternative Investments," Terri Duhon, George Spentzos, and Scott D. StewartSection 2110. Correct answer: A.The historical standard deviations of annual return for venture capital are higher than that ofcommon stocks. Investors should therefore require a higher return in exchange for accepting thishigher risk, along with the illiquidity of venture capital investing.CFA Level I"Introduction to Alternative Investments," Terri Duhon, George Spentzos, and Scott D. StewartSection 4.3Questions 111 ~120 Relate to Portfolio Management</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments> CFA levell-Mock-114Questions 107-110 Relate to Alternative Investments107. Correct answer: A.When a commodity market is in contango, futures prices are higher than spot prices. When spotprices are higher than the futures price, the market is said to be in backwardation.CFA Level I"Introduction to Alternative Investments," Terri Duhon, George Spentzos, and Scott D. StewartSection 6.4.1108. Correct answer: B.The Sharpe ratio and the safety-first measure use standard deviation as the measure of risk, whichignore the negative skewness in returns. The Sortino ratio uses the downside deviation as themeasure of risk, which will reflect negative skewness if present.CFA Level I"Introduction to Alternative Investments," Terri Duhon, George Spentzos, and Scott D. StewartSection 9.2109. Correct answer: B.The exclusion of returns of funds that have been liquidated is called survivorship bias. It is mostlikely that only poor performers are eliminated and thus reported returns are artificially inflated.CFA Level I"Introduction to Alternative Investments," Terri Duhon, George Spentzos, and Scott D. StewartSection 2110. Correct answer: A.The historical standard deviations of annual return for venture capital are higher than that ofcommon stocks. Investors should therefore require a higher return in exchange for accepting thishigher risk, along with the illiquidity of venture capital investing.CFA Level I"Introduction to Alternative Investments," Terri Duhon, George Spentzos, and Scott D. StewartSection 4.3Questions 111 ~120 Relate to Portfolio Management</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>Although the client owns a successful business and has a high income, she exhibits above-averagerisk aversion, indicating that her ability to take risk is high but her willingness to take risk is low.CFA Level I"Basics of Portfolio Planning and Construction," Alistair Byrne and Frank E. SmuddleSection 2.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>One of the assumptions of the CAPM is that investors plan for the same single holding period.CFA Level I"Portfolio Risk and Return: Part II," Vijay SingalSection 4.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>Jensen 's alpha = 0.12 – [0.027 + 1.5(0.075 – 0.027)] = 0.021, or 2.10%.CFA Level I"Portfolio Risk and Return: Part II," Vijay SingalSection 4.3.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>The execution step of the portfolio management process has three parts: asset allocation, securityanalysis, and portfolio construction.CFA Level I"Portfolio Management, An Overview," Robert M. Conroy and Alistair ByrneSection 4</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The optimal portfolio is identified as the point at which the capital allocation line (CAL) istangential to the investor's indifference curve. As investor risk aversion increases, the optimalportfolio slides down the CAL to a point of lower expected risk and lower expected return.CFA Level I"Portfolio Risk and Return: Part I," Vijay SingalSection 3.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>The increase in return with every unit increase in risk keeps decreasing as one moves from left toright because the slope of the efficient frontier continues to decrease. Thus, investors obtaindecreasing increases in returns as they assume more risk.CFA Level I"Portfolio Risk and Return: Part I," Vijay SingalSection 5.2</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: A.</answer>
        <comments>An individual's ability to take risk is affected by such factors as time horizon and expected income.Personality type is most likely to affect an individual's willingness to take risk.CFA Level I"Basics of Portfolio Management and Construction," Alistair Byrne and Frank E. SmuddeSection 2.2.1</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: B.</answer>
        <comments>The covariance is calculated from the standard deviations of the two assets and their correlation.The portfolio weights are not relevant.CFA Level I"Portfolio Risk and Return: Part I," Vijay SingalSection 4.1.3</comments>
    </problem>
    <problem>
        <question />
        <choices />
        <answer>Correct answer: C.</answer>
        <comments>BJKU CFA levell-Mock-114and E(RJKU) = RER + B JKU (Ry – Rep) = 0. 05 + 1 x (o. 12 – 0. 05) = 0. 12The required rate of return of JKU is 12%, and the expected return of JKU is 15%. Therefore, JKUis undervalued relative to the security market line (SML); the risk-return relationship lies abovethe SML.CFA Level I"Portfolio Risk and Return: Part II," Vijay SingalSection 4120. Correct answer: A.The standard deviation of a two asset portfolio is calculated as follows:op = (wºo + W; 6; + 2M, W,0,0,Cov(R,R,)CFA Level I"Portfolio Risk and Return: Part I," Vijay SingalSection 2.3.3</comments>
    </problem>
</problems>