<problems>
<problem>
	<question>2. When Jefferson Piedmont, CFA, joined Branch Investing, Branch began using a quantitative stock selection model Piedmont had developed on his own personal time prior to his employment with Branch. One year later when Piedmont left the firm, he found the original copy of the model he had developed in a file at his home and presented it to his new employer, who immediately began using the model. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, did Piedmont violate any CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Yes, because he misappropriated property now belonging to Branch.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Yes, because he failed to inform his new employer the model was the same one used by his previous employer.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 69-71 Study Session 1-2-a Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Although departing employees may not take employer property when departing (Standard IV (A) - Duties to Employers (Loyalty), the model Piedmont presented to his new employer was not Branch&#8217;s property. It was created by Piedmont prior to his employment with Branch. The model was not created for Branch in the course of his employment, but was adopted by Branch.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>3. Lawrence Hall, CFA, and Nancy Bishop, CFA, began a joint research report on Stamper Corporation. Bishop visited Stamper&#8217;s corporate headquarters for several days and met with all company officers. Prior to the completion of the report, Bishop was reassigned to another project. Hall utilized his and Bishop&#8217;s research to write the report but did not include Bishop&#8217;s name on the report, because she did not agree with Hall&#8217;s conclusion included in the final report. According to the CFA Institute Standards of Practice Handbook, did Hall violate any CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to misrepresentation.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to diligence and reasonable basis.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 29-31, 80-82 Study Session 1-2-a Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Members are in compliance with CFA Institute&#8217;s Standard V (A) Diligence and Reasonable Basis, if they rely on the research of another party who exercised diligence and thoroughness. Because Bishop&#8217;s opinion did not agree with the final report, disassociating her from the report is one way to handle this difference between the analysts.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>4. According to the Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS), which of the following is not a part of the verification process? Testing whether the:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">firm has complied with all the composite construction requirements.</choice>

		<choice id="B">verification is undertaken by the compliance department in the absence of a third party.</choice>

		<choice id="C">firm&#8217;s processes and procedures are designed to calculate results in compliance with GIPS standards.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>Introduction to the Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS&#174;) CFA Institute, 2006 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 131 Study Sessions 1-3-c Explain the requirements for verification of compliance with GIPS standards. Verification tests (Standard V) whether the investment firm has complied with all the composite construction requirements of GIPS on a firm-wide basis, and whether the firm&#8217;s processes and procedures are designed to calculate and present performance results in compliance with the GIPS Standards. Verification must be performed by an independent third party. A firm cannot perform its own verification. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>5. Umi Grabbo, CFA, is a highly regarded portfolio manager for Atlantic Advisors (AA), a mid-sized mutual fund firm investing in domestic securities. She has watched the hedge fund boom and on numerous occasions suggested her firm create such a fund. Senior management has refused to commit resources to the area. Attracted by potential higher fees associated with hedge funds, Grabbo and several other employees organize a hedge fund to invest in international securities. Grabbo is careful to work on the fund development only on her own time. Because AA management thinks hedge funds are a fad, she does not inform her supervisor about the hedge fund creation. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, Grabbo should most likely address which of the Standards immediately?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Disclosure of Conflicts.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Priority of Transactions.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Additional Compensation Arrangements.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 75, 89-92, 94-98 Study Sessions 1-2-a Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. According to Standard VI (A) Disclosure of Conflicts, Grabbo should disclose to her employer the fact she is developing a hedge fund that could possibly interfere with her responsibilities at AA. In setting up a new fund, Grabbo was not acting for the benefit of her employer. She should have informed AA that she wanted to organize a hedge fund and come to some mutual agreement on how this would occur.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>6. David Donnigan enrolled to take the Level II CFA examination in the current year, however he did not take the exam. Donnigan advised his employer he passed Level II. Subsequently, he registered to take the Level II exam the next year. Which CFA Institute Standard of Professional Conduct did Donnigan least likely violate?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Duty to employer.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Professional misconduct.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Referencing Candidacy in the CFA Program.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 35, 69-71, 105 Study Session 1-2-a Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Members should not engage in conduct involving dishonesty, fraud, deceit, or misrepresentation (Standard I (D)). The candidate&#8217;s dishonesty is not addressed in the Standard relating to Duty to Employer, however. As he registered to take the exam in the next year he still qualifies to state he is a candidate (Standard VII (B)) but he lied to his employer about passing the examination, which is a professional misconduct violation.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>7. Jeffrey Jones passed the Level I CFA examination in 1997 and the Level II examination in 2009. He is not currently enrolled for the Level III examination. According to the CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct, which of the following is the most appropriate way for Jones to refer to his participation in the CFA Program?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Jeffrey Jones, CFA (expected 2011).</choice>

		<choice id="B">Candidate in the CFA Institute CFA Program.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Passed Level II of the CFA examination in 2009.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 105-108 Study Session 1-2-a Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. No designation exists for someone who has passed Level I, Level II, or Level III of the CFA exam (Standard VII (B)). Persons who have passed a certain level of the exam may state that they have completed that level. A person can only state he is a Candidate if he is currently enrolled in the CFA Program. It is also an improper reference to use &#8220;expected&#8221; a part of the designation. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>8. Rebecca Wong is enrolled to take the Level I CFA examination. Her friend William Leung had purchased Level I study materials from a well-known CFA review program the previous year. Leung made a photocopy of the previous year&#8217;s copyrighted materials and sold it to Wong to help her study. Who violated the CFA Institute Code of Ethics or any Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Both violated.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Neither violated.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Only Leung violated.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 15-18 Study Session 1-2-a Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Photocopying copyrighted material, regardless of the year of publication, is a violation of the CFA Institute Standards (Standard I (A)) as copyrighted materials are protected by law. Candidates and members must comply with all applicable laws, rules, and regulations and must not knowingly participate or assist in a violation of laws.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>9. Nicholas Bennett, CFA, is a trader at a stock exchange. Another trader approached Bennett on the floor of the exchange and verbally harassed him about a poorly executed trade. Bennett in response pushed the trader and knocked him to the ground. The exchange, after investigation, cleared Bennett from any wrongdoing. Which of the following best describes Bennett&#8217;s conduct in relation to the CFA Institute Code of Ethics or Standards of Professional Conduct? Bennett:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">did not violate any Code or Standard.</choice>

		<choice id="B">violated the Professional Misconduct Standard.</choice>

		<choice id="C">violated both Misconduct and Integrity of Capital Markets Standards.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 11, 35 Study Session 1-2-a By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. The CFA Institute Code of Ethics requires members to act with integrity, competence, diligence, respect and in an ethical and professional manner; while the Standards of Professional Conduct relating to Professional Misconduct state members and candidates must not commit any act reflecting adversely on their professional reputation, integrity, or competence. Bennett&#8217;s actions violated the Code of Ethics and the Standard relating to Professionalism but not the Standard relating to Integrity of Capital Markets.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>10. Albert Nyakenda, CFA, was driving to a client&#8217;s office where he was expected to close a multi-million dollar deal, when he was pulled over by a traffic policeman When Nyakenda, realized the policeman planned to wrongly ticket him for speeding, he offered to buy him &#8220;lunch&#8221; so that he could quickly get to his client&#8217;s office. The alternative was to go to the police station and file a complaint of being wrongly accused that would also involve going to court the next day to present his case. The lunch would cost significantly more than the ticket. Did Nyakenda violate the CFA Code of Ethics?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Yes.</choice>

		<choice id="B">No, because he was wrongly accused.</choice>

		<choice id="C">No, because the cost of lunch is more than the ticket.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 11 Study Session 1-2-a, b Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. Nyakenda was effectively trying to bribe the policeman so that he would not issue a speeding ticket. This action violates the Code of Ethics. Despite feeling he was wrongly accused, it is only his opinion, and may not based on fact or in a court of law. Nyakenda has a responsibility to act with integrity and in an ethical manual. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>11. Delaney O&#8217;Keefe, a CFA candidate, is a portfolio manager at Bahati Management Company. The company is considering investing offshore for the first time, particularly in North America, on behalf of their clientele, whom are all high net worth individuals. O&#8217;Keefe does not have experience in offshore investments so she hires Mark Carlson, CFA of Carlson Consulting on the basis of his CFA Charter, to undertake due diligence exercises on the top ten portfolio managers in North America, ranked by Assets under Management (AUM). To avoid violating any Code and Standards, O&#8217;Keefe should most likely undertake:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">a sampling of the suitability of North America for clients.</choice>

		<choice id="B">a due diligence exercise on Mark Carlson and Carlson Consulting.</choice>

		<choice id="C">the due diligence exercise on the top ten asset managers herself.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 80 - 81 Study Session 1-2-a, c Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Recommend practices and procedures designed to prevent violations of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct. O&#8217;Keefe can delegate a due diligence exercise to a third party but must ensure the person or company hired to do so is competent with the skills necessary to undertake a thorough and appropriate analysis. Just because a person has a CFA Charter does not necessarily mean he is appropriate for the assignment.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>12. Reiko Kimisaki, CFA, is an investment advisor for a national social security fund in a frontier market with a very limited and illiquid capital market and a very young labor force with an investment time horizon of 25 - 30 years. She has been asked to suggest ways to increase the investment return of the overall portfolio. After careful assessment of the Fund&#8217;s previous investment history, and available asset classes, she considers investment in private equity. What is Kimisaki&#8217;s lowest priority to avoid any Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct violations prior to making this investment recommendation?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Assess the risk tolerance of the Fund.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Analyze the expected returns of private equity in the market.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Determine if the Investment Policy Statement allows for alternative investments.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 60 - 62 Study Session 1-2-c Recommend practices and procedures designed to prevent violations of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct Prior to undertaking analysis with regard to expected returns, an advisor must determine suitability of an investment class including whether it fits within the client&#8217;s risk tolerance and if it is an allowable asset class as per the client&#8217;s Investment Policy Statement. Only once these factors have been determined should she proceed if appropriate to analyze expected returns to determine a particular investment recommendation.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>13. While waiting in the business class lounge before boarding an airplane, Becca Msafari, CFA, an equity analyst, overhears a conversation by a group of senior managers, including members of the Board, from a large publicly listed bank. The managers discuss staff changes necessary to accommodate their regional expansion plans. Msafari heard several staff names mentioned. Under what circumstances could Msafari most likely use this information when making an investment recommendation to her clients?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Under no circumstances.</choice>

		<choice id="B">If she does not breach the confidentiality of names of staff.</choice>

		<choice id="C">If the discussed changes are unlikely to affect the public perception of the bank.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 36 - 39 Study Session 1-2-a, b Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. In order to comply with the Code and Standards, a member or candidate cannot use material non-public information when making investment recommendations. The information overheard would not be considered material only if the staff likely to be terminated were not considered to be in influential positions such that any public announcement of their removal would be unlikely to move the share By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. price of the bank, nor would the regional expansion substantially impact the value of the bank.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>14. Norman Bosno,,CFA acts as an outside portfolio manager to a Sovereign Wealth Fund. Raphel Palmeti, a Fund Official, approaches Bosno to interest him in investing in Starlite Construction Company. He tells Bosno if he approves a two million dollars investment in Starlite by the Fund Bosno will receive a &#8220;bonus&#8221; that will make him wealthy. Palmeti also adds if Bosnoviak decides not to invest, he will lose the Fund account. After doing a quick and simple analysis, Bosno determines the investment is too risky for the Fund. If Bosno agrees to make the investment what Standard is least likely to be violated?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Loyalty, Prudence and Care</choice>

		<choice id="B">Diligence and Reasonable Basis.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Additional Compensation Arrangements.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 48 - 50, 75, 80 - 81 Study Session 1-2-a Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Despite Bosno undertaking a quick and simple analysis to determine the investment would be too risky for the Sovereign Wealth Fund doesn&#8217;t necessarily mean he was not diligent and did not have a reasonable basis for making that determination.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>15. Francesca Ndenda, CFA and Grace Rutabingwa work for New Age Managers where Rutabingwa reports to Ndenda on a daily basis, working in the same department. It has come to the attention of Ndenda that Rutabingwa received a Notice of Enquiry from the Professional Conduct Program at the CFA Institute regarding a potential cheating violation when he sat for the CFA exam in June. As Rutabingwa&#8217;s supervisor, Ndenda is afraid the behavior of Rutabingwa will be seen as a violation of the CFA Code and Standards. Does Ndenda have cause for concern?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Yes.</choice>

		<choice id="B">No, because her responsibilities do not apply.</choice>

		<choice id="C">No, not until Rutabingwa is found guilty of cheating.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 76 - 77 Study Session 1-2-a, b Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. A supervisor&#8217;s responsibilities relate to detecting and preventing violations by anyone subject to their supervision or authority regarding activities they supervise. Ndenda had no way of detecting and/or preventing Rutabingwa from cheating during the CFA exam, an event she did not attend.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>16. Jean-Luc Schlumberger, CFA, is an independent research analyst providing equity research on companies listed on exchanges in emerging markets. He often incorporates statistical data he obtained from the web sites of the World Bank and the Central Banks of the various countries into the body of his research reports. While not indicated within the reports, whenever his clients ask where he gets his information he informs them the information is in the public domain, so he doesn&#8217;t keep his own records. When the clients ask for the specific web site addresses he provides the information. Which Standard has Schlumberger most likely violated?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Misconduct.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Record Retention.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Misrepresentation.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 30 Study Session 1-2-a, b Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. Schlumberger has plagiarized the information he obtained from the websites of the World Bank and the various Central Banks by not quoting the sources within the research reports. This is a violation of Standard I - Professionalism (C) Misrepresentation. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>17. Oni Erobo, CFA, is the General Partner in a real estate development project and is responsible for completing the project within an 18-month period and within budget. Erobo is expected to receive equity of 20% if the project comes within budget. Concerned that project costs would escalate, the Limited Partners require Erobo to cap expenses at 15% above budget. Costs were within expectation up until the last month of construction when costs of imported lighting fixtures (accounting for roughly 5% of total costs) escalated by more than 50%. As a result, the overall return declined below the partners expected 35% ROI. Erobo did not inform the Limited Partners about the increased costs. Did Erobo violate the CFA Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Yes, because returns are lower than expected by the Partners.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Yes, because he did not disclose the increased costs to his Partners.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 35-36 Study Session 1-2-a, b Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and Standards. No violation took place. Erobo was not required to inform the Limited Partners regarding the increase in lighting fixtures as the increase in cost would not cause the overall project cost to escalate higher than the 15% budget variance contingency agreed within the partnership.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>18. A Central Bank fines a commercial bank for not following statutory regulations with regard to making specific non-performing loan provisions on three loans. Louis Marie Buffet, CFA, sits on the Board of Directors of the Commercial Bank as a non-executive director, representing minority shareholders. He also chairs the internal audit committee of the bank that determines the provisioning policy of the bank. Mercy Gatabaki, CFA is the bank&#8217;s external auditor and follows international auditing standards whereby she tests the loan portfolio by randomly selecting loans to check for compliance in all aspects of Central Bank regulations. Which Charterholder is most likely in violation of the Code and Standard?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Both.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Buffet.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Gatabaki. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Guidance for Standards I-VII&#8221;, CFA Institute 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 15 - 17 Study Session 1-2-a Demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and Standards to situations involving issues of professional integrity. Buffet sat on the audit committee that determined the bank&#8217;s provisioning provisions that were contrary to the statutory regulations of the Central Bank. As a result he most likely violated Standard I - Professionalism by not abiding by regulations of a regulatory body. Gatabaki did not violate Standard I - Professionalism as it is not apparent she knowingly facilitated the incorrect provisioning policy or even followed it. Auditors in the course of their audit sample files. As a result, it is possible Gatabaki did not even come across the files which were treated in a manner by the bank that was contrary to the Central Bank regulations. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 19 through 32 relate to Quantitative Methods</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Ethical and Professional Standards</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>19. An increase in which of the following items is most likely to result in a wider confidence interval for the population mean?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Sample size</choice>

		<choice id="B">Reliability factor</choice>

		<choice id="C">Degrees of freedom</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Sampling and Estimation,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 487-493 Study Session 3-10-j Calculate and interpret a confidence interval for a population mean, given a normal distribution with 1) a known population variance, 2) an unknown population variance, or 3) an unknown variance and a large sample size. An increase in the reliability factor (the degree of confidence) increases the width of the confidence interval. Increasing the sample size and increasing the degrees of freedom both shrink the confidence interval.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>20. The joint probability of returns, for securities A and B, are as follows: Joint Probability Function of Security A and Security B Returns (Entries are joint probabilities) Return on security B=30% Return on security B=20% Return on security 0.60 0 A= 25% Return on security 0 0.40 A= 20% The covariance of the returns between securities A and B is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">3.</choice>

		<choice id="B">12.</choice>

		<choice id="C">24.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Probability Concepts,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 391-392 Study Session 2-8-m Calculate and interpret covariance given a joint probability function. Expected return on security A = 0.6 x 25% + 0.4 x 20% = 15% + 8% = 23% Expected return on security B = 0.6 x 30% + 0.4 x 20% = 18% + 8% = 26% Cov (Ra,Rb) = 0.6 [(25 - 23)(30 -26)] +0.4 [(20 - 23)(20 - 26)] = 0.6(2 x 4) + 0.4(-3 x -6) = 0.6(8) +0.4(18) = 4.8 + 7.2 = 12.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>21. An analyst determines that approximately 99 percent of the observations of daily sales for a company are within the interval from $230,000 to $480,000 and that daily sales for the company are normally distributed. The standard deviation of daily sales (in $) for the company is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">41,667.</choice>

		<choice id="B">62,500.</choice>

		<choice id="C">83,333.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Common Probability Distributions,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, page 441 Study Session 3-9-j Determine the probability that a normally distributed random variable lies inside a given confidence interval. Given that sales are normally distributed, the mean is centered in the interval. Mean = ($230,000 + 480,000) / 2 = $355,000. 99 percent of observations under a normal distribution will be plus/minus three standard deviations. Thus, ($355,000 - $230,000)/3.0 = $41,667. It is also the case that ($480,000 - $355,000)/3.0 = $41,667.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>22. The least accurate statement about measures of dispersion for a distribution is that the:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">range provides no information about the shape of the data distribution.</choice>

		<choice id="B">arithmetic average of the deviations around the mean will always be equal to one.</choice>

		<choice id="C">mean absolute deviation will always be less than or equal to the standard deviation.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 307-308 Study Session 2-7-g Define, calculate, and interpret 1) a range and mean absolute deviation, and 2) the variance and standard deviation of a population and of a sample. The arithmetic sum of the deviations around the mean will always equal zero, not one.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>23. An analyst gathers the following information ($ millions) about the performance of a portfolio: Quarter Value at Beginning of Quarter (prior to inflow or outflow) Cash Inflow (Outflow) At Beginning of Quarter Value at End of Quarter 1 2.0 0.2 2.4 2 2.4 0.4 2.6 3 2.6 (0.2) 3.2 4 3.2 1.0 4.1 The portfolio&#8217;s annual time-weighted rate of return (%) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">8.</choice>

		<choice id="B">27.</choice>

		<choice id="C">32.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Discounted Cash Flow Applications,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 247-253 Study Session 2-6-c Calculate, interpret, and distinguish between the money-weighted and time- weighted rates of return of a portfolio and appraise the performance of portfolios based on these measures. The time-weighted rate of return is calculated by computing the quarterly holding period returns and linking those returns into an annual return. In this case, the quarterly holding periods are 2.4/2.2 = 1.0909, 2.6/2.8 = 0.9286, 3.2/2.4 = 1.3333, and 4.1/4.2 = 0.9762. The time-weighted return is thus (1.0909 x 0.9286 x 1.3333 x 0.9762) - 1 = 1.3185 - 1 = 0.3185 or 31.85%. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>24. A mutual fund manager wants to create a fund based on a high-grade corporate bond index. She first distinguishes between utility bonds and industrial bonds; she then, for each segment, defines maturity intervals of less than 5 years, 5 to 10 years, and greater than 10 years. For each segment and maturity level, she classifies the bonds as callable or non-callable. She then selects bonds from each of the subpopulations she has created. For the manager&#8217;s sample, which of the following best describes the sampling approach?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Systematic</choice>

		<choice id="B">Simple random</choice>

		<choice id="C">Stratified random</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Sampling and Estimation,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 476-479 Study Session 3-10-b Distinguish between simple random and stratified random sampling. In stratified random sampling, one divides the sample into sub-populations and randomly samples from within the subpopulations.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>25. An analyst conducts a significance test to determine if the relation between two variables is real or the result of chance. His null hypothesis is that the population correlation coefficient is equal to zero and his alternative hypothesis is that the population correlation coefficient is different from zero. He gathers the following information: Value of the test statistic 2.8092 Critical value at the 0.05 significance level 1.96 Critical value at the 0.01 significance level 2.58 The analyst most likely conducted a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">one-tailed test and can reject his null hypothesis.</choice>

		<choice id="B">two-tailed test and can reject his null hypothesis.</choice>

		<choice id="C">two-tailed test and cannot reject his null hypothesis.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Hypothesis Testing,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 517-524 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Study Session 3-11-a, c Define a hypothesis, describe the steps of hypothesis testing, interpret and discuss the choice of the null hypothesis and alternative hypothesis, and distinguish between one-tailed and two-tailed tests of hypotheses. Define and interpret a decision rule and the power of a test, and explain the relation between confidence intervals and hypothesis tests. Because the alternative hypothesis is that the correlation is different from zero (either above or below zero), the analyst conducted a two-tailed test. Because the test statistic is greater than either of the critical values, the analyst can reject the null hypothesis.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>26. The null hypothesis is most appropriately rejected when thep-value is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">negative.</choice>

		<choice id="B">close to one.</choice>

		<choice id="C">close to zero.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Hypothesis Testing,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 525-526 Study Session 3-11-e Explain and interpret the p-value as it relates to hypothesis testing. The p-value is the smallest level of significance at which the null hypothesis can be rejected. The smaller the p-value, the more strong the evidence against accepting the null as true, P-values close to zero strongly suggest the null hypothesis should be rejected.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>27. Under which measurement scale is data most likely categorized without being ranked?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Ordinal</choice>

		<choice id="B">Nominal</choice>

		<choice id="C">Interval</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 270 Study Session 2-7-a By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Differentiate between descriptive statistics and inferential statistics, between a population and a sample, and among the types of measurement scales. Data is categorized, but not ranked under a nominal scale. Under an ordinal scale data is ranked, while under an interval scale, data is ranked and separated by equal intervals.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>28. On 7 January 2008, an investor purchases 100 shares of stock for $32.50 a share. On 7 January 2009, the investor purchases 100 more shares of the same stock for $36.70 a share. On 7 January 2010, the investor sells all 200 shares of the stock for $42.00 a share. The internal rate of return for this investment is best described as an example of a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">geometric mean return.</choice>

		<choice id="B">time-weighted rate of return.</choice>

		<choice id="C">money-weighted rate of return.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Discounted Cash Flow Applications,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 246-247 Study Session 2-6-c Calculate, interpret, and distinguish between the money-weighted and time- weighted rates of return of a portfolio and appraise the performance of portfolios based on these measures. The money-weighted return is the internal rate of return for the portfolio.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>29. A 180-day U.S. Treasury bill has a holding period yield (HPY) of 2.375%. The bank discount yield (in %) is closest to :	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">4.640.</choice>

		<choice id="B">4.750.</choice>

		<choice id="C">4.875. Answer: A &#8220;Discounted Cash Flow Applications,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 253-257 Study Session 2-6-d, e Calculate and interpret the bank discount yield, holding period yield, effective annual yield, and money market yield for a U.S. treasury bill By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Convert among holding period yields, money market yields, effective annual yields, and bond equivalent yields. First, use the HPY to find money market yield: rMM = (HPY) x(360/t) = .02375 x (360 / 180) = 0.0475. Then use the money market yield to find the bond discount yield: rMM = (360 rBD) / ((360 - (t)( rBD)). In this case: 0.0475 = (360 rBD) / ((360</choice>

		<choice id="D" />

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Discounted Cash Flow Applications,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 253-257 Study Session 2-6-d, e Calculate and interpret the bank discount yield, holding period yield, effective annual yield, and money market yield for a U.S. treasury bill By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Convert among holding period yields, money market yields, effective annual yields, and bond equivalent yields. First, use the HPY to find money market yield: rMM = (HPY) x(360/t) = .02375 x (360 / 180) = 0.0475. Then use the money market yield to find the bond discount yield: rMM = (360 rBD) / ((360 - (t)( rBD)). In this case: 0.0475 = (360 rBD) / ((360 - (180)( rBD)). Now solve for rBD. 0.0475 x ((360 - (180)( tbd) = (360 tbd). 17.10 = (360 rBD) + 8.55 rBD. tbd = 17.10 / 368.55 = 0.046398.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>30. The sample variance based on the following data points: -6.0 percent, 5.8 percent, 8.4 percent, and 9.7 percent is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">0.000360.</choice>

		<choice id="B">0.003855.</choice>

		<choice id="C">0.005140.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 312-313 Study Session 2-7-g Define, calculate, and interpret 1) a range and mean absolute deviation, and 2) the variance and standard deviation of a population and of a sample. The sample mean is calculated as (-6.0% + 5.8% + 8.4% + 9.7%)/4 = 4.48% and the sample variance is ([-6.0% - 4.48%]2 + [5.8% - 4.48%]2 + [8.4% - 4.48%]2 + [9.7% - 4.48%]2) / (4-1) = 0.005140.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>31. An analyst determines that 60 percent of all U.S. pension funds hold hedge funds. In evaluating this probability, a random sample of 10 U.S. pension funds is taken. Tl! Using the binomial probability function, P(X = x) = ^n_xyx, Px0- ~ P)nx, the probability (in %) that exactly 6 of the 10 firms in the sample hold hedge funds is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">25.08.</choice>

		<choice id="B">27.99.</choice>

		<choice id="C">60.00.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Common Probability Distributions,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 428 Study Session 3-9-f Calculate and interpret probabilities given the discrete uniform and the binomial distribution functions. The number of trials is 10, the number of success is 6, and the probability of success is 0.60. P(X = 6) = , 10!, 0.66(1 - 0.6)10"6 = 0.250823. v J (10&#8212;6)!6! v J</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>32. An energy analyst forecasts that the price per barrel of crude oil five years from now will range between USD$175 and USD$205. Assume oil prices are a continuous uniform distribution. Recall that the cumulative distribution function for a continuous uniform variable is: for x&lt;a fW = x-a fora&lt;x&lt;b b-a for x&gt;b The probability (in %) that the price will be less than USD$180 five years from now is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">5.6.</choice>

		<choice id="B">16.7.</choice>

		<choice id="C">44.4.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Common Probability Distributions,&#8221; Richard A. Defusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 435-439 Study Session 3-9-h Describe the continuous uniform distribution, and calculate and interpret probabilities, given a continuous uniform probability distribution. The probability that the price per barrel of crude oil five years from now will be less than E1SD$80 (F(80)): F(80) - (180~175) = A = 1 = 0.166667, or 16.7%. (205-175) 30 6 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 33 through 44 relate to Economics</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Quantitative Methods</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>33. For a firm in perfect competition, as the quantity of labor increases, the marginal revenue product most likely diminishes because of a decline in:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">marginal product only.</choice>

		<choice id="B">marginal revenue only.</choice>

		<choice id="C">both marginal product and marginal revenue.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Markets for Factors of Production,&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p. 268 Study Session 5-21-a Explain why demand for the factors of production is called derived demand, differentiate between marginal revenue and marginal revenue product (MRP), and describe how the MRP determines the demand for labor and the wage rate. For a firm in perfect competition, as quantity of labor increases, marginal revenue product diminishes because marginal product diminishes.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>34. If a price cut of a product increases total revenue, demand is best described as:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">elastic.</choice>

		<choice id="B">inelastic.</choice>

		<choice id="C">unit elastic.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Elasticity,&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p.14 Study Session 4-13-b Calculate elasticities on a straight-line demand curve, differentiate among elastic, inelastic, and unit elastic demand, and describe the relation between price elasticity of demand and total revenue. A product&#8217;s demand is elastic if demand increases by a greater percentage than the percentage price cut when prices are cut. For example, if a 1 percent price cut increases the quantity sold by more than 1 percent, total revenue increases and demand is said to be elastic. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>35. Which of the following types of unemployment is most likely to be associated with an economy in which many workers have been made obsolete by changing technology?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Cyclical</choice>

		<choice id="B">Frictional</choice>

		<choice id="C">Structural</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Monitoring Jobs and the Price Level,&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p. 313 Study Session 5-22-c Explain the types of unemployment, full employment, the natural rate of unemployment, and the relation between unemployment and real GDP. Structural unemployment arises when changes in technology or international competition change the skills needed to perform jobs or change the locations of jobs.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>36. The free-rider problem, an obstacle to efficiency, is most likely associated with:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">monopolies.</choice>

		<choice id="B">public goods.</choice>

		<choice id="C">subsidies and quotas.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Efficiency and Equity,&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p. 50 Study Session 4-14-e Explain 1) how efficient markets ensure optimal resource utilization and 2) the obstacles to efficiency and the resulting underproduction or overproduction, including the concept of deadweight loss. Public goods can be consumed simultaneously by everyone and it is in each person&#8217;s interest to free ride on everyone else and avoid paying for her or his share of a public good.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>37. An expansionary fiscal policy is least likely to include an increase in:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">tax rates.</choice>

		<choice id="B">government borrowing.</choice>

		<choice id="C">government expenditures.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Fiscal Policy,&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 448-450 Study Session 6-26-d Discuss the use of fiscal policy to stabilize the economy, including the effects of the government expenditure multiplier, the tax multiplier, and the balanced budget multiplier. An expansionary fiscal policy means that government increases its purchases of goods and services and/or cuts tax rates to increase aggregate demand. As a consequence, government borrowing is likely to increase.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>38. For markets with perfectly elastic supply, the introduction of a tax will most likely result in:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">a price increase and the seller pays the entire tax.</choice>

		<choice id="B">a price increase and the buyer pays the entire tax.</choice>

		<choice id="C">no change in price and the seller pays the entire tax.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Markets in Action,&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 82-83 Study Session 4-15-c Explain the impact of taxes on supply, demand, and market equilibrium, and describe tax incidence and its relation to demand and supply elasticity. When supply is perfectly elastic (horizontal supply curve) the price increases by the amount of tax and the seller passes on the entire tax burden to the buyer.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>39. A company determines that the quantity demanded of a product increases by 5% when price is reduced by 10%. The product&#8217;s price elasticity of demand is best described as:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">elastic.</choice>

		<choice id="B">inelastic.</choice>

		<choice id="C">perfectly elastic.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Elasticity,&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 12-16 Study Session 4-13-a Calculate and interpret the elasticities of demand (price elasticity, cross elasticity, income elasticity) and the elasticity of supply and discuss the factors that influence each measure. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. When the price elasticity of demand is between 0 and 1, the good is said to have an inelastic demand. In this case, the price elasticity of demand is calculated as 5% / 10% = 0.5.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>40. In perfectly competitive industries what is the most likely final long-run effect of a permanent decrease in demand?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Price decreases.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Economic profit decreases.</choice>

		<choice id="C">The number of firms decreases.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Perfect Competition&#8221;, Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol.2, pp. 175-176 Study Session 5-18-d Discuss how a permanent change in demand or changes in technology affect price, output and economic profit. A permanent decrease in demand in a perfectly competitive industry will, in the short-run, cause the demand curve to shift to the left causing prices to fall and creating losses for producers. As the fall in demand is permanent, eventually firms will leave the industry due to these economic losses. As firms leave the industry the supply curve moves to the right thus increasing prices back to an equilibrium where economic profit is zero.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>41. If a regulatory agency sets prices equal to a monopoly&#8217;s long-run average cost (LRAC), the monopoly will most likely have economic profit that is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">zero.</choice>

		<choice id="B">positive.</choice>

		<choice id="C">negative.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Monopoly,&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 210-212 Study Session 5-19-e Explain the potential gains from monopoly and the regulation of a natural monopoly. If regulators set the price to equal long-run average cost, the monopolist will earn zero economic profits (Figure 11, p. 210). By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>42. When rent controls limit rents to prices below equilibrium prices, which of the following is most likely to occur?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">New housing construction expands.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Long-time tenants extract significant benefit from landlords.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Newcomers are given preferential entry into rent-controlled apartments.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>"Markets in Action&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p. 71-72 Study Session 4-15-a Explain market equilibrium, distinguish between long-term and short-term effects of outside shocks, and describe the effects of rent ceilings on the existence of black markets in the housing sector and on the market&#8217;s efficiency. Rent ceilings reduce construction and create a housing shortage. They lower rents for some but raise them for others. Long-time renters are winners but mobile newcomers are losers.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>43. Consider the following information regarding consumer price index (CPI) numbers for this year and last year._ CPI this year 267.54 CPI last year 261.25 The inflation rate (in %) for the period is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.35.</choice>

		<choice id="B">2.38.</choice>

		<choice id="C">2.41.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Monitoring Jobs and the Price Level&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 319-320 Study Session 5-22-d Explain and calculate the consumer price index (CPI) and the inflation rate, describe the relation between the CPI and the inflation rate, and explain the main source of CPI bias. The inflation rate is calculated as: ((CPI this year - CPI last year) / CPI last year) x 100. In this question, the inflation rate is ((267.54 - 261.25) / 261.25) x 100 = 2.407656. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>44. The quantity theory of money is best described as the proposition that, in the long run, an increase in the quantity of money brings a percentage increase in the price level that is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">equal.</choice>

		<choice id="B">lower.</choice>

		<choice id="C">higher.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>"Money, the Price Level, and Inflation&#8221; Michael Parkin 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, p. 385-387 Study Session 6-24-i Discuss the quantity theory of money and its relation to aggregate supply and aggregate demand. The quantity theory of money is the proposition that in the long run, an increase in the quantity of money brings an equal percentage increase in the price level. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 45 through 68 relate to Financial Statement Analysis</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Economics</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>45. According to the International Financial Reporting Standards framework, which of the following qualities of financial information is least likely to improve its reliability?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Neutrality</choice>

		<choice id="B">Consistency</choice>

		<choice id="C">Substance over form</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Standards&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 107-108 Study Session 7-31-d Describe the International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) framework, including the qualitative characteristics of financial statements, the required reporting elements, and the constraints and assumptions in preparing financial statements. The IFRS framework identifies five factors that contribute to reliability: faithful representation, substance over form, neutrality, prudence and completeness. Consistency is not one of them.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>46. The following information is available about a company ($ millions): Year ended 31 December 2009 2008 Sales 322.8 320.1 Net income 27.2 26.8 Cash flow from operations 15.3 38.1 During 2009 the company most likely decreased the:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">proportion of sales made on a cash basis.</choice>

		<choice id="B">inventory, anticipating lower demand for its products in 2010.</choice>

		<choice id="C">proportion of interest-bearing debt relative to trade accounts payable.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Understanding the Cash Flow Statement&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 267, 280-281 Study Session 8-34-g Analyze and interpret a cash flow statement using both total currency amounts and common-size cash flow statements. Sales, net income, and net margin are relatively constant for the two years. The substantial drop in cash flow from operations could be attributed to an increase in receivables and/or inventory. A decrease in the proportion of cash sales implies an increase in the proportion of credit sales, increasing accounts receivable. An increase in accounts receivable would decrease cash flow from operations.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>47. According to International Financial Reporting Standards which of the following is one of the conditions that must be met for revenue recognition to occur?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Costs can be reliably measured</choice>

		<choice id="B">Payment has been partially received</choice>

		<choice id="C">Goods have been delivered to the customer</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Income Statement&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 144-145 Study Session 8-32-b Explain the general principles of revenue recognition and accrual accounting, demonstrate specific revenue recognition applications (including accounting for long-term contracts, installment sales, barter transactions, and gross and net reporting of revenue) and discuss the implications of revenue recognition principles for financial analysis. The IASB&#8217;s conditions that must be met include that the costs incurred can be reliably measured, there is assurance of payment, not necessarily an actual receipt of any payment, and that the significant risks and rewards of ownership have been transferred, which is normally (but not always) when the goods have been delivered. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>48. A company accrued wages of $2,000 and collected accounts receivable of $10,000. Which of the following best describes the effect of these two transactions on the company?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Net income will increase</choice>

		<choice id="B">Current ratio will decrease</choice>

		<choice id="C">Cash from operations will decrease</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Cash Flow Statement&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 267-269, 275-276 &#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 328-329 Study Session 8-34-g, 8-35-d Analyze and interpret a cash flow statement using both total currency amounts and common-size cash flow statements. Calculate, classify, and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios. Accruing wages increases current liabilities and expenses, but collecting receivables has no effect on current assets or sales therefore the current ratio and net income both decrease. Collecting accounts receivable increases cash flow from operations and accruing wages increases current liabilities, which also increases cash flow from operations so cash from operations will increase not decrease.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>49. A company had 100,000 common shares outstanding on 1 January 2009. The company has no plans to issue additional shares or purchase treasury shares during the year, but is planning either a two-for-one stock split or a 100 percent stock dividend on 1 July. The number of shares used to determine earnings per share at 31 December 2009, will be closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">200,000 for both the stock split and the stock dividend.</choice>

		<choice id="B">200,000 for the stock split and 150,000 for the stock dividend.</choice>

		<choice id="C">150,000 for the stock split and 200,000 for the stock dividend.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Understanding the Income Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 170-172 Study Session 8-32-g Describe the components of earnings per share and calculate a company&#8217;s earnings per share (both basic and diluted earnings per share) for both a simple and complex capital structure. Stock dividends and stock splits are treated in the same way for purposes of determining weighted average number of shares outstanding; the adjustment in the number of shares is made as if the stock split or dividend occurred at the beginning of the year.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>50. Under International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) the preparation of a complete set of financial statements is best described as a(n):	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">objective of financial reporting.</choice>

		<choice id="B">general requirement for financial statements.</choice>

		<choice id="C">qualitative characteristic of the IFRS Framework.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Standards,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 111-112 Study Session 7-31-e Explain the general requirements for financial statements. The preparation of a complete set of financial statements is a general requirement for financial statements.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>51. Which of the following transactions will most likely result in a decrease in a company&#8217;s current ratio? The:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">recording of a warranty expense.</choice>

		<choice id="B">recording of revenue before cash is received.</choice>

		<choice id="C">payment of a property insurance policy for the following year.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Income Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 160 &#8220;Understanding the Balance Sheet,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 197 &#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 329 Study Session 8-32-c, 8-33-a, 8-35-d Discuss the general principles of expense recognition, such as the matching principle, specific expense recognition applications (including depreciation of long-term assets and inventory methods), and the implications of expense recognition principles for financial analysis. Illustrate and interpret the components of the balance sheet, and discuss the uses of the balance sheet in financial analysis. Calculate, classify and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios. The recording of a warranty expense will create a warranty liability and the resulting increase in current liabilities will decrease the current ratio.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>52. A company issued bonds in 2009 that mature in 2019. The measurement basis that will most likely be used on the 2009 balance sheet for the bonds is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">market value.</choice>

		<choice id="B">historical cost.</choice>

		<choice id="C">amortized cost.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Balance Sheet,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 223-225 Study Session 8-33-e, f Explain the measurement bases (e.g., historical cost and fair value) of assets and liabilities, including current assets, current liabilities, tangible assets, and intangible assets. Demonstrate the appropriate classifications and related accounting treatments for marketable and non-marketable financial instruments held as assets or owed by the company as liabilities. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Bonds payable issued by a company are financial liabilities that are measured at amortized cost.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>53. Which of the following transactions is least likely to increase a company&#8217;s reported cash from operations?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Securitizing accounts receivable</choice>

		<choice id="B">Delaying payments made to suppliers</choice>

		<choice id="C">Using short-term debt to reduce an existing account payable</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Accounting Shenanigans on the Cash Flow Statement,&#8221; Marc A. Siegel 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 592-595 Study Session 10-41 The candidate should be able to analyze and discuss the following ways to manipulate the cash flow statement: &#8226; stretching out payables &#8226; financing of payables &#8226; securitization of receivables &#8226; using stock buybacks to offset dilution of earnings. Using short-term debt to pay down payables will have no effect on the cash from operations. Payables will decrease which decreases cash from operations, but short-term debt will increase, which is an offsetting increase in cash from operations, resulting in no net effect on cash from operations.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>54. The settlement value for a liability is best described as:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">the amount of proceeds received in exchange for the obligation.</choice>

		<choice id="B">the discounted value of the future cash flows that are required to satisfy the obligation.</choice>

		<choice id="C">the undiscounted amount of cash or cash equivalents expected to be paid to satisfy the obligation.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Standards&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp.111 Study Session: 7-31-d Describe the International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS) framework, including the qualitative characteristics of financial statements, the required By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. reporting elements, and the constraints and assumptions in preparing financial statements. The settlement value for a liability is the undiscounted amount of cash or cash equivalents expected to be paid to satisfy the liabilities in the normal course of business.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>55. A company has just completed the sale of a tract of land for &#8364;3.5 million which was originally acquired at a cost of &#8364;2.0 million. The purchaser made a down&#172; payment of &#8364;200,000 with the remainder to be paid in equal installments over the next 10 years. A short time after the sale, significant doubt arose about the purchaser&#8217;s ability to meet the future obligations for the land purchase. When compared to the cost recovery method of revenue recognition, the profit (in &#8364;) that the company will recognize in the year of the sale under the installment method is most likely to be higher by:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">85,714.</choice>

		<choice id="B">114,286.</choice>

		<choice id="C">150,000.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Income Statement&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp.150-152 Study Session: 8-32-b Explain the general principles of revenue recognition and accrual accounting, demonstrate specific revenue recognition applications (including accounting for long-term contracts, installment sales, barter transactions, and gross and net reporting of revenue), and discuss the implications of revenue recognition principles for financial analysis; Under the installment method, the portion of the total profit of the sale (3.5 - 2.0 = 1.5) that is recognized in each period is determined by the percentage of the total sales price for which the seller has received cash, which is &#8364;1.5/&#8364;3.5 x &#8364;200,000 = &#8364;85,714; under the cost recovery method, no profit is recognized until the cash amounts received have exceed the seller&#8217;s cost of the property. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>56. Presented below are abbreviated balance sheets for two merchandising companies following the format found in each of their annual reports. Company A (in $ U.S. Millions) Company B (in &#165; Millions) Assets Assets Noncurrent assets 9,640 Current Assets 4,333 Current Assets 2,096 Noncurrent assets 19,923 Total Assets 11,736 Total Assets 24,256 Shareholders&#8217; Equity Liabilities &amp; Shareholders&#8217; Equity Issued Capital 2,490 Current liabilities 2,413 Retained Earnings 1,333 Non-Current Liabilities 6,847 Other Reserves 2,926 Minority Interests 506 Minority Interests 1,045 Total Equity 7,255 Shareholders&#8217; Equity Non-Current Liabilities 3,313 Issued Capital 5,149 Current liabilities 1,168 Retained Earnings 2,755 Total Liabilities 4,481 Other Reserves 6,047 Total Equity 13,951 Total Equity &amp; Liabilities 11,736 Total Equity &amp; Liabilities 24,256 Which of the companies most likely prepares their financial statements in accordance with U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles)?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Both</choice>

		<choice id="B">Company A only</choice>

		<choice id="C">Company B only</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Balance Sheet&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp.203-207 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Study Session: 8-33-b Describe the various formats of balance sheet presentation. Company A prepares its financial statements under IFRS while company B uses U.S. GAAP. The common practice under IFRS presentation is to present noncurrent assets before current assets and long term liabilities before current ones. Minority interest must be shown as a component of equity under IFRS. Under U.S. GAAP, current assets are presented before long term assets and current liabilities before long term ones; under U.S. GAAP, minority interest is often shown &#8220;in-between&#8221; liabilities and equity (although it could also be shown as an equity component).</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>57. An analyst makes the appropriate adjustments to the financial statements of retail companies that are lessees using a substantial number of operating leases. Compared to ratios computed from the unadjusted statements, the ones computed from the adjusted statements would most likely be higher for:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">the debt-equity ratio but not the interest coverage ratio.</choice>

		<choice id="B">the interest coverage ratio but not the debt-equity ratio.</choice>

		<choice id="C">both the debt-equity ratio and the interest coverage ratio.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Long-term Liabilities and Leases,&#8221; Elizabeth A. Gordon and R. Elaine Henry, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 537, 544-547 Study Session 9-39-g Determine the effects of finance and operating leases on the financial statements and ratios of the lessees and lessors. The adjustments to convert operating leases into capital leases would increase the amount of total debt in the debt-equity ratio thus increasing the ratio; the portion of the lease payment estimated to be lease interest expense would lower the interest coverage ratio.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>58. To gain insight into what portion of a company&#8217;s assets is liquid, an analyst will most likely use:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">the cash ratio.</choice>

		<choice id="B">the current ratio.</choice>

		<choice id="C">common-size balance sheets.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 312-315, 329 &#8220;Working Capital Management&#8221;, Edgar A. Norton, Jr. CFA, Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp 95-98 Study Session 8-35-a, 11-46-b Evaluate and compare companies using ratio analysis, common-size financial statements, and charts in financial analysis. Compare a company&#8217;s liquidity measures with those of peer companies. A common-size balance sheet expresses all balance sheet accounts as a percentage of total assets.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>59. An analyst gathers the following information ($ millions) about three companies operating in the same industry: Company Annual Depreciation Expense Accumulated Depreciation 1 10.8 58.9 2 27.8 80.3 3 33.6 128.8 Although the companies have different levels of sales and assets, they are all experiencing sales growth at about the same rate and use the same type of equipment in the manufacturing process. All three companies also use the same depreciation method. Which company is least likely to require major capital expenditures in the near future? Company:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">1.</choice>

		<choice id="B">2.</choice>

		<choice id="C">3.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Long-Lived Assets,&#8221; R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Elizabeth Gordon 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 438-439 Study Session 9-37-e Discuss the use of fixed asset disclosures to compare companies&#8217; average age of depreciable assets, and calculate, using such disclosures, the average age and average depreciable life of fixed assets. Company Average age of assets = accumulated depreciation/annual depreciation expense 1 58.9/10.8 = 5.5 years By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 2 80.3/27.8 = 2.9 years 3 128.8/33.6 = 3.8years Because Company 2 has the lowest average age of assets, it is least likely to need major capital expenditures</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>60. The following information (U.S. $ millions) for two companies operating in the same industry during the same time period is available: Company A Company B Net sales 120 300 Total assets 70 140 Total liabilities 25 40 If both companies achieve a return on equity of 15% for the period, which of the following statements is most likely correct? Compared to Company B, Company A has a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">higher net profit margin.</choice>

		<choice id="B">higher total asset turnover.</choice>

		<choice id="C">lower financial leverage multiplier.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA Modular 2010 Level I, Vol. 3 pp.342-344 &#8220;Financial Statement Analysis&#8221;, Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp.142-146 Study Session 8-35-d, f, 11-47 Calculate, classify, and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios The DuPont system can be used to break down the ROE into three components: ROE = Profit margin x total asset turnover x financial leverage multiplier. Component Company A Company B Total asset turnover (sales/total assets) 120/170 1.71 300/140 2.14 Company A has a lower total asset turnover, not higher Equity (total assets - total liabilities) 70-25 $45 140-40 $100 Financial leverage multiplier (assets/equity) 70/45 1.56 140/100 1.40 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Company A has a higher financial leverage multiplier, not lower Company A&#8217;s Net Profit Margin from ROE: = 15% = (net profit margin) x 1.71 x 1.56 Company A&#8217;s net profit margin = 5.6% Company A&#8217;s Net Profit Margin from ROE: = 15% = (net profit margin) x 2.14 x 1.40 Company A&#8217;s net profit margin = 5.0% The net profit margin could also be computed by computing net income for each company from the basic ROE definition: ROE = Net Income/Common Equity For Company A: ROE = 15% = net income/ (70-25); net income is 6.75, and net profit margin = net income/Sales = 6.75/ 120 = 5.6%.) For Company B: ROE = 15% = net income/ (140-40); net income is 15, and net profit margin = net income/Sales = 15/ 300 = 5.0%.) Company A has a higher net profit margin than Company B</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>61. Is the reversal of an inventory write-down permitted under U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) and International Financial Reporting Standards (IFRS)?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No, under both</choice>

		<choice id="B">Yes, under both</choice>

		<choice id="C">Yes under IFRS but not under U.S. GAAP</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Inventories,&#8221; Elbie Antonites, CFA and Michael Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 380-381 &#8220;International Standards Convergence,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 653-654 Discuss how inventories are reported in the financial statements and how the lower of cost or net realizable value is used and applied. Study Session 9-36-b, 10-43-a Discuss how inventories are reported in the financial statements and how the lower of cost or net realizable value is used and applied. Identify and explain the major international accounting standards for each asset and liability category on the balance sheet and the key differences from U.S. generally accepted accounting principles (GAAP). By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. The reversal of an inventory write-down is permitted under IFRS but not under U.S. GAAP.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>62. A retail company prepares its financial statements in accordance with U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles). Its purchases and sales of inventory s first two years of o perations are listed be ow. First Year Second Year Units Purchased 80,000 100,000 Unit Cost $8.43 $12.25 Units Sold 73,000 78,000 Unit Selling Price $15.00 $16.00 8,003. In its second year of operation, the company&#8217;s ending inventory is $3Z Which of the following inventory cost flow assumptions is the company was most likely using?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">FIFO</choice>

		<choice id="B">LIFO</choice>

		<choice id="C">Weighted average cost</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Inventories,&#8221; Elbie Antonites, CFA and Michael Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 382-384 Study Session 9-36-c Compute ending inventory balances and cost of goods sold using the FIFO, weighted average cost, and LIFO methods to account for product inventory and explain the relationship among and the usefulness of inventory and cost of goods sold data provided by the FIFO, weighted average cost, and LIFO methods when prices are 1) stable, 2) decreasing, or 3) increasing. The company is accounting for its inventory using the weighted average cost method. In the 2nd year of operations, under Weighted Average Cost: Units available for sale include ending inventory from year 1 plus purchases for year 2: 7,000 + 100,000 = 107,000 Cost of Goods Available for Sale: 7,000 x $8.43 + 100,000 x $12.25 = $1,284,000 Unit Cost: $1,284,000/107,000 = $12.00 End Inventory = 107,000 -78,000 = 29,000 units. $12.00 x 19,000 = $348,003 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>63. A company issued a $50,000 7-year bond for $47,565. The bonds pay 9 percent per annum and the yield-to-maturity at issue was 10 percent. The company uses the effective interest rate method to amortize any discounts or premiums on bonds. After the first year, the yield to maturity on bonds equivalent in risk and maturity to these bonds is 9 percent. The amount of the bond discount amortization ($) recorded in the second year is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">282.</choice>

		<choice id="B">348.</choice>

		<choice id="C">2,178.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Long-term Liabilities and Leases,&#8221; Elizabeth A. Gordon and R. Elaine Henry, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp.520-523 Study Session 9-39-a Compute the effects of debt issuance and amortization of bond discounts and premiums on financial statements and ratios. Interest paid = Market rate at issue x Issued amount of bonds = 9% x $50,000 Interest expense = Market rate at issue x Carrying (BV) of bonds Amortization of discount = Interest expense - Interest paid Year Interest Paid Interest Expense Amortization of Discount Carrying Value 0 47,565 1 4,500 4,757 257 47,822 2 4,500 4,782 282 48,104 Amortization in the 2nd year is 282 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>64. The following selected information is from a company&#8217;s most recent financial statements: (&#163; millions) 2009 2008 Sales 2,801 2,885 Cost of Goods Sold 1,969 2,071 Interest Expense 123 110 Cash &amp; Marketable Securities 108 105 Accounts Receivable 318 286 Inventories 248 285 Accounts Payable 361 346 Notes Payable 50 99 The 2009 cash conversion cycle, in days, is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">23.</choice>

		<choice id="B">26.</choice>

		<choice id="C">28.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 329-330 &#8220;Working Capital Management,&#8221; Edgar A. Norton, Jr., CFA, Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4 pp.89-93 Study Session 8-35-d, 11-46-c Calculate, classify and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios. Evaluate overall working capital effectiveness of a company, using the operating and cash conversion cycles, and compare its effectiveness with other peer companies. Activity Ratios Calculation Inventory Turnover 7.39 COGS/Average Inventory 1969/(248+285)/2 DOH (days on hand) 49.4 365/Inventory Turnover 365/7.39 Receivable Turnover 9.27 Sales/Average Receivables 2801/(318+286)/2 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. DSO (days sales o/s) 39.4 365/Receivables Turnover 365/9.27 Payables Turnover 5.57 COGS/Average Payables 1969/(361+346)/2 Days in Payables 65.5 365/Payables Turnover 365/5.57 Cash Conversion Cycle 23.3 DOH + DSO - Days In Pay 49.4 + 39.4 - 65.5</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>65. In the evaluation of credit ratings, a company will most likely be assigned a higher credit rating if it has a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">lower EBITDA/Interest ratio.</choice>

		<choice id="B">lower dividends-to-total-debt ratio.</choice>

		<choice id="C">higher five year average of its coefficient of variation of its operating margin.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&#8221; Richard A. DeFusco, CFA, Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and David E. Runkle, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 319-321 &#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques&#8221;, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 331-335 &#8220;Financial Statement Analysis: Applications,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2009 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 617-620 Study Session 2-7-i, 8-35-d, 10-42-c Define, calculate, and interpret the coefficient of variation and the Sharpe ratio. Calculate, classify and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios. Describe the role of financial statement analysis in assessing the credit quality of a potential debt investment. A lower dividend means more retention and increased equity: higher retained cash flow will result in a higher credit rating By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>66. A company purchased a &#8364;2,000 million long-term asset in 2009 when the corporate tax rate was 30 percent. Asset year end value for (All figures in &#8364; millions.) 2010 2009 Accounting purposes 1,800 1,900 Tax purposes 1,280 1,600 On January 15, 2010 the government lowered the corporate tax rate to 25 percent for 2010 and beyond. The deferred tax liability (&#8364;) as at 31 December 2010 is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">130.</choice>

		<choice id="B">156.</choice>

		<choice id="C">205.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Income Taxes,&#8221; Elbie Antonites, CFA and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 477-478, 483-484 Study Session: 9-38-d Calculate income tax expense, income taxes payable, deferred tax assets, and deferred tax liabilities, and calculate and interpret the adjustment to the financial statements related to a change in the income tax rate. The deferred tax liability equals the difference between the value for accounting and the value for tax times the current tax rate in effect. (1,800 - 1,280) x 0.25 = 520 x 0.25 = 130</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>67. Which of the following is least likely a condition present in a &#8220;fraud triangle&#8221;?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Constraining debt covenants.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Adding independent members to the Board of Directors.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Management&#8217;s belief that a decline in performance is due to temporary economic conditions.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Quality: Red Flags and Accounting Warning Signs,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA and Paul Munter 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 574 &#8220;The Corporate Governance of Listed Companies: A Manual for Investors,&#8221; 2010 Modular Level I, Vol.4, pp. 171-176 Study Session: 10-40-c, 11-48-c By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Describe the &#8220;fraud triangle&#8221;. Describe board independence and explain the importance of independent board members in corporate governance. The &#8220;fraud triangle&#8221; requires incentives (e.g., debt covenants), opportunities, and management&#8217;s ability to rationalize (temporary economic conditions). Adding independent members to the Board of Directors should improve corporate governance and hence decrease the opportunity for fraud.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>68. A company is buying back its stocks to offset the dilution of earnings from its stock option program. Which of the following statements best describes the effect on the financial statements of the amount spent to buy back the stocks? The amount spent reduces:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">net income.</choice>

		<choice id="B">cash from operating activities.</choice>

		<choice id="C">cash from financing activities.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Cash Flow Statement&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2020 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 251-252 &#8220;Accounting Shenanigans on the Cash Flow Statement,&#8221; Marc A. Siegel 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 595-598 Study Session 8-34-a, 10-41 Compare and contrast cash flows from operating, investing and financing activities and classify cash flow items as relating to one of these three categories, given a description of the items. The candidate should be able to analyze and discuss the following ways to manipulate the cash flow statement: &#8226; stretching out payables, &#8226; financing of payables, &#8226; securitization of receivables, and &#8226; using stock buybacks to offset dilution of earnings The amount spent to buy back stocks to offset dilution is classified as a financing activity on the cash flow statement and therefore cash from financing decreases. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 69 through 78 relate to Corporate Finance</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Financial Statement Analysis</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>69. A company is determining the cost of debt for use in its weighted average cost of capital. It has recently issued a 10-year, 6 percent semi-annual coupon bond for $864. The bond has a maturity value of $1,000. If the marginal tax rate is 35 percent, the cost of debt (%) they should use in their calculation is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.6.</choice>

		<choice id="B">3.9.</choice>

		<choice id="C">5.2.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Cost of Capital,&#8221; Yves Courtois, CFA, Gene C. Lai, and Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 42, 47-49 Study Session 11-45-b, f Describe how taxes affect the cost of capital from different capital sources. Calculate and interpret the cost of fixed rate debt capital using the yield-to- maturity approach and the debt-rating approach. The pre-tax cost of debt is the YTM of the bond. found by solving the following equation for i: f 20 &#8482; N The YTM of the bond can be 864 = ^ 30 "~r&gt; V*=1 y+l^J 1000 Using a financial calculator, enter N=20, PV=-864, PMT=30, and FV=1,000. Compute I/YR. The result (4%) is the semi-annual rate; double it to get the annual rate, 8%. This is the pre-tax cost of debt. Multiplying the pre-tax cost of debt by 1 - tax rate gives the result 5.2% (8 * 0.65 = 5.2). Note: because the bond pays coupons semi-annually, there are 20 periods (10 years times two payments per year) and the periodic coupon payment is $30 (6% of $1,000 per year paid in two equal payments every six months).</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>70. The post-audit performed as part of the capital budgeting process is least likely to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">improve a firm&#8217;s operations.</choice>

		<choice id="B">produce concrete ideas for future investments.</choice>

		<choice id="C">force management to revise the original forecast to match actual results. Answer: C</choice>

		<choice id="D" />

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Capital Budgeting,&#8221; John D. Stowe, CFA and Jacques R. Gagne, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 6-7 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Study Session 11-44-a Explain the capital budgeting process, including the typical steps of the process, and distinguish among the various categories of capital projects. The purposes of the post-audit process are to monitor forecasts, improve operations, and generate concrete ideas for future investments. The original forecast is, in effect, a &#8220;sunk cost.&#8221; The point is not to revise after the fact the original forecast, but to create a more accurate forecast over the new planning horizon.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>71. A company is considering building a distribution center on undeveloped land that it acquired more than ten years ago at a cost of $400,000. The company estimates the cost of putting in utilities, sewers, roads and other such costs of preparing the land for the distribution center at $200,000. Alternatively, the undeveloped land could be sold today to another company for $600,000. In evaluating this capital project, the investment outlay associated with the use of the land by the distribution center will most likely be:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$400,000.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$600,000.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$800,000. Answer: C</choice>

		<choice id="D" />

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Capital Budgeting,&#8221; John D. Stowe, CFA and Jacques R. Gagne, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 9-10 Study Session 11-44-b Discuss the basic principles of capital budgeting, including the choice of the proper cash flows. The investment outlay associated with the use of the land should reflect the opportunity cost of the foregone sale ($600,000) plus the incremental cost of preparing the land for use as a distribution center ($200,000). $600,000 plus $200,000 equals $800,000.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>72. When considering capital projects, which of the following statements is most accurate? Compared to the NPV method, the IRR method:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">can result in multiple values.</choice>

		<choice id="B">has the more appropriate reinvestment rate assumption.</choice>

		<choice id="C">uses more accurate estimates of the project&#8217;s cash flows. Answer: A By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</choice>

		<choice id="D" />

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Capital Budgeting,&#8221; John D. Stowe, CFA and Jacques R. Gagne, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 19-25 Study Session 11-44-e Explain the NPV profile, compare and contrast the NPV and IRR methods when evaluating independent and mutually-exclusive projects, and describe the problems associated with each of the evaluation methods. If the cash flows of the project are nonconventional, the IRR method can result in multiple IRRs.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>73. A company wants to determine the cost of equity to use in the calculation of its weighted average cost of capital. The CFO has gathered the following information: Rate of return on 3-month Treasury bills 3.0% Rate of return on 10-year Treasury bonds 3.5% Market equity risk premium 6.0% The company&#8217;s estimated beta 1.6 The company&#8217;s after-tax cost of debt 8.0% Risk premium of equity over debt 4.0% Corporate tax rate 35% Using the bond-yield-plus-risk-premium approach, the cost of equity (%) for the company is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">12.0.</choice>

		<choice id="B">16.3.</choice>

		<choice id="C">18.3.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Cost of Capital,&#8221; Yves Courtois, CFA, Gene C. Lai, and Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 57 Study Session 11-45-h Calculate and interpret the cost of equity capital using the capital asset pricing model approach, the dividend discount model approach, and the bond-yield-plus risk-premium approach. The cost of equity using bond-yield-plus-risk-premium approach is to take the before-tax cost of debt plus the risk premium of equity over debt. The before-tax cost of debt is the after-tax cost of debt divided by (1- tax rate). 8.0/(1 - 0.35) = 12.3%. Adding the risk premium results in a cost of equity of 12.3% + 4% = 16.3%. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>74. A publicly listed company has a 12-person Board of Directors whose composition is as follows: &#8226; the Chairman, who is the past president of the company and was named Chairman on his retirement date four years ago, &#8226; five members of senior management including the current president, and &#8226; six outside directors. Each member is elected for a two-year term and one-half of the positions stand for election every year. The three members of the Audit Committee are all outside directors and have relevant financial experience. The Remuneration Committee is composed of the Chairman and two outside directors. Which of the following actions would provide the greatest improvement in the corporate governance of this company?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">The Chairman of the Board should be an independent director.</choice>

		<choice id="B">All members of the Board of Directors should stand for election every year.</choice>

		<choice id="C">The company&#8217;s Vice-President of Finance should be a member of the audit committee.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Corporate Governance of Listed Companies: A Manual for Investors,&#8221; 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 174-185 Study Session 11-48-b, c Discuss and critique characteristics and practices related to board and committee independence, experience, compensation, external consultants and frequency of elections and determine whether they are supportive of shareowner protection. Describe board independence and explain the importance of independent board members in corporate governance. If the chair of the board is a former chief executive of the company, it may hamper efforts to undo the mistakes made by him or her as chief executive. It is not clear if it is better to have all members elected annually (more flexibility to meet changes in the marketplace) or if it is better to have staggered board terms (better continuity of board expertise). All members of the audit committee should be independent members of the board.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>75. Which of the following methods would be least likely to improve the cash collections of a retail organization?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Lockbox</choice>

		<choice id="B">Debit cards</choice>

		<choice id="C">Electronic checks</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Working Capital Management,&#8221; Edgar A. Norton, Jr., CFA, Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 116-118 Study Session 11-46-d Identify and evaluate the necessary tools to use in managing a company&#8217;s net daily cash position. A lockbox is a deposit system coordinated with a bank and is useful when the customer is not paying at the time of sale. In retail organizations, the customer normally pays at the time of sale and the best ways to improve cash collections are to ensure the payments made at that time have no credit risk for the seller. Debit cards, credit cards and electronic checks eliminate the credit risk for the seller.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>76. Assuming current assets and current liabilities remain a constant proportion of sales (30 percent and 20 percent respectively), as sales grow 5 percent annually, through time the current ratio will most likely:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increase.</choice>

		<choice id="B">decrease.</choice>

		<choice id="C">remain unchanged.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Statement Analysis,&#8221; Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol.4, pp. 151-159 Study Session 11-47 The candidate should be able to demonstrate the use of pro forma income and balance sheet statements. Because the proportion relative to sales does not change, the current ratio will remain unchanged.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>77. Which is least likely to be a component of a developing country&#8217;s equity premium?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Sovereign yield spread</choice>

		<choice id="B">Annualized standard deviation of the developing country&#8217;s equity index</choice>

		<choice id="C">Annualized standard deviation of the sovereign bond market in terms of the developing country&#8217;s currency</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. &#8220;Cost of Capital,&#8221; Yves Courtois, CFA, Gene C. Lai, and Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol.4, pp. 65-66 Study Session 11-45-j Explain the country equity risk premium in the estimation of the cost of equity for a company located in a developing market. The annualized standard deviation of the sovereign bond market in terms of the developing country&#8217;s currency is not part of the equity premium calculation. Country equity premium = sovereign yield spread * (annualized standard deviation of equity index ^ annualized standard deviation of the sovereign bond market in terms of the developed market currency)</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>78. A company extends its trade credit terms by four days to all its credit customers. The most likely effect of this change to the company&#8217;s credit customers is a four day:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increase in their operating cycle.</choice>

		<choice id="B">decrease in their operating cycle.</choice>

		<choice id="C">decrease in their net operating cycle.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>"Financial Analysis Techniques," Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, R. Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol.3, p. 329 &#8220;Working Capital Management&#8221; Edgar A. Norton, Jr., CFA, Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela P. Peterson, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol.4, page 101 Study Session 8-35-d; 11-46-c Calculate, classify, and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios. Evaluate the overall working capital effectiveness of a company, using the operating and cash conversion cycles, and compare its effectiveness with other peer companies. A four day increase in payables will reduce the cash conversion cycle (net operating cycle) by four days. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 79 through 90 relate to Equity Investments</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Corporate Finance</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>79. The issue of differences in accounting conservatism between companies is best addressed when companies are compared using which of the following ratios?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Price-to-earnings</choice>

		<choice id="B">Price-to-cash flow</choice>

		<choice id="C">Price-to-book value Answer: B</choice>

		<choice id="D" />

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Introduction to Price Multiples,&#8221; John D. Stowe, CFA, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 215-217 Study Session 14-59-a Discuss the rationales for, and the possible drawbacks to, the use of price-to- earnings (P/E), price-to-book value (P/BV), price-to-sales (P/S), and price-to-cash flow (P/CF) in equity valuation. Using price-to-cash flow rather than price-to-earnings addresses the issue of differences in accounting conservatism between companies (differences in quality of earnings).</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>80. A continuous market most likely exists for a stock when:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">specialists or market makers attempt to derive new equilibrium prices in an orderly manner.</choice>

		<choice id="B">new information about the company prospects is continuously released to market participants.</choice>

		<choice id="C">trades occur at any time the market is open wherein stocks are priced either by auction or by dealers.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Organization and Functioning of Securities Markets,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 14-15 Study Session 13-52-c Distinguish between call and continuous markets. In a continuous market, trades occur at any time the market is open and the stocks are priced either by auction or by dealers. The dealers provide liquidity for investors by buying and selling the shares of stock for themselves. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>81. Capital market efficiency is desirable, but there are limitations to achieving full market efficiency. Which of the following is least likely to be a limitation to achieving full capital market efficiency?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Survivorship bias</choice>

		<choice id="B">Limits of arbitrage</choice>

		<choice id="C">Cost of information</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Market Efficiency and Anomalies,&#8221; Vijay Singal, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 107-109 Study Session 13-55-a Explain the three limitations to achieving fully efficient markets. The three limitations for achieving full capital market efficiency are: 1) cost of information, 2) cost of trading, and 3) limits of arbitrage. Survivorship bias is not one of them.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>82. A price-weighted index series is composed of the following three stocks: Stock Number of Shares Outstanding Before Stock Split Market Price Before Split Day 1 Market Price After Split Day 3 X 1,000,000 $10 $12 Y 5,000,000 $20 $19 Z 4,000,000 $60 $22 If stock Z completes a three-for-one stock split at the end of Day 1, the value of the index after the split (at the end of Day 3) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">29.9.</choice>

		<choice id="B">31.7.</choice>

		<choice id="C">32.3.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Security-Market Indexes,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 46-48 Study Session 13-53-a Compare and contrast the characteristics of, and discuss the source and direction of bias exhibited by, each of the three predominant weighting schemes used in constructing stock market indices and compute a price-weighted, a value- weighted, and an unweighted index series for three stocks. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. The price-weighted index is computed by totaling the current prices of the stocks in the index and dividing the sum by a divisor that has been adjusted for stock splits and changes in the sample over time. Index before the split = (10 + 20 + 60) / 3 = 30; New divisor: [(10 + 20 + 20) / X] = 30; X = 1.67 Index after the split = (12 + 19 + 22) / 1.67 = 31.7</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>83. An analyst gathers the following information about a company: Net profit margin 8.0% Return on assets 10.0% Financial leverage (total assets/equity) 2.5 Beta for the company&#8217;s stock 1.5 Expected rate of return on the market index 10.0% Risk-free rate of return 5.0% The analyst expects the information above to accurately reflect the future. If the company wants to achieve a growth rate of 15% without changing its capital structure or issuing new equity, the company&#8217;s maximum dividend payout ratio (in %) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">25.</choice>

		<choice id="B">40.</choice>

		<choice id="C">60.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 342-347 &#8220;An Introduction to Security Valuation,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 158-159 Study Session 8-35-e, f; 14-56-g Demonstrate how ratios are related and how to evaluate a company using a combination of different ratios. Demonstrate the application of and interpret changes in the component parts of the DuPont analysis (the decomposition of return on equity). Describe a process for developing estimated inputs to be used in the DDM, including the required rate of return and expected growth rate of dividends. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. ROE = ROA x Financial leverage; Retention ratio = growth rate / ROE; Payout ratio = 1 - Retention ratio ROE = (10.0%)(2.5) = 25%; Retention ratio = 0.15/0.25 = 0.60; Payout ratio = 1 - 0.60 = 40.0%</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>84. A company has furnished the following information: Return on equity 20% Earnings retention rate 50% Current dividend per share (Do) paid on the company&#8217;s common stock &#8364;2.00 Required rate of return on the company&#8217;s common stock 15% Current stock price &#8364;50 Company&#8217;s P/E ratio 30x Industry average P/E ratio 20x Stock&#8217;s beta 0.7 According to the dividend discount model and the other data given, the company&#8217;s stock is best described as a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">growth stock.</choice>

		<choice id="B">cyclical stock.</choice>

		<choice id="C">speculative stock.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Security Valuation,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 142, 158 &#8220;Company Analysis and Stock Valuation,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 176-178 Study Session 14-56-c, f; 14-58-a Calculate and interpret the value of both a preferred stock and a common stock using the dividend discount model (DDM). Estimate the dividend growth rate, given the components of the required rate of return incorporating the earnings retention rate and current stock price. Differentiate between 1) a growth company and a growth stock, 2) a defensive company and a defensive stock, 3) a cyclical company and a cyclical stock, 4) a speculative company and a speculative stock, and 5) a value stock and a growth stock. A speculative stock is (i) substantially overvalued and (ii) it sells at an extremely high P/E ratio. The computations for intrinsic value are: Implied dividend growth By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. rate = ROE x RR = 20% x 0.5 = 10%; Intrinsic value of the stock = &#8364;2.20 / (15% - 10%) = &#8364;44.00 compared to the market price of &#8364;50. The stock's P/E is 30x versus the industry average of 20x.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>85. An investor opens a margin account with an initial deposit of $5,000. He then purchases 300 shares of a stock at $30. His margin account has a maintenance margin requirement of 30%. Ignoring commissions and interest, the price (in $) at which the investor receives a margin call is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">19.05.</choice>

		<choice id="B">23.08.</choice>

		<choice id="C">23.81.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Organization and Functioning of Securities Markets,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 26-28 Study Session 13-52-g Describe the process of buying a stock on margin, compute the rate of return on a margin transaction, define maintenance margin, and determine the stock price at which the investor would receive a margin call. Determine the stock price at which the investor receives a margin call by solving for the critical stock price, P, as: [(#of shares x P) - Margin Loan] / (# of shares x P) = % of Maintenance Margin (300P - $4,000) / 300P = .30; P = $4,000 / 210 = $19.05 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>86. The following information is from a company&#8217;s most recent financial statements: U.S. $ in millions except for shares outstanding and tax rate Preferred stock 40 Common stock 120 Additional paid-in capital 30 Retained earnings 190 Treasury stock (55d Total shareholders&#8217; equity 325 Total number of common shares outstanding 10 million Tax rate 40% The company uses the LIFO inventory method. The footnotes to the financial statements indicate that if the company had used the FIFO method, the inventory balance would have been $45 million higher than the amount reported on the company&#8217;s most recent financial statements. If the company&#8217;s common stock is currently selling for $59 per share, the company&#8217;s adjusted price-to book-value ratio is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">1.67.</choice>

		<choice id="B">1.79.</choice>

		<choice id="C">1.89. Answer: C &#8220;Inventories,&#8221; Elbie Antonites, CFA and Michael Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 396-402</choice>

		<choice id="D" />

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Inventories,&#8221; Elbie Antonites, CFA and Michael Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 396-402 &#8220;Introduction to Price Multiples,&#8221; John D. Stowe, CFA, Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jerald E. Pinto, CFA, and Dennis W. McLeavey, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 207-212 Study Session 9-36-g, 14-59-a, b Calculate adjustments to reported financial statements related to inventory assumptions to aid in comparing and evaluating companies. Discuss the rationales for, and the possible drawbacks to, the use of price to earnings (P/E), price to book value (P/BV), price to sales (P/S), and price to cash flow (P/CF) in equity valuation; Calculate and interpret P/E, P/BV, P/S, and P/CF. Adjusted book value equals shareholders' equity adjusted for equity claims that are senior to common stock and inventory method, and other adjustments related to pension and retirement plans. Dividing by the number of outstanding common shares results in the adjusted book value per share. Adj. price to book value ratio = Current stock price / Adj. book value per share Adj. book value per share = [$325 - $40 + $45(0.6)] / 10 = $31.20 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Adj. price to book value ratio = $59 / $31.20 = 1.89.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>87. An investor gathers the following data for a company: Net profit margin 2% Total assets $200 million Total liabilities $120 million Net income $10 million Dividends paid on common stock $2 million The company&#8217;s estimated dividend growth rate (in %) is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">8.0.</choice>

		<choice id="B">10.0</choice>

		<choice id="C">12.5.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, CFA, Jan Hendrik van Greuning, CFA, Elaine Henry, CFA, and Michael A. Broihahn, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 342-344 &#8220;An Introduction to Security Valuation,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 158-159 Study Session 10-35-e, f; 14-56-f Demonstrate how ratios are related and how to evaluate a company using a combination of different ratios. Demonstrate the application of and interpret changes in the component parts of the DuPont analysis (the decomposition of return on equity). Estimate the dividend growth rate, given the components of the required rate of return incorporating the earnings retention rate and current stock price. ROE = Net income / Equity; Retention rate = 1 - (Dividends / Net income); g = Retention rate x Return on equity Equity = $200 million - $120 million = $80 million; ROE = $10 million / $80 million = 12.5%. Alternatively using the DuPont Model: ROE = Return on assets x Financial leverage or Profit margin x Total assets turnover x Financial leverage; Sales = NI / NPM = $10 million / 0.02 = $500 million; TAT = 500 / 200 = 2.5 Financial Leverage = 200 / 80 = 2.5 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. ROE = 2 x 2.5 x 2.5 = 12.5% Retention rate = 1 - ($2 million / $10 million) = 80%; Growth rate = 12.5% x 80% = 10%.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>88. A company&#8217;s $100 par perpetual preferred stock has a dividend rate of 7 percent and a required rate of return of 11 percent. The company&#8217;s earnings are expected to grow at a constant rate of 3 percent per year. If the market price per share for the preferred stock is $75, the preferred stock is most appropriately described as being:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">overvalued by $11.36.</choice>

		<choice id="B">undervalued by $15.13.</choice>

		<choice id="C">undervalued by $36.36.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Security Valuation,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 134-135 Study Session 14-56-c Calculate and interpret the value of both a preferred stock and a common stock using the dividend discount model (DDM). Value of perpetual preferred stock = Dividend / Investor&#8217;s required rate of return $7/ 0.11 = $63.64. The stock is overvalued by $75.00 - 63.64 = $11.36.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>89. An equity analyst working for a growth oriented mutual fund has a tendency to misvalue the stocks of popular companies that she has previously recommended and the fund already owns. Her behavior is most likely consistent with which of the following biases?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Escalation bias</choice>

		<choice id="B">Prospect theory</choice>

		<choice id="C">Confirmation bias</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Efficient Capital Markets,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 89-90 Study Session 13-54-d Define behavioral finance and describe prospect theory, over-confidence bias, confirmation bias, and escalation bias. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Confirmation bias refers to the bias of looking for information that supports prior opinions and decisions, which leads to a tendency to misvalue the stocks of generally popular companies.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>90. A company earned $3 a share last year and just paid a dividend of $2 a share. The company&#8217;s dividends are expected to grow by 8 percent annually for the next two years. An investor with an 11 percent required rate of return expects to sell the stock at $75 two years from now. The maximum amount the investor should be willing to pay for this company&#8217;s stock (in $) today is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">58.68.</choice>

		<choice id="B">64.71.</choice>

		<choice id="C">66.63.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Security Valuation,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly, CFA and Keith C. Brown, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 138-141 Study Session 14-56-c Calculate and interpret the value of both a preferred stock, and a common stock, using the dividend discount model (DDM). V = D1 / (1 + k) + D2 / (1 + k)2 + SP2 / (1 + k)2 The value of the stock: 2($1.08) | 2($1.08)2 | $75 ?1 (1.11) (1.11)2 (111)2 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 91 through 96 relate to Derivative Investments.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Equity Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>91. When the underlying stock price is $95, an investor pays $2 for a call option with an exercise price of $95. If the stock price moves to $96, the intrinsic value of the call option would be closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">-$1.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$0.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$1.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Option Markets and Contracts&#8221;, Don M. Chance 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 98-101 Study Session 17-70-g Define intrinsic value and time value and explain their relationship. The intrinsic value of a call option is the stock price less the strike price if that difference is positive, and zero otherwise. The stock trading at $96 can be purchased for $95, so the intrinsic value is $1.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Derivative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>92. Margin in the futures market is most accurately described as a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">loan to the futures trader.</choice>

		<choice id="B">requirement set by federal regulators.</choice>

		<choice id="C">down payment from the futures trader.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Futures Markets and Contracts,&#8221; Don M. Chance 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 55-58 Study Session 17-69-c Differentiate between margin in the securities markets and margin in the futures markets and explain the role of initial margin, maintenance margin, variation margin, and settlement in futures trading. It is the amount of money that must be deposited into an account by a party opening a futures position; the money helps ensure that the party fulfills his/her obligation. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Derivative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>93. A derivative is most accurately defined as a financial instrument that provides:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">a return based on the return of another asset.</choice>

		<choice id="B">an adjustment to another asset&#8217;s level of risk.</choice>

		<choice id="C">an agreement between two parties to provide something for each other.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Derivative Markets and Instruments,&#8221; Don M. Chance 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 5-6 Study Session 17-67-a Define a derivative and differentiate between exchange-traded and over-the- counter derivatives. This is the definition directly out of the readings. Its return is derived from another underlying asset.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Derivative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>94. An investor enters into a 1 X 3 forward rate agreement (FRA) at a LIBOR rate of 1.5 percent. At expiration, the 60-day LIBOR rate is 1.7 percent and the 90-day LIBOR rate is 1.6 percent. Assuming the contract covers a $1 million notional principal, what payment will the investor most likely receive?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$249.00</choice>

		<choice id="B">$332.39</choice>

		<choice id="C">$333.33</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Forward Markets and Contracts&#8221;, Don M. Chance 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 40-43 Study Session 17-68-g Calculate and interpret the payoff of an FRA, and explain each of the component terms. B is correct because $1 million [(.017-.015)(60/360)/1+.017(60/360)] = $332.39. (0.017&#8212;0.015)(6%60)~ $1,000,000 X = $332 .A is incorrect because it uses a 90- i+o.oi7(60/360) day term: $1 million [(.016-.015)(90/360)/1+.016(90/360)] = $249.00 C is incorrect because it ignores TVM = $1 million (.017-.015)(60/360) = $333.33 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Derivative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>95. In comparison to a forward contract, a futures contract is most likely to be less:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">liquid.</choice>

		<choice id="B">publicized.</choice>

		<choice id="C">customized.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Futures Markets and Contracts&#8221;, Don M. Chance 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 51-53 Study Session 17-69-b Distinguish between futures contracts and forward contracts. The terms of a forward contract are customized to meet the needs of both parties. A futures contract is not customized rather, the exchange establishes the terms.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Derivative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>96. In what way is the payoff of a forward rate agreement (FRA) most likely different from the payoff of an interest rate option?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">It is based on a fixed exercise rate.</choice>

		<choice id="B">It is based on a notional principal amount.</choice>

		<choice id="C">It is paid immediately when the contract expires.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Option Markets and Contracts&#8221;, Don M. Chance 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 92-95 Study Session 17-70-d Compare and contrast interest rate options with forward rate agreements (FRAs). The payoff of a FRA is paid immediately when the contract expires. If at expiration the option is in-the-money and exercised, the payoff of an option is not paid immediately at expiration; it is paid at the end of the term of the underlying interest rate. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 97 through 108 relate to Fixed Income Investments.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Derivative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>97. An analyst determines that a 5.50 percent coupon option-free bond, maturing in 7 years, would experience a 3 percent decrease in price if market interest rates rise by 50 basis points. If market interest rates instead fall by 50 basis points, the bond&#8217;s price would increase by:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">exactly 3%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">less than 3%.</choice>

		<choice id="C">more than 3%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Introduction to the Measurement of Interest Rate Risk,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 524-528 Study Session 16-66-b Demonstrate the price volatility characteristics for option-free, callable, prepayable, and putable bonds when interest rates change. The bond is option-free and will therefore exhibit positive convexity. An equal change in rates will produce a greater percentage gain when rates decrease than the percentage loss produced when rates increase.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>98. Holding all other factors constant, an increase in expected yield volatility will cause the price of a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">putable bond to increase.</choice>

		<choice id="B">callable bond to increase.</choice>

		<choice id="C">putable bond to decrease.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated with Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 284 Study Session 15-61-n Explain how yield volatility affects the price of a bond with an embedded option and how changes in volatility affect the value of a callable bond and a putable bond. Increasing yield volatility increases the value of both put options and call options, which increases the value of a putable bond (which is long the put option) but decreases the value of a callable bond (which is short the call option.) By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. 99. The table below summarizes the yields and corresponding prices for a hypothetica 15-year option-free bond that is initially priced to yield 7%: Yield(%) Price($) 6.90 7.00 7.10 100.9254 100.0000 99.0861 Using a 10 basis point rate shock, the duration for this bond is closest to: A. 4.6 years. B. 7.5 years. C. 9.2 years. Answer: C &#8220;Introduction to the Measurement of Interest Rate Risk,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 532-533 Study Session 16-66-d Compute and interpret the effective duration of a bond, given information about how the bond's price will increase and decrease for given changes in interest rates, and compute the approximate percentage price change for a bond, given the bond's effective duration and a specified change in yield. Effective duration 100.9254-99.0861 2(100)(0.001) 92years</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>100. According to the market segmentation theory, an upward sloping yield curve is most likely due to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">investor expectations that short-term interest rates will fall in the future.</choice>

		<choice id="B">different levels of supply and demand for short-term and long-term funds.</choice>

		<choice id="C">an increasing yield premium required by investors for bearing interest rate risk.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding Yield Spreads,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 367 Study Session 15-63-c Explain the basic theories of the term structure of interest rates and describe the implications of each theory for the shape of the yield curve. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. The market segmentation theory asserts that the supply and demand for funds determine the interest rates for each maturity sector.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>101. An 8 percent coupon bond with a par value of $100 matures in 2 years and is selling at $98.24 to yield 9 percent. Exactly one year ago this bond sold at a price of $95.03 to yield 10 percent. The bond pays annual interest. The change in price attributable to the change in maturity is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$1.50.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$3.21.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$4.97.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Introduction to the Valuation of Debt Securities,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 404-406. Study Session 16-64-c, d Compute the value of a bond and the change in value that is attributable to a change in the discount rate; Explain how the price of a bond changes as the bond approaches its maturity date, and compute the change in value that is attributable to the passage of time. The price of the bond one year ago was $95.03 to yield 10%. If the yield stays at 10%, the price of the bond today is: 8 108 1.101 + 1.102 96.53 The change in price attributable to moving to maturity = $96.53 - $95.03 = $1.50.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>102. A fixed income portfolio manager owns a $5 million par value non-callable bond. The bond&#8217;s duration is 5.6 and the current market value is $5,125,000. The dollar duration of the bond is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$280,000.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$287,000.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$700,000.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated with Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 271 Study Session 15-61-f Compute and interpret the duration and dollar duration of a bond. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. A bond&#8217;s dollar duration is the expected price change given a 100 basis point change in yield. In this case, dollar duration = 5.6 x 0.01 x $5,125,000 = $287,000.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>103. Two amortizing bonds have the same maturity date and same yield to maturity. The reinvestment risk for an investor holding the bonds to maturity is greatest for the bond that is:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">a zero-coupon bond.</choice>

		<choice id="B">a coupon bond selling at a discount to par.</choice>

		<choice id="C">a coupon bond selling at a premium to par value.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated with Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 276-277 Study Session 15-61-i Identify the factors that affect the reinvestment risk of a security and explain why prepayable amortizing securities expose investors to greater reinvestment risk than nonamortizing securities. Because they have the same yield to maturity, we know that the bond selling for a premium has the higher coupon rate. Reinvestment risk refers to the risk that interest rates will decline causing the future income expected from reinvesting coupon payments to decline. The more coupon interest being paid, the greater the reinvestment risk.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>104. If investors expect stable rates of inflation in the future, the pure expectations theory suggests that the yield curve is currently:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">flat.</choice>

		<choice id="B">inverted.</choice>

		<choice id="C">upward-sloping.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding Yield Spreads,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 365-366 Study Session 15-63-c Explain the basic theories of the term structure of interest rates and describe the implications of each theory for the shape of the yield curve. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. The pure expectations theory explains the term structure in terms of expected future short-term interest rates. Assuming that interest rates reflect a relatively stable real rate of interest plus a premium for expected inflation, stability in inflation expectations would mean unchanged future short-term interest rates and a flat yield curve.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>105. A portfolio of option-free bonds is least likely to be exposed to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">volatility risk.</choice>

		<choice id="B">yield curve risk.</choice>

		<choice id="C">reinvestment risk.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated with Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 271-277, Study Session 15-61-a Explain the risks associated with investing in bonds. Volatility risk is the risk that the price of a bond with an embedded option will decline when expected yield volatility changes. By definition, option-free bonds are not affected by volatility risk.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>106. An investor purchases a 5 percent coupon bond maturing in 3 years for $102.80, providing a yield-to-maturity of 4 percent. At what rate must the coupon payments be reinvested to generate the 4 percent yield?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">0%</choice>

		<choice id="B">4%</choice>

		<choice id="C">5%</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Yield Measures, Spot Rates, and Forward Rates&#8221;, Frank J. Fabozzi, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 451 Study Session 16-65-b Compute and interpret the traditional yield measures for fixed-rate bonds and explain their limitations and assumptions. B is correct since the yield-to-maturity measure assumes that the coupon payments can be reinvested at an interest rate equal to the yield-to-maturity, in this case 4%. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>107. The yield of a U.S. bond issue quoted on a bond-equivalent basis is 6.8 percent. The yield-to-maturity on an annual-pay basis is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">6.69%.</choice>

		<choice id="B">6.92%</choice>

		<choice id="C">14.06%.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Yield Measures, Spot Rates, and Forward Rates&#8221;, Frank J. Fabozzi, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 457 Study Session 16-65-d Compute and interpret the bond equivalent yield of an annual-pay bond, and the annual-pay yield of a semiannual-pay bond. B is correct because the yield on an annual-pay basis is calculated as: [(1.034)2 - 1] = 6.92% The yield on an annual-pay basis is always greater than the yield on a bond- equivalent basis because of compounding.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>108. Given the data in the table below, the price of a 3% coupon corporate bond maturing in 2 years is closest to: Period Years to Maturity Spot Rate (%) Corporate Spread (%) 1 0.5 3.00 0.50 2 1.0 3.30 0.50 3 1.5 3.50 0.50 4 2.0 4.00 0.50	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$97.19.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$98.12.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$100.04.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Yield Measures, Spot Rates, and Forward Rates,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi, CFA 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 468473 Study Session 16-65-e Describe the methodology for computing the theoretical Treasury spot rate curve and compute the value of a bond using spot rates. A is correct because the cash flows should be discounted using the appropriate spot rate plus spread : By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Cash Flow 1 i Cash Flow 1 _ Cash Flow 1 _ Cash Flow 1 = (l + Zi)1 + (l + z2)2 + (l + z3)3 + (l + z,.)* _ 1.50 i 1.50 _ 1.50 _ 101.50 &#8221; (1.0175)1 + (1.019)2 + (1.02)3 + (1.0225)4 = 1.474 + 1.445 + 1.413 + 92.857 = 97.19 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 109 through 114 relate to Alternative Investments.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Fixed Income Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>109. A variation of which real estate valuation approach is most likely to use slope coefficients derived from a statistical analysis to estimate the value of a property?	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Cost approach.</choice>

		<choice id="B">Income approach.</choice>

		<choice id="C">Sales comparison approach.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 202-206 Study Session 18-73-e Describe the various approaches to the valuation of real estate. One variation of the sales comparison approach (hedonic price estimation) uses recent transactions in the area to derive an equation that weights various property attributes to determine a value for the property.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Alternative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>110. An investor has gathered the following data, presented on an annual basis, for an apartment complex that is being considered for purchase: Potential income (net of vacancy and collection losses ) $180,000 Insurance and taxes $15,000 Utilities $10,000 Repairs and maintenance $18,000 Depreciation $21,000 Interest on proposed financing $16,000 The annual net operating income (NOI) for the apartment complex is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$116,000.</choice>

		<choice id="B">$121,000.</choice>

		<choice id="C">$137,000.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 205-207 Study Session 18-73-f By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Calculate the net operating income (NOI) from a real estate investment, the value of a property using the sales comparison and income approaches, and the after-tax cash flows, net present value, and yield of a real estate investment NOI = $180,000 - $15,000 - $10,000 - $18,000 = $137,000.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Alternative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>111. Hedge funds that contain infrequently traded assets would most likely exhibit a downward bias with respect to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">measured risk but not correlations with conventional equity investments.</choice>

		<choice id="B">correlations with conventional equity investments but not measured risk.</choice>

		<choice id="C">both measured risk and correlations with conventional equity investments.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8217;&#8217;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey 2010 Modular Level I, Volume 6, pp. 228-229 Study Session 18-73-l Discuss the performance of hedge funds, the biases present in hedge fund performance measurement, and explain the effect of survivorship bias on the reported return and risk measures for a hedge fund data base. The presence of infrequently traded assets leads to smoothed pricing that induces a significant downward bias to the measured risk of the assets as well as reducing the correlations of returns with conventional equity and fixed income returns.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Alternative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>112. When the spot price of a commodity is above the futures price, the commodity market is said to be in:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">contango.</choice>

		<choice id="B">full carry.</choice>

		<choice id="C">backwardation.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Investing in Commodities,&#8221; Ronald G. Layard-Liesching 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 266-267 Study Session 18-74-a Explain the relationship between spot prices and expected future prices in terms of contango and backwardation. C is correct because when a commodity market is in backwardation, the futures prices is below the spot price as market participants believe the spot price will be By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. lower in the future. When spot prices are below the futures price, the market is said to be in contango.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Alternative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>113. When investing in commodities through a collateralized commodity futures position, the return associated with rolling forward the maturity of a futures contract is referred to as the:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">collateral yield.</choice>

		<choice id="B">spot price return.</choice>

		<choice id="C">convenience yield.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Investing in Commodities,&#8221; Ronald G. Layard-Liesching 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 268-269 Study Session 18-74-b Describe the sources of return and risk for a commodity investment and the effect on a portfolio of adding an allocation to commodities. C is correct because the roll or convenience yield is the return from rolling forward the maturity of the derivatives position. The roll yield can be either negative or positive.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Alternative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>114. A typical hedge fund fee structure is least likely to include a:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">base fee.</choice>

		<choice id="B">high water mark.</choice>

		<choice id="C">negative incentive fee.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8217;&#8217;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 220-221 Study Session 18-73-i Define hedge fund in terms of objectives, legal structure, and fee structure, and describe the various classifications of hedge fund. C is correct because the fee structure can include a base fee and &#8220;high water mark&#8221; but not a negative performance fee. The lowest performance fee would be zero. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose. Questions 115 through 120 relate to Portfolio Management.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Alternative Investments</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>115. Factors such as fluctuations in interest rates and changes in industrial production contribute to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">systematic risk.</choice>

		<choice id="B">unsystematic risk.</choice>

		<choice id="C">both systematic and unsystematic risk.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Asset Pricing Models,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 273-275 Study Session 12-51-c Define systematic and unsystematic risk and explain why an investor should not expect to receive additional return for assuming unsystematic risk. A is correct. Systematic (market-related) risk is caused by macroeconomic variables such as interest rate volatility and variability in industrial production. Unsystematic risk is caused by company-specific attributes.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Portfolio Management</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>116. When assessing the performance of a single investment fund, the asset allocation decision explains:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">a little less than 100% of the level of a fund&#8217;s returns.</choice>

		<choice id="B">about 90% of the fund&#8217;s variation in returns across time.</choice>

		<choice id="C">an average of 40% of the variation in returns of a fund across time.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Asset Allocation Decision&#8221;, Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 230-232 Study Session 12-49-e Describe the importance of asset allocation, in terms of percentage of a portfolio&#8217;s return that can be explained by the target asset allocation, and explain how political and economic factors result in differing asset allocations by investors in various countries. B is correct. Studies have shown that for a single fund, the asset allocation decision explains about 90% of the fund&#8217;s variation in returns across time and more than 100% of the level of return. Across all funds asset allocation explains an average of 40% of the variation in fund returns. By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Portfolio Management</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>117. According to the Capital Asset Pricing Model (CAPM) if investors borrow at a rate that exceeds the risk-free lending rate the resulting borrowing portfolios will:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">plot on a flatter line.</choice>

		<choice id="B">plot on a steeper line.</choice>

		<choice id="C">no longer plot on a straight line.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Asset Pricing Models,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 285-286 Study Session 12-51-d Explain the capital asset pricing model, including the security market line (SML) and beta and describe the effects of relaxing its underlying assumptions. A is correct. If investors borrow at a rate that exceeds the lending rate, the resulting borrowing portfolios will not be as profitable as the case where borrowing and lending is carried out at the same risk-free rate. The result is that borrowing portfolios will plot on a line with a flatter slope compared to borrowing portfolios constructed from borrowing at the risk-free lending rate.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Portfolio Management</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>118. Which of the following is not an assumption of the Markowitz model? Investors:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">have homogeneous expectations.</choice>

		<choice id="B">maximize one-period expected utility.</choice>

		<choice id="C">base decisions solely on expected return and risk.</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Portfolio Management,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p.241 Study Session 12-50-b List the assumptions about investor behavior underlying the Markowitz model. A is correct. This is not an assumption of the Markowitz model, it is an assumption of the Capital Asset Pricing Model (CAPM). By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Portfolio Management</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>119. The table below provides a probability distribution of stock returns for shares of Orion Corporation: Probability Rate of Return (%) 0.15 -12 0.60 11 0.25 18 The variance of returns for Orion Corporation stock is closest to:	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">44.36</choice>

		<choice id="B">50.94</choice>

		<choice id="C">88.71</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Portfolio Management,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp.242-244 Study Session 12-50-c Compute and interpret the expected return, variance, and standard deviation for an individual investment and the expected return and standard deviation for a portfolio. C is correct. The table below provides the calculation of the variance Probability (Pi) Rate of Return (%) Pi x R R - E( R) (R - E( R))2 Pi(R-E( R))2 0.15 -12 -1.8 -21.3 453.69 68.0535 0.6 11 6.6 1.7 2.89 1.734 0.25 18 4.5 8.7 75.69 18.9225 9.3 88.71 Expected return E( R) = 9.3% Variance of returns = 88.71 By accessing this mock exam, you agree to the following terms of use: This mock exam is provided to currently-registered CFA candidates. Candidates may view and print the exam for personal exam preparation only. The following activities are strictly prohibited and may result in disciplinary and/or legal action: accessing or permitting access by anyone other than currently-registered CFA candidates; copying, posting to any website, emailing, distributing and/or reprinting the mock exam for any purpose.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Portfolio Management</topic></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>120. For a retired 65-year-old investor, with moderate risk tolerance and adequate insurance and cash reserves, the appropriate portfolio will most likely have the following mix of bonds and stocks: Bonds Stocks</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">55-65% 35-45%</choice>

		<choice id="B">30-40% 60-70%</choice>

		<choice id="C">15-50% 50-85%</choice>

	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Asset Allocation Decision&#8221;, Frank K. Reilly and Keith C. Brown. 2010 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, p. 222 Study Session 12-49-c, d Describe the return objectives of capital preservation, capital appreciation, current income, and total return. Describe the investment constraints of liquidity, time horizon, tax concerns, legal and regulatory factors, and unique needs and preferences. A is correct. A moderately risk tolerant retired 65-year-old can structure his or her portfolio so that it provides income and some principal growth. The principal growth is needed because the time horizon is still fairly long. Such a portfolio could have an allocation of 55-65% in bonds and 35-45% in stocks.</comments>
<year filename="2010_afternoon_answer.xml">2010</year><topic>Portfolio Management</topic></problem>
</problems>