<problems>
<problem>
	<question>2. Dolores Bridgestone, CFA, manages small-cap portfolios for institutional clients. Bridgestone is convinced, given the  deteriorating economic conditions, that as a group, small-cap equities will underperform during the next 12-24 months. To  preserve her client's wealth, Bridgestone sells what she considers to be the most vulnerable small-cap equities. After  considerable research, she buys large-cap equities that she believes are better positioned to weather the expected economic  downturn. Has Bridgestone violated any CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, relating to suitability. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, relating to loyalty, prudence, and care. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, relating to diligence and reasonable basis. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook 2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 60-62 Study Session 1-2-b  According to Standard III(C), members who are responsible for managing a portfolio to a specifi c mandate, strategy, or style,  must only make investment recommendations or take investment actions that are consistent with the stated objectives and  constraints of the portfolio.  </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem>

<problem>
	<question>3. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, a supervisor establishing procedures to eliminate conflicts of interest  relating to personal trading would least likely recommend requiring:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">disclosure of holdings. </choice>
		<choice id="B">preclearance procedures. </choice>
		<choice id="C">a ban on employee investments. </choice>
		<choice id="D">duplicate confirmations of employee transactions. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook 2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 97 Study Session 1-2-c  recommend practices and procedures designed to prevent violations of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional  Conduct Banning employee investments is not recommended. According to Standard VI(B), investment transactions for  clients and employers must have priority over investment transactions in which a member or candidate is the benefi cial owner.  Recommended procedures for compliance with this Standard include establishing reporting procedures for investment  personnel. Recommended reporting requirements include disclosure of holdings; preclearance procedures; and duplicate confi  rmations of employee transactions. These reporting requirements are recommended for monitoring and enforcing procedures  established to eliminate confl icts of interest relating to personal trading.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>4. Which of the following may claim compliance with the Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS)?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Financial planners. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Portfolio managers. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Portfolio consultants. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Asset management firms. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Introduction to the Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS)  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 120  Study Session 1-3-a  explain why the GIPS standards were created, what parties the GIPS   standards apply to, and who is served by the standards  Only investment management firms that actually manage assets can claim compliance with the standards.  Compliance is a   firm-wide process that cannot be achieved on a single product, portfolio, or composite.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>5. The Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS) were created to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">provide GIPS-compliant firms with a competitive edge. </choice>
		<choice id="B">educate investors on misleading practices in performance measurement. </choice>
		<choice id="C">ensure fair representation and full disclosure of performance information. </choice>
		<choice id="D">impose CFA Institute Standards of Professional Conduct on nonmembers. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Introduction to the Global Investment Performance Standards (GIPS)  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 119-120  Study Session 1-3-a  explain why the GIPS standards were created, what parties the GIPS standards apply to, and who is served by the standards  In the past, the investment community had great difficulty making meaningful comparisons on the basis of accurate investment  performance data. The GIPS standards ensure fair representation and full disclosure of performance information.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>6. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, members are least likely required to disclose to clients their:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">service as directors. </choice>
		<choice id="B">beneficial ownership of stock. </choice>
		<choice id="C">firm's market-making activities. </choice>
		<choice id="D">responsibilities as CFA charterholders. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, p. 90  Study Sessions 1-1-c, 1-2-b  explain the ethical responsibilities required by the Code and Standards, including the multiple subsections of each Standard;  distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and the Standards  Members are not required to disclose their responsibilities as CFA charterholders to clients. They are, however, required to  disclose all matters that could reasonably be expected to impair their independence and objectivity or interfere with respective  duties to their clients, prospective clients, and employer. Service as a director, market-making activities, and beneficial  ownership of stock are three examples of such matters.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>7. According to the Standards of Practice Handbook, a member with supervisory responsibilities violates the CFA Institute  Standards of Professional Conduct when:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">delegating supervisory duties. </choice>
		<choice id="B">failing to prevent violations of the law. </choice>
		<choice id="C">failing to prevent violations of the CFA Code and Standards. </choice>
		<choice id="D">failing to establish and implement written compliance procedures. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 76-78  Study Sessions 1-1-c, 1-2-b   explain the ethical responsibilities required by the Code and Standards, including the multiple subsections of each Standard;  distinguish between conduct that conforms to the Code and Standards and conduct that violates the Code and the Standards  Members with supervisory responsibility must make reasonable efforts to detect violations of laws, rules, regulations, and the  Code and Standards. They exercise reasonable supervision by establishing and implementing written compliance procedures.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>8. Rachel Pederson, CFA, has managed the account of Olga Stefansson for the past decade and has a very good relationship  with her client. Stefansson has a beach house in the Bahamas and offers Pederson and her family two free weeks at the  house as a reward for the excellent returns generated in her account. Pederson is so busy at work she does not tell anyone  where she is going for vacation. When accepting Stefansson's offer, Pederson least likely violates the CFA Institute Standard  relating to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Loyalty to Employer. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Disclosure of Conflicts. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Independence and Objectivity. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Additional Compensation Arrangements. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 15-16, 83, 91, 113   Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 21-22, 69, 75, 89  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  The Standards require that members not accept gifts or compensation that might reasonably compete with their employer&#8217;s  interest unless they obtain written consent from all parties involved. Arrangements such as that offered to Pederson may cause  a conflict of interest or result in partiality that could impede Pederson&#8217;s independence and objectivity.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>9. Vera Abel, CFA, is the research director for ZigZag Investments. Abel discovers one of her top analysts trading in stocks in  advance of client transactions and repeatedly warns him that this activity is not appropriate. Does Abel violate any CFA  Institute Standards of Professional Conduct?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to fair dealing. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to responsibilities of supervisors. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to diligence and reasonable basis. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 93-94  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 76-77  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  The Standards require that members make reasonable efforts to detect and prevent violations of applicable laws, rules, and  regulations. Supervisors exercise reasonable supervision by establishing and implementing written compliance procedures and  ensuring the procedures are followed through periodic review. Once a supervisor learns of a possible violation, the supervisor  must promptly initiate an investigation. Warning the employee to cease the activity, as Abel has done, is not enough. Pending  the outcome of the investigation, Abel may need to place limits on the employee&#8217;s activities to ensure the violations will not be  repeated.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>10. After work each day, Shinichi Takada, CFA, runs a popular Internet blog where he comments on micro-cap stocks. The blog  includes a bio of Takada with his education and employment history. He receives no compensation for the blog. On the blog,  Takada recommends purchases and sales of stocks based upon astrology. When blogging, Takada least likely violates CFA  Institute Standard relating to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Fair Dealing. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Duty to Employer. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Loyalty, Prudence, and Care. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Diligence and Reasonable Basis. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Guidance for Standards I-VII, Standards of Practice Handbook   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 50-53, 69-70, 80-81  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  Takada&#8217;s use of astrology as a research methodology violates the Standards relating to Loyalty, Prudence, and Care as well as  Diligence and Reasonable Basis. His research methodology and blog may also reflect poorly on his employer and cause the  employer harm. Takada is least likely to violate the Standard relating to Fair Dealing because the blog is a method of mass  communication that makes Takada&#8217;s investment recommendations available to all readers simultaneously.  </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem>

<problem>
	<question>11. Jimmi Alvarez, CFA, is the founder of an investment advisory firm serving high net worth investors. For the past decade,  Alvarez has invested his clients' money in mid-cap stocks. After much research, Alvarez determines that small-cap stocks  are undervalued and moves a portion of all of his clients' assets into these stocks. Alvarez plans to inform his clients of this  change with their year-end statements in three months. Has Alvarez violated any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to misrepresentation. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to diligence and reasonable basis. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to communication with clients and prospective clients. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 105-107  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 84-85  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  According to the Standards, members must promptly disclose to clients any changes to their investment process. Alvarez  should notify his clients promptly of the change in his investment process and strategy.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>12. Scott Campbell, CFA, develops a complex quantitative model forSelecting mortgage bonds. Campbell is careful to  document in writing all assumptions in the model and his reasoning for the assumptions. Another firm offers Campbell a  position leading the startup of a mortgage bond research department. In his new position, Campbell creates a similar model  and supporting documents. Does Campbell violate any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to record retention. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to loyalty to employer. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to preservation of confidentiality. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 83-89, 111  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 70-74, 88  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  The Standards do not impose a prohibition on the use of experience or knowledge gained at one employer from being used at  another employer. Because records created on behalf of an employer are the property of the firm and not the member,  Campbell must take care not to use the property or records of his former employer when creating a model for his new  employer.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>13. Romar Brockman, CFA, is a sell-side analyst. Approximately half of Brockman's compensation comes from his firm's  investment-banking division. Brockman is asked to write a report about Anacortes Concrete (AC), an investment-banking  client. Despite concerns about the slowdown in concrete demand, Brockman issues a very positive report on AC. When  issuing his report, Brockman least likely violates the CFA Institute Standard relating to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Loyalty to Employer. </choice>
		<choice id="B" />
		<choice id="C">ent. Despite concerns about the slowdown in concrete demand, Brockman issues a very positive report on AC. When  issuing his report, Brockman least likely violates the CFA Institute Standard relating to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   A. Loyalty to Employer.  B. Disclosure of Conflicts.  C. Loyalty, Prudence, and Care. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Independence and Objectivity. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 113-115  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 89-91  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  The Standards require members to put client interests ahead of member and employer interests. Because Brockman&#8217;s  compensation is dependent upon investment banking revenues, Brockman may not be objective. When issuing the report, he is  in jeopardy of violating Standards relating to Independence and Objectivity; Loyalty, Prudence, and Care; and Disclosure of  Conflicts.                                                                                                             </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>14. Eric Pantoja is enrolled as a candidate in the CFA examination program. He works as an assistant for Chehalis Investments  (CI). Pantoja sees CI's purchase list and purchases several of the recommended stocks. Pantoja least likely violates the CFA  Institute Standard relating to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Misconduct. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Loyalty to Employer. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Priority of Transactions. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Diligence and Reasonable Basis. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 121-122  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 36, 70, 81, 94-95  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  Pantoja least likely violates the Standard relating to Diligence and Reasonable Care because he is taking investment actions on  his own behalf rather than on behalf of clients. His actions violate the Standards relating to Priority of Transactions (he trades  ahead of his employer and its clients), Loyalty to Employer (his actions cause harm to his employer), and Misconduct (his  actions reflect adversely on his professional integrity).    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>15. Fred Brubacher, CFA, is an analyst at Van City Bank (VCB). Brubacher receives compensation for referrals to the bank's  brokerage and personal financial-planning divisions. His recent referrals are long-time clients from his previous employer,  and Brubacher does not mention VCB's referral arrangement. Does Brubacher violate any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to suitability. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to misrepresentation. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to conflicts of interest. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 127  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 99  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  Compensation or other benefits received for the recommendation of products or services represents a conflict of interest.  According to the Standards, Brubacher must disclose the referral fee arrangement.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>16. Hailey Donnelly works long hours as an investment analyst and is studying for Level I of the CFA Examination. She is  concerned that she is not adequately prepared for the exam. Desperate to pass, Donnelly writes several formulas on a small  piece of paper which she takes into the examination room. During the exam Donnelly realizes that she does not need the  formulas. Has Donnelly violated any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to fair dealing. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to duty to employer. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to responsibilities as a CFA Candidate. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), p. 131  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 101-102  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  Candidates must not participate in any conduct which compromises the reputation or integrity of the CFA Examination.      </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>17. Abigail Unger, CFA, is a portfolio manager at Cascade Investments (CI). After thoroughly researching mortgage-backed  securities and checking client investment objectives for appropriateness, Unger purchases two of the bonds for several  clients. Following steep declines in the mortgage-backed securities, several clients complain to CI, claiming the bonds were  unsuitable investments. Has Unger violated any CFA Institute Standards?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">No. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Yes, with respect to suitability. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Yes, with respect to misconduct. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Yes, with respect to diligence and reasonable basis. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), pp. 25-27, 33, 69-71  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 29-30, 35, 60-62  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  Unger exercised diligence in her research; had a reasonable basis for the investment; and confirmed the suitability of the  investment for her clients. Her actions were consistent with the Standards of Professional Conduct.      </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>18. A. L. Guzdar is a portfolio manager at Woodstock Investments (WI). Guzdar manages a billion-dollar hedge fund and two  large mutual funds. Market declines cause significant losses for all of the accounts. Unable to find bids for certain  thinly-traded stocks, Guzdar trades the stocks between the accounts to provide liquidity and pricing. Guzdar least likely  violates the CFA Institute Standard relating to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">A. Misconduct. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Misrepresentation. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Market Manipulation. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Loyalty, Prudence, and Care. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>Standards of Practice Handbook, 9th edition (CFA Institute, 2005), p. 49  Standards I-VII  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 31, 36, 47, 50  Study Session 1-2-a  demonstrate a thorough knowledge of the Code of Ethics and Standards of Professional Conduct by applying the Code and  Standards to specific situations presenting multiple issues of questionable professional conduct  Guzdar least likely violates the Standard relating to Loyalty, Prudence, and Care as he attempted to provide liquidity to his  clients. However, Guzdar&#8217;s actions inflate trading volumes and distort prices and thus violate the Standard relating to Market  Manipulation. Guzdar violates the Standard relating to Misconduct because market manipulation reflects adversely on his  professional integrity. Guzdar may also violate the Standard relating to Misrepresentation if he misrepresents the actual  liquidity and value of the stocks held in the portfolios.      </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>19. A money manager has $1,000,000 to invest for one year. She has identified two alternative one-year certificates of deposit (CD) shown below: 
 Compounding frequency Annual interest rate 
CD1 
CD2 

Quarterly 
Continuously 

8.00% 
7.95% 

Which CD has the highest effective annual rate (EAR) and how much interest will it earn? 
 Highest EAR Interest earned 

A CD1 $ 81. 902 
B CD1 $ 82. 432 
C CD2 $ 82. 746 
D CD2 $ 83. 287  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following: </question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D</choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Time Value of Money,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 179-183  Study Session 2-5-c  calculate and interpret the effective annual rate, given the stated annual interest rate and the frequency of compounding, and  solve time value of money problems when compounding periods are other than annual  The effective annual rate (EAR) and interest earned on the alternative investments is:    Quarterly:   EAR = (1.02)4 - 1 = 1.082432 - 1 = 0.082432 = 8.2432%    Interest = $1,000,000 x 8.2432% = $82,432  Continuous:EAR =   e0.0795x1 = 1.082746 = 8.2746%    Interest = $1,000,000 x 8.2746% = $82,746    Therefore, the CD paying 7.95% compounded continuously offers the highest effective annual rate. Note that the EAR is the  same concept as the effective annual yield (EAY) presented in Reading 6.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>20. Jorge MacDonald is shopping for a home. His budget will support a monthly payment of $1,300 on a 30-year mortgage with  an annual interest rate of 7.2%. If MacDonald puts a 10% down payment on the home, the most he can pay for his new  home is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$189,755. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$191,518. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$210,840. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$212,800. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Time Value of Money,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 190-208  Study Session 2-5-d, e  calculate and interpret the future value (FV) and present value (PV) of a single sum of money, an ordinary annuity, an annuity  due, a perpetuity (PV only), and a series of unequal cash flows;  draw a time line, specify a time index, and solve time value of money applications (for example, mortgages and savings for  college tuition or retirement)  MacDonald&#8217;s budget will support a monthly payment of $1,300. Given a 30-year mortgage at 7.2%, the loan amount will be  $191,517.76 (N = 360, %I = 0.6, PMT = 1,300, solve for PV). If MacDonald makes a 10% down payment, then the most he  can pay for his new home = $191,517.76 / (1 - 0.10) = $212,797.51 ? $212,800. </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem>

<problem>
	<question>21. It is least appropriate to use the internal rate of return (IRR) rule to differentiate between mutually exclusive projects when  either the projects' scale or cash flow timing, respectively, is:    Scale of the projects Cash flow timing  A Similar Similar  B Similar Different  C Different Similar  D Different Different  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D</choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Discounted Cash Flow Applications,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 219-221  Study Session 2-6-a  calculate and interpret the net present value (NPV) and the internal rate of return (IRR) of an investment, contrast the NPV rule  to the IRR rule, and identify problems associated with the IRR rule  The IRR rule should not be used to differentiate between mutually exclusive projects if the scale of the projects differs or if the  timing of the projects&#8217; cash flows differs.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>22. An analyst gathered the following information about a common stock investment:   Date Amount  Stock purchase (1) 15 January 2006 &#8364;86.00  Stock purchase (1) 15 January 2007 &#8364;94.00  Stock sale (2@106) 15 January 2008 &#8364;212.00  The stock does not pay a dividend. The money-weighted and time-weighted rates of return on the investment are closest to:   Money-weighted  rate of return  Time-weighted  rate of return  A 11.02% 8.53%  B 11.02% 11.02%  C 11.60% 8.53%  D 11.60% 11.02%  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Discounted Cash Flow Applications,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 222-225  Study Session 2-6-c  calculate, interpret, and distinguish between the money-weighted and time-weighted rates of return of a portfolio and appraise  the performance of portfolios based on these measures  The money-weighted rate of return is the IRR based on the cash flows related to the investment. In this case, a cash outflow of  &#8364;86 occurs at t=0, another outflow of &#8364;94 occurs at t=1, and an inflow of &#8364;212 occurs at t=2. Using a financial calculator, the  IRR of these cash flows is 11.60%.  The time-weighted rate of return is the geometric mean of the annual rates of return in the stock irrespective of the amounts  invested in the various time periods. The rate of return for the first period is (94 - 86) / 86 = 9.3023% and for the second period  is (106 - 94) / 94 = 12.7660%. The geometric mean is (1.093023 x 1.127660)0.5 - 1 = 11.02%.     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>23. An analyst gathered the price-earnings ratios (P/E) for the firms in the SP 500 and then ranked the firms from highest to  lowest P/E. She then assigned the number 1 to the group with the lowest P/E ratios, the number 2 to the group with the  second lowest P/E ratios, and so on. The measurement scale used by the analyst is best described as:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">ratio. </choice>
		<choice id="B">ordinal. </choice>
		<choice id="C">interval. </choice>
		<choice id="D">nominal. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 242-243  Study Session 2-7-a  differentiate between descriptive statistics and inferential statistics, between a population and a sample, and among the types of  measurement scales  The analyst is using an ordinal scale which involves sorting data into categories based on some characteristic, such as the  firms&#8217; P/E ratios.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>24. Using Chebyshev's inequality, what is the minimum proportion of observations from a population of 500 that must lie  within two standard deviations of the mean, regardless of the shape of the distribution?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">71%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">75%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">89%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">99%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 289-291  Study Session 2-7-g  calculate and interpret the proportion of observations falling within a specified number of standard deviations of the mean,  using Chebyshev&#8217;s inequality  Chebyshev&#8217;s inequality holds for any distribution, regardless of shape, and states that the minimum proportion of observations  located within k standard deviations of the mean is equal to 1 - 1/k2. In this case, k = 2 and 1 - 1/4 = 0.75 or 75%.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>25. If a distribution exhibits positive skewness, then the mean most likely is located to the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">left of both the median and mode. </choice>
		<choice id="B">right of both the median and mode. </choice>
		<choice id="C">left of the median and right of the mode. </choice>
		<choice id="D">right of the median and left of the mode. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Statistical Concepts and Market Returns,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 297-302  Study Session 2-7-i  define and interpret skewness, explain the meaning of a positively or negatively skewed return distribution, and describe the  relative locations of the mean, median, and mode for a nonsymmetrical distribution  A positively skewed distribution has a long tail to the right with a large frequency of observations occurring in the left part of  the  distribution. For a distribution of returns, this means frequent small losses and a few extreme gains. The result is that the  extreme   gains pull the mean to the right while the mode resides on the left with the bulk of the observations. The median  falls between the mean and the mode.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>26. The manager of a pension fund determined that during the past five years 85% of the stocks in the portfolio have paid a  dividend and 40% of the stocks have announced a stock split. If 95% of the stocks have paid a dividend and/or announced a  stock split, the joint probability of a stock paying a dividend and announcing a stock split is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">10%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">30%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">45%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">55%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Probability Concepts,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 325-326  Study Session 2-8-e  calculate and interpret 1) the joint probability of two events, 2) the probability that at least one of two events will occur, given  the probability of each and the joint probability of the two events, and 3) a joint probability of any number of independent  events  The probability that at least one of two events will occur is the sum of the probabilities of the separate events less the joint  probability of the two events.     P(A or   B) = P(A) + P(B) - P(AB)     95% = 85% + 40% - P(AB); therefore P(AB) = 30%   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>27. Which of the following statements about a normal distribution is least accurate? A normal distribution:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">has a skewness of zero. </choice>
		<choice id="B">has an excess kurtosis of 3. </choice>
		<choice id="C">is completely described by two parameters. </choice>
		<choice id="D">can be the linear combination of two or more normal random variables. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Common Probability Distributions,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 389-390  Study Session 2-9-f  explain the key properties of the normal distribution, distinguish between a univariate and a multivariate distribution, and  explain the role of correlation in the multivariate normal distribution  A normal distribution has a kurtosis of 3. Its excess kurtosis (kurtosis - 3.0) equals zero.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>28. A portfolio manager gathered the following information about four possible asset allocations:     Allocation Expected annual return Standard deviation of  return  A 13% 6%  B 25% 14%  C 18% 17%  D 32% 20%  The manager's client has stated that her minimum acceptable return is 8%. Based on Roy's safety-first criterion, the most  appropriate allocation is:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Allocation A </choice>
		<choice id="B">Allocation B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Allocation C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Allocation D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Common Probability Distributions,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 397-399  Study Session 2-9-i  define shortfall risk, calculate the safety-first ratio, andSelect an optimal portfolio using Roy&#8217;s safety-first criterion  Roy&#8217;s safety-first ratio = [E(RP) - RL] / ?P   with the optimal portfolio having the highest ratio. The safety-first ratios for   the four allocations are:     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>29. An analyst gathered the following information:   Sample mean 12%  Sample size 50  Sample variance 32  The standard error of the sample mean is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">0.47%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">0.64%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">0.80%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">2.67%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Sampling and Estimation,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 428-429  Study Session 2-10-e  calculate and interpret the standard error of the sample mean  The standard error of the sample mean is the sample standard deviation (or the population standard deviation if known)  divided by the square root of the sample size. In this case, the standard error of the sample mean = 320.5 / 500.5 = 0.80%   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>30. Compared to the normal distribution, the Student's t-distribution most likely:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">has fatter tails. </choice>
		<choice id="B">is more peeked. </choice>
		<choice id="C">exhibits skewness. </choice>
		<choice id="D">has greater degrees of freedom. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Sampling and Estimation,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 436-438  Study Session 2-10-i  describe the properties of Student&#8217;s t-distribution, and calculate and interpret its degrees of freedom  The Student&#8217;s t-distribution has fatter tails and is less peeked compared to the normal distribution. </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem>

<problem>
	<question>31. The width of a confidence interval most likely will be smaller if the sample variance and number of observations,  respectively, are:   Sample variance Number of observations A Smaller Smaller  B Smaller Larger  C Larger Smaller  D Larger Larger  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Sampling and Estimation,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 436-438  Study Session 2-10-j  calculate and interpret a confidence interval for a population mean, given a normal distribution with 1) a known population  variance, 2) an unknown population variance, or 3) with an unknown variance and the sample size is large  The width of a confidence interval depends on the size of the standard error. The standard error will be smaller if the sample  variance (standard deviation) is smaller and the sample size n is larger.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>32. Which of the following steps in hypothesis testing most likely follows collecting the data and calculating the test statistic?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following: 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Stating the hypotheses. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Stating the decision rule. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Making the statistical decision. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Specifying the significance level. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Hypothesis Testing,&#8221; RichardA. Defusco, Dennis W. McLeavey, Jerald E. Pinto, and David E. Runkel  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 1, pp. 456-466  Study Session 2-11-a  define a hypothesis, describe the steps of hypothesis testing, interpret and discuss the choice of the null hypothesis and  alternative hypothesis, and distinguish between one-tailed and two-tailed tests of hypotheses  The seven steps in hypothesis testing are:  1) Stating the hypothesis.  2) Identifying the appropriate test statistic and its probability distribution.  3) Specifying the significance level.  4) Stating the decision rule.  5) Collecting the data and calculating the test statistic.  6) Making the statistical decision.  7) Making the economic or investment decision.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>33. Which of the following is the most likely effect of an increase in output on the marginal cost in the short run?   at low levels of output? at high levels of output?  A Decrease due to economies  from greater specialization  Decrease due to economies from  greater specialization  B Decrease due to economies  from greater specialization  Increase due to the law of  diminishing returns  C Increase due to the law of  diminishing returns  Decrease due to economies from  greater specialization  D Increase due to the law of  diminishing returns  Increase due to the law of  diminishing returns  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Output and Costs,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 129-130  Study Session 4-17-d  explain the firm&#8217;s production function, its properties of diminishing returns and diminishing marginal product of capital, the  relation between short-run and long-run costs, and how economies and diseconomies of scale affect long-run costs  Marginal cost decreases at low outputs because of economies from greater specialization. At higher levels of production, it  eventually increases because of the law of diminishing returns.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>34. A firm is said to be operating on its long-run average cost curve when:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following: 	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">it experiences constant returns to scale. </choice>
		<choice id="B">its long-run average cost curve is horizontal. </choice>
		<choice id="C">it produces a given output at the least possible cost. </choice>
		<choice id="D">it chooses a plant size that minimizes the average fixed cost. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Output and Costs,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 136-138  Study Session 4-17-d  explain the firm&#8217;s production function, its properties of diminishing returns and diminishing marginal product of capital, the  relation between short-run and long-run costs, and how economies and diseconomies of scale affect long-run costs  When a firm is producing a given output at the least possible cost, it is said to be operating on its long-run average cost curve.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>35. Key factors that influence the levels of structural and frictional unemployment in an economy, respectively, are:   Structural unemployment Frictional unemployment  A changes in technology changes in technology  B changes in technology unemployment compensation  C unemployment compensation changes in technology  D unemployment compensation unemployment compensation  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Monitoring Cycles, Jobs, and the Price Level,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 297-299  Study Session 5-22-c  explain the types of unemployment, full employment, the natural rate of unemployment, and the relation between  unemployment and real GDP  Structural unemployment refers to the unemployment due to changes in technology, changes in skills needed to perform jobs  or changes in the location of jobs. Frictional unemployment, on the other hand, is influenced by unemployment compensation.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>36. Which of the following are the most likely effects of an increase in tax on interest income on the investment demand and  interest rates, respectively?    Effect on investment demand Effect on interest rates  A No effect No effect  B No effect Increase  C Decrease No effect  D Decrease Increase  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Fiscal Policy,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 441-443  Study Session 6-27-b  discuss the sources of investment finance and the influence of fiscal policy on capital markets, including the crowding-out  effect  The quantity of investment that firms plan to undertake depends only on how productive capital is and what it costs - its real  interest rate. Therefore, a tax on interest income has no effect on investment demand. On the other hand, a tax on interest  income weakens the incentive to save as savers look at the after-tax real interest rate they receive. The interest rates would rise  as a result of the decrease in saving supply.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>37. The best description of the elasticity of supply of renewable and nonrenewable natural resources, respectively, is:    Renewable resource Nonrenewable resource  A perfectly elastic perfectly elastic  B perfectly elastic perfectly inelastic  C perfectly inelastic perfectly elastic  D perfectly inelastic perfectly inelastic  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Demand and Supply in Factor Markets,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 271-274  Study Session 5-21-g  differentiate between renewable and non-renewable natural resources and describe the supply curve for each   The quantity of land and other renewable natural resources is fixed and their supply is perfectly inelastic. On the other hand,  the flow supply of a nonrenewable natural resource (e.g., oil) is perfectly elastic.     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>38. For factors of production that differ in their supply elasticity, perfectly elastic or perfectly inelastic, the factor income is  entirely:    Perfectly elastic supply Perfectly inelastic  supply  A economic rent economic rent  B economic rent opportunity cost  C opportunity cost economic rent  D opportunity cost opportunity cost  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Demand and Supply in Factor Markets,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 275-277  Study Session 5-21-h  differentiate between economic rent and opportunity costs  When the supply of the factor is perfectly elastic (horizontal supply curve), the factor&#8217;s entire income comprises opportunity  cost. When the supply of the factor is perfectly inelastic (vertical supply curve), the factor&#8217;s entire income comprises economic  rent.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>39. Which of the following is the most likely effect of changes in inflation and/or unemployment on the Phillips curve?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">A change in the expected inflation causes a shift in both short-run and long-run Phillips curves. </choice>
		<choice id="B">A change in the natural rate of unemployment causes a shift in both short-run and long-run Phillips curves. </choice>
		<choice id="C">A change in the natural rate of unemployment causes a shift in the short-run but not the long-run Phillips curve. </choice>
		<choice id="D">If inflation falls below its expected rate, unemployment falls below its natural rate and there would be a movement up  along the short-run Phillips curve. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Inflation,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 414-418  Study Session 6-26-e  explain the impact of inflation on unemployment, and describe the short-run and long-run Phillips curve, including the effect  of changes in the natural rate of unemployment  A change in the natural rate of unemployment shifts both short-run and long-run Phillips curves. Suppose the natural rate of  unemployment increases from 6 to 9%, but the inflation remains constant at 10%. As a result, both short-run and long-run  Phillips curves move outward adjusting to the new, higher level of natural unemployment rate. The new point of intersection  between the two lines would be at 9% unemployment rate and 10% inflation rate (Figure 11, p. 418)   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>40. According to the feedback rule with productivity shocks, in order to stabilize the price level the most likely action by the Fed  and the resulting effect on real GDP, respectively, are:   Fed&#8217;s action Effect on real GDP  A Fed decreases the quantity of money the real GDP declines  B Fed decreases the quantity of money the real GDP remains constant  C Fed keeps the quantity of money constant the real GDP declines  D Fed keeps the quantity of money constant the real GDP remains constant  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Monetary Policy,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 473-475  Study Session 6-28-c  discuss the fixed-rule and feedback-rule policies to stabilize aggregate supply in response to a productivity shock and a  cost-push inflation shock  According to the feedback rule, when the price level rises the Fed decreases the quantity of money in order to reduce aggregate  demand. As a result, the price level as well as the real GDP would remain constant.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>41. In a perfectly competitive environment, a firm achieves maximum profit at the level of production where marginal revenue  and marginal revenue product of labor, respectively, are equal to:   Marginal revenue Marginal revenue  product of labor  A average cost wage rate  B average cost marginal product  C marginal cost wage rate  D marginal cost marginal product  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A </choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Demand and Supply in Factor Markets,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 253-256  Study Session 5-21-a  explain why demand for the factors of production is called derived demand, differentiate between marginal revenue and  marginal revenue product (MRP), and describe how the MRP determines the demand for labor and the wage rate  A change in total revenue that results from one more unit of labor is called the marginal revenue product of labor. In a  perfectly competitive market, profit is maximized when, at the quantity of labor hired, marginal revenue equals marginal cost  and marginal revenue product equals the wage rate. These two conditions are equivalent and the quantity of labor that  maximizes profit produces the output that maximizes profit.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>42. In regulating a natural monopoly, the pricing rule most commonly adopted by a regulator, and its effect on the firm's profit,  respectively, are:    Pricing rule Effect on firm&#8217;s profit  A average cost pricing the firm earns normal profit  B average cost pricing the firm incurs economic loss  C marginal cost pricing the firm earns normal profit  D marginal cost pricing the firm incurs economic loss  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D   </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Monopoly,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 198-200  Study Session 5-19-e  explain the potential gains from monopoly and the regulation of a natural monopoly  The marginal cost pricing rule is efficient but it leaves the natural monopoly incurring an economic loss. Therefore, regulators  almost never impose marginal cost pricing rule. Instead, they adopt the average cost pricing rule, which allows the firm to  cover its costs and earn a normal profit.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>43. Which of the following is the most accurate description of the determination of interest rates?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">The real interest rate is determined in the money market. </choice>
		<choice id="B">The nominal interest rate is determined in the capital market. </choice>
		<choice id="C">The real interest rate equals the nominal interest rate minus the expected inflation rate. </choice>
		<choice id="D">The nominal interest rate equals the real interest rate plus the unexpected inflation rate. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Inflation,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 419-421  Study Session 6-26-f  explain the relation among inflation, nominal interest rates, and the demand and supply of money  The real interest rate equals the nominal interest rate minus the expected inflation rate, which is the same as nominal interest  rate equals the real interest rate plus the expected inflation rate.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>44. The short-run effect of an increase in aggregate demand as a result of increases in government purchases on price level and  real GDP, respectively, are:    Effect on price  level  Effect on real GDP A increase increase  B increase no effect  C no effect increase  D no effect no effect  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Inflation,&#8221; Michael Parkin  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 2, pp. 402-405  Study Session 6-26-b  describe and distinguish among the factors resulting in demand-pull and cost-push inflation, and describe the evolution of  demand-pull and cost-push inflationary processes  An increase in aggregate demand as a result of an increase in government purchases, an example of demand-pull inflation,  leads to an increase in both price level and the real GDP (Figure 2, p. 402).   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>45. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following information about a company:   Cost of goods sold $18.4 million Average inventory $2.5 million Receivables turnover 24 times Payables payment period 25 days The company's cash conversion cycle is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">40 days. </choice>
		<choice id="B">59 days. </choice>
		<choice id="C">65 days. </choice>
		<choice id="D">90 days. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 590-593  &#8220;Working Capital Management,&#8221; EdgarA. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 89-92  Study Sessions 10-41-d, 11-46-a  calculate and interpret activity, liquidity, solvency, profitability, and valuation ratios;  calculate and interpret liquidity measures usingSelected financial ratios for a company and compare it with peer companies   The cash conversion cycle is equal to inventory processing days + days in accounts receivable - payables payment period.  Inventory turnover = $18.4 / $2.5 = $7.36.   Inventory processing days: 365 / inventory turnover = 365 / 7.36 = 49.59 days.  Days in accounts receivables: 365 / 24 = 15.21 days.  Cash conversion cycle: 49.59 + 15.21 - 25 = 39.8 days.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>46. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Two companies operating in the same industry both achieved the same return on owner's equity with  the same net sales,  but the two companies were different with respect to return on total assets. Compared with the company that had the higher  return on total assets, the company with the lower return on total assets most likely had a higher:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">net profit margin. </choice>
		<choice id="B">total asset turnover. </choice>
		<choice id="C">financial leverage multiplier. </choice>
		<choice id="D">proportion of common equity in the capital structure. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 604-607  Study Session 10-41-f  demonstrate the application of DuPont analysis (the decomposition of return on equity)  The DuPont system can be used to break down return on equity (ROE) into three components: Profit margin, total asset  turnover, and financial leverage multiplier.   The first two components can be multiplied to calculate the return on assets (ROA). If the two companies have the same ROE,  the company with the lower ROA must have a higher financial leverage multiplier (lower proportion of common equity in the  capital structure).   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>47. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  If an analyst is preparing common-size financial statements for several companies in the same industry, the most appropriate  way of expressing the interest expense for each company is as a percentage of:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">sales for the industry. </choice>
		<choice id="B">sales for that company. </choice>
		<choice id="C">total interest-bearing debt for the industry. </choice>
		<choice id="D">total interest-bearing debt for that company. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Analysis Techniques,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 574-576   Study Session 10-41-a  evaluate and compare companies using ratio analysis, common-size financial statements, and charts in financial analysis  Interest expense is an income statement account and the common-size percentage should be computed as a percentage of sales  for that company.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>48. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following information about three equipment sales that a company made at the end of the year:     Original Cost Accumulated  Depreciation  at Date of Sale  Sale  Proceeds  1 $200,000 $150,000 $70,000  2 $200,000 $200,000 $30,000  3 $300,000 $250,000 $40,000  All else equal for that year, the company's cash flow from operations will most likely be:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$40,000 less than net income. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$10,000 less than net income. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$10,000 more than net income. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$40,000 more than net income. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Cash Flow Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 271-273, 275-276  Study Session 8-34-f  demonstrate the steps in the preparation of direct and indirect cash flow statements, including how cash flows can be computed  using income statement and balance sheet data  Equipment sale 1 results in a gain of $20,000, sale 2 results in a gain of $30,000, and sale 3 results in a loss of $10,000. The  net gain is $40,000. The amount that would be deducted from net income to determine cash flow from operations is equal to  the net gain of $40,000.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>49. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  The following information is from a company's 2007 financial statements ($ millions):  Balances as of the year ended 31 December 2007 2006  Retained earnings 140 120 Accounts receivable 43 38 Inventory 48 45 Accounts payable 29 36 The company declared and paid cash dividends of $5 million in 2007 and recorded depreciation expense in the amount of  $25 million for 2007. The company's 2007 cash flow from operations ($ millions) was closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">10. </choice>
		<choice id="B">25. </choice>
		<choice id="C">30. </choice>
		<choice id="D">35. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Cash Flow Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 275-278  Study Session 8-34-f  demonstrate the steps in the preparation of direct and indirect cash flow statements, including how cash flows can be computed  using income statement and balance sheet data  The change in retained earnings is $20 and dividends are paid from retained earnings. 2007 net income would equal the change  in retained earnings plus any dividends paid during 2007. Depreciation expense would be added to net income and the changes  in balance sheet accounts would also be considered to determine cash flow from operations.  $20 + 5 (dividends) + 25 (depreciation) - 5 (increase in receivables) - 3 (increase in inventory) - 7 (decrease in payables) = $35  million.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>50. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  A company using the LIFO inventory method reported a $20,000 decrease in the LIFO reserve during the year that reduced the  LIFO reserve to $85,000 at year-end. If the company had used FIFO instead of LIFO in that year, the company's financial  statements would have reported:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">a lower cost of goods sold, but a higher inventory balance. </choice>
		<choice id="B">a higher cost of goods sold, but a lower inventory balance. </choice>
		<choice id="C">both a lower cost of goods sold and a lower inventory balance. </choice>
		<choice id="D">both a higher cost of goods sold and a higher inventory balance. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Analysis of Inventories,&#8221; Gerald I. White, AshwinpaulC. Sondhi, and Dov Fried   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 312-320  Study Session 9-35-c, d, e  compare and contrast the effect of the different methods on cost of goods sold and inventory balances, and discuss how a  company&#8217;s choice of inventory accounting method affects other financial items such as income cash flow, and working capital;  compare and contrast the effects of the choice of inventory method on profitability, liquidity, activity, and solvency ratios;  indicate the reasons that a LIFO reserve might decline during a given period and evaluate the implications of such a decline for  financial analysis  The negative change in the LIFO reserve would increase the cost of goods sold under FIFO compared to LIFO. FIFO COGS =  LIFO COGS - Change in LIFO reserve.  The LIFO reserve has a positive balance so that FIFO inventory would be higher than LIFO inventory. FIFO inventory = LIFO  inventory + LIFO reserve.  </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem>

<problem>
	<question>51. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  The year-end balances in a company's LIFO reserve were $56.8 million in the company's financial statements for both 2006 and  2007. For 2007, the measure that will most likely be the same regardless of whether the company used the LIFO or FIFO  inventory method is the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">current ratio. </choice>
		<choice id="B">inventory turnover. </choice>
		<choice id="C">gross profit margin. </choice>
		<choice id="D">amount of working capital. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Analysis of Inventories,&#8221; Gerald I. White, AshwinpaulC. Sondhi, and Dov Fried   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 320-325  Study Session 9-35-c, d  compare and contrast the effect of the different methods on cost of goods sold and inventory balances, and discuss how a  company&#8217;s choice of inventory accounting method affects other financial items such as income cash flow, and working capital;  compare and contrast the effects of the choice of inventory method on profitability, liquidity, activity, and solvency ratios  The LIFO reserve did not change from 2006 to 2007. Without a change in the LIFO reserve, cost of goods sold would be the  same under both methods. Sales are always the same for both, so gross profit margin would be the same in 2007. The FIFO  inventory would be higher because the LIFO inventory and LIFO reserve are added to compute FIFO inventory. Because the  inventory balances would be different under FIFO, the current ratio, inventory turnover, and net working capital would also be  different under FIFO.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>52. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following information about a company:  Shares of common stock 1,000,000  Net income for the year  $1,500,00  Par value of convertible bonds with a 4% coupon rate   $10,000,000  Par value of cumulative preferred stock with a 7% dividend rate  $2,000,000  Tax rate  30%   The bonds were issued at par and can be converted into 300,000 common shares. All securities were outstanding for the  entire year.  Diluted earnings per share for the company are closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$1.05. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$1.26. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$1.36. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$1.43. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Income Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA. Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 172-176  Study Session 8-32-h  describe the components of earnings per share and calculate a company&#8217;s earnings per share (both basic and diluted earnings  per share) for both a simple and complex capital structure  Dividends of $140,000 (0.07 x 2,000,000) should be deducted from net income to derive amount available for common  shareholders: $1,360,000 = (1,500,000 - 140,000). Basic EPS would be $1,360,000 / 1,000,000 or $1.36 per share. Diluted  EPS would consider the convertible bonds if they were dilutive. Interest on the bonds would be $400,000 and the after-tax add  back to net income would be $400,000 (0.7) or $280,000. Diluted EPS would be $1,640,000 / 1,300,000 shares assuming  conversion = $1.26 per share.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>53. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  At the beginning of the year, two companies issued debt with the same market rate, maturity date, and total face value. One  company issued coupon-bearing bonds at par and the other company issued zero-coupon bonds. All other factors being equal  for that year, compared with the company that issued par bonds, the company that issued zero-coupon debt will most likely  overstate:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">cash flow from operations but not interest expense. </choice>
		<choice id="B">interest expense but not cash flow from operations. </choice>
		<choice id="C">both cash flow from operations and interest expense. </choice>
		<choice id="D">neither cash flow from operations nor interest expense. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Analysis of Financing Liabilities,&#8221; Gerald I. White, AshwinpaulC. Sondhi, and Dov Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 466-475  Study Session 9-39-b, c  determine the effects of debt issuance and amortization of bond discounts and premiums on the financial statements and ratios;  analyze the effect on financial statements and financial ratios of issuing zero-coupon debt  When a company issues a zero-coupon bond, cash flow from operations is overstated over the life of the bond. Interest expense  is recorded for income statements purposes, but is added back in the statement of cash flows as a non-cash adjustment to cash  flow from operations.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>54. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst would find information about significant uncertainties affecting a company's liquidity, capital resources and results  of operations in the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">auditor's report. </choice>
		<choice id="B">notes to the financial statements. </choice>
		<choice id="C">balance sheet and income statement. </choice>
		<choice id="D">management discussion and analysis. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Statement Analysis: An Introduction,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 20  Study Session 7-29-c  discuss the importance of financial statement notes and supplementary information (including disclosures of accounting  methods, estimates and assumptions) and management&#8217;s discussion and analysis  Management must highlight any favorable and unfavorable trends and identify significant events and uncertainties that affect  the company&#8217;s liquidity, capital resources and results of operations in the MDA.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>55. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  When the financial statements materially depart from accounting standards and are not fairly presented, the audit opinion would  be a(n):  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">limited opinion. </choice>
		<choice id="B">adverse opinion. </choice>
		<choice id="C">qualified opinion. </choice>
		<choice id="D">disclaimer of opinion. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Statement Analysis: An Introduction,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 21  Study Session 7-29-d  discuss the objective of audits of financial statements, the types of audit reports, and the importance of effective internal  controls  An adverse opinion occurs when the financial statements materially depart from accounting standards and are not fairly  presented.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>56. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  When an issue is going to be put to a vote, by shareholders, at an annual general meeting the company prepares a(n):  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">annual report. </choice>
		<choice id="B">interim report. </choice>
		<choice id="C">proxy statement. </choice>
		<choice id="D">management statement of responsibility. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Statement Analysis: An Introduction,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 25  Study Session 7-29-e  identify and explain information sources other than annual financial statements and supplementary information that analysts  use in financial statement analysis  Proxy statements are prepared and distributed to shareholders on matters that are to be put to a vote at shareholder meetings.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>57. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Which of the following is least likely to be classified as a financial statement element?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Asset </choice>
		<choice id="B">Revenue </choice>
		<choice id="C">Liability </choice>
		<choice id="D">Net income </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Mechanics,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, Elaine Henry, and  MichaelA. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 37-39  Study Session 7-30-b  explain the relationship of financial statement elements and accounts, and classify accounts into the financial statement  elements  Net income is not an element of the financial statements, but the net result of revenues less expenses. The elements are: assets,  liabilities, owners&#8217; equity, revenue and expenses.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>58. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Bishop Ltd. received an advanced payment of $10,000 on December 1, for rent on a property for December and January. On  receipt they correctly recorded it as cash and unearned revenue. If at December 31, their year-end, they failed to make an  adjusting entry related to this payment, ignoring taxes, what would the effect on the financial statements for the year be?   Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Assets are overstated by $5,000 and Liabilities are overstated by $5,000.  </choice>
		<choice id="B">Liabilities are overstated by $5,000 and Net income is overstated by $5,000.  </choice>
		<choice id="C">Assets are overstated by $5,000 and Owner's equity is overstated by $5,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Liabilities are overstated by $5,000 and Owners' equity is understated by $5,000. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Mechanics,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, Elaine Henry, and  MichaelA. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 66  Study Session 7-30-e  explain the need for accruals and other adjustments in preparing financial statements  The company should have made an adjusting entry to reduce the Unearned revenue account (a liability) by $5,000 and increase  Revenue (and hence net income and retained earnings) by $5,000. As the company failed to make the adjusting entry the  liabilities are overstated and owners&#8217; equity is understated.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>59. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst gathered the following information from a company's accounting records:  Assets, December 31, 2007 $5,250,000  Liabilities, December 31, 2007 $2,200,000  Contributed capital, December 31, 2007 $1,400,000  Retained earnings, January 1, 2007 $800,000  Dividends declared during 2007 $200,000  The analyst's estimate of net income for 2007 would be closest to:   Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A"> $650,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B"> $850,000. </choice>
		<choice id="C"> $1,050,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D"> $1,850,000. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Mechanics,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, Elaine Henry, and  MichaelA. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 40-42  Study Session 7-30-c, f  explain the accounting equation in its basic and expanded forms;  prepare financial statements, given account balances or other elements in the relevant accounting equation, and explain the  relationships among the income statement, balance sheet, statement of cash flows, and statement of owners&#8217; equity  Total assets = liabilities + owner&#8217;s equity.   Owner&#8217;s equity = $5,250,000 - 2,200,000 = 3,050,000.   Owners equity = contributed capital + ending retained earnings.   Ending retained earnings = 3,050,000 - 1,400,000 = 1,650,000.   Ending retained earnings = beginning retained earnings + net income - dividends.  1,650,000 = 800,000 + NI - 200,000. Net income = $1,050,000   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>60. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  A financial reporting system has two components: the establishing of the rules or standards, and the enforcing of the rules. The  responsibility for those two components generally lies with which of the following bodies?    Establishing the rules Enforcing the rules  A Standard-setting bodies  Standard-setting bodies   B Standard-setting bodies  Regulatory authorities  C Regulatory authorities Standard-setting bodies   D Regulatory authorities Regulatory authorities   Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A"> Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B"> Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C"> Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D"> Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Standards,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, Elaine Henry, and  MichaelA. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 100-101  Study Session 7-31-b  explain the role of standard-setting bodies, such as the International Accounting Standards Board and the U.S. Financial  Accounting Standards Board, and regulatory authorities such as the International Organization of Securities Commissions, the  U.K. Financial Services Authority, and the U. S. Securities and Exchange Commission in establishing and enforcing financial  reporting standards  Standard-setting bodies such as FASB or IASB are responsible for making the rules and developing accounting standards,  whereas regulatory authorities such as the SEC, FSA, or IOSCO have the legal authority to enforce the standards.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>61. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Which of the following is least likely to be a characteristic of an effective financial reporting framework?   Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A"> Consistency </choice>
		<choice id="B"> Transparency </choice>
		<choice id="C"> Comparability </choice>
		<choice id="D"> Comprehensiveness </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Standards,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, Elaine Henry, and  MichaelA. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 122  Study Session 7-31-g  identify the characteristics of a coherent financial reporting framework and barriers to creating a coherent financial reporting  network  The characteristics of a coherent financial reporting network are transparency, consistency and comprehensiveness.  Comparability is a qualitative characteristic of financial statements.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>62. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An analyst has gathered the following data about Geneva Group Inc. and the health care industry in which it operates:   Geneva  Group  ($ millions)  Industry Averages  as a percent of sales  Revenues   5,000 100%  Cost of goods sold 2,100 45%  Operating expenses 1,750 32%  Profit margin 475 9.5%  Which of the following conclusions can the analyst reasonably make? Compared to the industry Geneva:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">spends less on nonoperating costs and income taxes. </choice>
		<choice id="B">has the same cost structure and net profit margin as the industry. </choice>
		<choice id="C">is better at controlling product costs, but less effective at controlling operating costs. </choice>
		<choice id="D">has a lower gross profit margin than the industry and spends more on its operating costs. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Income Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 181-182  Study Session 8-32-j  evaluate a company&#8217;s financial performance using common-size income statements and financial ratios based on the income  statement  The gross profit for Geneva = 5,000 - 2,100 = 2,900 or 58%. The gross profit for the industry is 1-.45 = 55%. Therefore,  Geneva&#8217;s cost of goods sold, or product costs, are lower; they must control them better. Operating costs are $1,750 / 5000 =  35% for Geneva and 32% for the industry, hence they are not as effective at controlling their operating costs as the industry.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>63. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Differences between accrued revenue and expenses and cash flows result in the creation of assets and liabilities. Would each of  the following revenue events result in the creation of an asset or a liability when the event originally occurs?    Revenue is recognized  before the cash is received.  Cash is received before the revenue is recognized.  A Asset Asset  B Asset Liability  C Liability Asset  D Liability Liability  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Reporting Mechanics,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Karen O&#8217;Connor Rubsam, Elaine Henry, and  MichaelA. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 53, 56  &#8220;Understanding the Balance Sheet,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA. Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 197  Study Session 7-30-d, 8-33-a  explain the process of recording business transactions using an accounting system based on the accounting equations;  illustrate and interpret the components of the assets, liabilities, and equity sections of the balance sheet, and discuss the uses of  the balance sheet in financial analysis  Revenue recognition before the cash is received will result in the creation of an accounts receivable, an asset, whereas when  the cash is received before the revenue is recognized a liability, unearned revenue, is created.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>64. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Lazlo Ltd, a European-based telecommunications provider, follows IASB GAAP and capitalizes new product development  costs. During 2007 they spent &#8364;25 million on new product development and reported an amortization expense related to a prior  year's new product development of &#8364;10 million. Other information related to 2007 is as follows:    in &#8364;  millions  Net income 225 Average assets 1,875 Cash flow from operations 290 An analyst would like to compare Lazlo to a U.S.-based telecommunications provider and has decided to adjust their  financial statements to U.S. GAAP. Under U.S. GAAP, and ignoring tax effects, the return on assets (ROA) and cash flow from  operations (CFO) for Lazlo would be closest to:   ROA CFO  millions  A 10.7% &#8364; 265  B 10.7% &#8364; 275  C 11.2% &#8364; 265  D 11.2% &#8364; 275  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D</choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Analysis of Long-Lived Assets: Part I - The Capitalization Decision,&#8221; Gerald I. White, AshwinpaulC. Sondhi, and Dov Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 354-356  Study Session 9-36-a, b  demonstrate the effects of capitalizing versus expensing on net income, shareholders&#8217; equity, cash flow from operations, and  financial ratios;  determine which intangible assets, including software development costs and research and development costs, should be  capitalized, according to U.S. GAAP and international accounting standards  If all development costs had been expensed then net income would be reduced by the amount spent, and increased by the  amortization of the previously capitalized amounts: 225 - 25 + 10 = 210 million. ROA = 210 / 1,875 = 11.2%. CFO would be  lower by the amount spent on development 290 - 25 = 265 million. Note: The amortization of previous development costs is a  non-cash expense so does not affect cash flow.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>65. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Which of the following best describes taxes payable?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Total liability for current and future taxes </choice>
		<choice id="B">Expense based on current period pre-tax income </choice>
		<choice id="C">Tax return liability resulting from current period taxable income </choice>
		<choice id="D">Actual cash outflow for income taxes including payments (refunds) for other years </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Analysis of Income Taxes,&#8221; Gerald I. White, AshwinpaulC. Sondhi, and Dov Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 423  Study Session 9-38-a  explain the key terms related to income tax accounting and the origin of deferred tax liabilities and assets  Taxes payable is the current liability resulting from the current period taxable income based on taxable income.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>66. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Madison Inc. is planning a bond issue. They are considering issuing either a straight coupon bond or a coupon bond with  warrants attached. The proceeds from either issue would be the same. What will be the effect on their interest expense and  balance sheet liability if they issue the bonds with warrants as compared to the straight bonds? For the bonds with warrants  the:    interest expense  will be  balance sheet liability will be  A lower lower  B lower higher  C higher lower  D higher higher  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Analysis of Income Taxes,&#8221; Gerald I. White, AshwinpaulC. Sondhi, and Dov Fried  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 486  Study Session 9-39-d  classify a debt security with equity features as a debt or equity security and demonstrate the effect of issuing debt with equity  features on the financial statements and ratios  The portion of the proceeds attributable to the warrants would be classified as equity, thus the portion classified as a liability  would be smaller (lower). The lower balance sheet value would lead to a lower interest expense when it is calculated. The  interest expense is based on the liability at the beginning of the period, not the coupon payment.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>67. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Kim Lee, CFA, is trying to forecast net income for Robinson's Ltd, a chain of retail furniture outlets. He has prepared the  following common sized data from their recent annual report and has estimated sales for 2008 using a forecasting model his  firm developed for consumer goods.    2008  forecast  2007  actual  2006  actual  Sales $ millions 2,250 2,150 1,990  Sales as % of sales  100.00% 100.00%  Cost of goods sold  45.00% 45.00%  Operating expenses  40.00%  40.00%  Interest expense  3.72% 4.02%  Restructuring  expense   0% 7.2%  Pre-tax margin  11.28% 3.78%  Taxes (35%)  3.95% 1.32%  Net income  7.33% 2.46%  The capital structure of the company has not changed. The projected net income (in $ millions) for 2008 is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">110.1. </choice>
		<choice id="B">162.8. </choice>
		<choice id="C">164.9. </choice>
		<choice id="D">167.4. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Financial Statement Analysis: Applications,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 641-646  Study Session 10-42-b  prepare a basic projection of a company&#8217;s future net income and cash flow  The cost of goods sold and operating expenses are relatively constant over the   two-year period and averages of them can reasonably be used to forecast 2008.   Interest expense is declining as a percent of sales, implying it is a fixed   cost. Conversion into dollars for each year shows what interest expense has been   (2007 = $80, 2006 = $80) and that would be a reasonable projected amount to use.   The restructuring charge should not be included as it is a non-recurring item.   The tax rate, 35%, is given.           </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>68. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  Where are the unrealized gains and losses arising from changes in the market value of available-for-sale securities reported  under U.S. GAAP and IFRS? They are reported in:   U.S. GAAP IFRS  A equity equity  B equity Income statement  C Income statement equity  D Income statement income statement  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Understanding the Income Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 186  &#8220;International Standards Convergence,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Jan Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, p. 682  Study Sessions 8-32-k, 10-43-a  state the accounting classification for items that are excluded from the income statement but affect owners&#8217; equity, and list the  major types of items receiving that treatment; identify and explain the major international accounting standards for each asset  and liability category on the balance sheet and the key differences from U.S. generally accepted accounting principles (GAAP)  Under both U.S. GAAP and IFRS the unrealized gains and losses arising from carrying available-for-sale securities at market  value are reported in equity as part of accumulated other comprehensive income.     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>69. A large corporation recently decided to accept a project with a negative net present value. That project most likely is  classified in which of the following categories?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Expansion project. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Replacement project. </choice>
		<choice id="C">New product or service. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Regulatory or environmental project. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Capital Budgeting,&#8221; JohnD. Stowe and Jacques R. Gagn&#233;  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 8-10  Study Session 11-44-a  explain the capital budgeting process, including the typical steps of the process, and distinguish among the various categories  of capital projects  Regulatory, safety, and environmental projects are often mandated by governmental agencies. The corporation may be  required to install equipment to meet a regulatory standard, and the cost of satisfying the standard is born by the corporation.  In this case, the corporationSelects the lowest cost alternative that meets the requirement, i.e., the alternative with the least  negative net present value.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>70. Howard Quarries has recently opened a limestone quarry at a location outside their traditional service area. Because  limestone is a major ingredient in concrete, if the quarry is successful Howard plans to build a ready-mix concrete plant at  the same location. The investment in the concrete plant is best described as:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">an externality. </choice>
		<choice id="B">project sequencing. </choice>
		<choice id="C">a mutually exclusive project. </choice>
		<choice id="D">an example of investment synergy. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Capital Budgeting,&#8221; JohnD. Stowe and Jacques R. Gagn&#233;  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 10-12  Study Session 11-44-c  explain how the following project interactions affect the evaluation of a capital project: (1) independent versus mutually  exclusive projects, (2) project sequencing, and (3) unlimited funds versus capital rationing  Project sequencing occurs when the investment in one project creates the option to invest in future projects.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>71. An analyst determined the following cash flows for a capital project:  Year 0 1 2 3 4 5  Cash flow (&#8364;) -100 30 40 40 30 20  The required rate of return for the project is 13%. The net present value (NPV) and the profitability index for the project,  respectively, are closest to:   NVP Profitability index  A &#8364;14.85 1.15  B &#8364;14.85 1.30  C &#8364;29.78 1.15  D &#8364;29.78 1.30  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Capital Budgeting,&#8221; JohnD. Stowe and Jacques R. Gagn&#233;  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 12-19  Study Session 11-44-d  calculate and interpret the results using each of the following methods to evaluate a single capital project: net present value  (NPV), internal rate of return (IRR), payback period, discounted payback period, average accounting rate of return (AAR), and  profitability index (PI)  Using a calculator with a 13% discount rate, the NPV is &#8364;14.85.  The profitability index = 1 + (NPV / initial investment) = 1 + 14.85 / 100) = 1.15.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>72. An analyst gathered the following information about the capital structure and before-tax component costs for a company.  The company's marginal tax rate is 40%.  Capital  component  Book Value  (000)  Market Value (000) Component cost  Debt $100 $80 8%  Preferred stock $20 $20 10%  Common stock $100 $200 12%  The company's weighted average cost of capital (WACC) is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">8.55%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">9.95%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">10.00%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">10.80%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Cost of Capital,&#8221; Yves Courtois, GeneC. Lai, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I,   Vol. 4, pp. 38-43  Study Session 11-45-a, c  calculate and interpret the weighted average cost of capital (WACC) of a company;  describe alternative methods of   calculating the weights used in the weighted average cost of capital, including the use of the company&#8217;s target capital structure  Because the target capital weights   are not given, you can use market value weights to compute the WACC. The market value weights for debt, preferred stock  and equity are   0.2667, 0.0667, and 0.6667 respectively.  WACC = wd x rd x (1 - t) + wp x rp   + we x re  = 0.2667 x 8% x (1 - 0.4) + 0.0667 x 10% + 0.6667 x 12% = 9.95%   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>73. A company's optimal capital budget is best described as the amount of new capital required to undertake all projects with an  internal rate of return greater than the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">marginal cost of capital. </choice>
		<choice id="B">cost of new debt capital. </choice>
		<choice id="C">cost of retained earnings. </choice>
		<choice id="D">weighted average cost of capital. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Cost of Capital,&#8221; Yves Courtois, GeneC. Lai, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 43-45  Study Session 11-45-d  explain how the marginal cost of capital and the investment opportunity schedule are used to determine the optimal capital  budget  The optimal capital budget is the amount of new capital required to undertake all investment projects with an IRR greater than  the marginal cost of capital.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>74. Waynesboro Industries is considering issuing a 10-year, option-free, semiannual coupon bond with a 9% coupon rate. The  bond is expected to sell at 95% of par value. If the company's marginal tax rate is 30%, then the after-tax cost of debt is  closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">6.30%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">6.86%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">9.00%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">9.80%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Cost of Capital,&#8221; Yves Courtois, GeneC. Lai, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I,   Vol. 4, pp. 45-47  Study Session 11-45-f  calculate and interpret the cost of fixed rate debt capital using the yield-to-maturity approach and the debt-rating   approach  Using a financial calculator: N = 20, PMT = 45, PV = 950, FV = 1000; solve for %I = 4.90%. The annual yield is twice the  semiannual yield = 4.90% x 2 = 9.80%.   The after-tax cost of debt = annual yield x (1 - t) = 9.80% x (1 - 0.30) = 6.86%   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>75. Staunton Manufacturing is considering issuing nonconvertible, noncallable fixed-rate perpetual preferred stock with a $6  annual dividend. The preferred stock is expected to sell for $40. If the company's marginal tax rate is 30%, then the after-tax  cost of preferred stock is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">4.50%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">6.67%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">10.5%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">15.0%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Cost of Capital,&#8221; Yves Courtois, GeneC. Lai, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 48-49  Study Session 11-45-g  calculate and interpret the cost of noncallable, nonconvertible preferred stock  The cost of a perpetuity is the annual cash flow divided by the selling price. In this case: rp = 6.00 / 40 = 15.0%. Because the  preferred stock dividend is not tax deductible to the issuing company, there is no after-tax adjustment.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>76. An analyst gathered the following information about Afton, Inc., and the market:  Current market price per share of common stock &#8364;32.00  Most recent dividend per share paid on common stock &#8364;2.40  Expected dividend payout rate 40%  Expected return on equity (ROE) 15%  Beta for the common stock 1.5  Expected return on the market portfolio 12%  Risk-free rate of return 4%  Using the dividend discount model approach, the cost of common equity is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">15.0%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">16.0%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">16.5%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">17.2%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Cost of Capital,&#8221; Yves Courtois, GeneC. Lai, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 54-55  Study Session 11-45-h  calculate and interpret the cost of equity capital using the capital asset pricing model approach, the dividend discount model  approach, and the bond-yield-plus risk-premium approach  According to the dividend discount model approach, the cost of common equity is equal to the dividend yield plus the growth  rate. In this case, the growth rate is the earnings retention rate times the expected ROE or (1 - dividend payout rate) x expected  ROE = 1 - 0.4) x 15% = 9%. The expected dividend = 2.40 x (1 + 0.09) = 2.616. The expected dividend yield = 2.616 / 32 =  8.175%. The cost of common equity = 8.175% + 9.0% ? 17.2%.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>77. The cash manager for Wicker Enterprises is investigating the purchase of a banker's acceptance (BA). The $1,000,000 face  value BA has 150 days to maturity and is quoted at 4.05% on a discount-basis yield. If Wicker's marginal tax rate is 25%,  then the money market yield on the BA is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">3.09%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">3.13%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">4.12%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">4.18%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Working Capital Management,&#8221; EdgarA. Norton, Jr., Kenneth L. Parkinson, and Pamela p. Peterson  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 101-102  Study Session 11-46-e  compute and interpret comparable yields on various securities, compare portfolio returns against a standard benchmark, and  evaluate a company&#8217;s short-term investment policy guidelines  Money market yield = discount-basis yield x (face value / purchase price)  Purchase price = face value - [face value x discount-basis yield x (days to maturity / 360)]  = $1,000,000 - [$1,000,000 x 0.0405 x (150 / 360)] = $983,125  Money market yield = 4.05% x ($1,000,000 / $983,125) = 4.12%   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>78. Regarding corporate governance, which of the following most likely would be a reason for concern when evaluating the  compensation committee? The compensation committee:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">has written policies and procedures. </choice>
		<choice id="B">includes members of executive management. </choice>
		<choice id="C">purchases shares on the open market to fund stock option commitments. </choice>
		<choice id="D">discloses information about compensation paid to executives and board members. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Corporate Governance of Listed Companies: A Manual for Investors&#8221; (CFA Institute, 2005)  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 173-175  Study Session 11-48-f  state the key areas of responsibility for which board committees are typically created, and explain the criteria for assessing  whether each committee is able to adequately represent shareowner interests  The compensation committee should be independent from executive management.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>79. Hari Raju, CEO of Securities Tracking Associates (STA), is thinking of devising a new index for the Indian stock market.  He does not, however, like an index that requires adjustment for stock splits. Given this preference, Raju would be least  likely to develop which of the following types of indexes?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Style Index </choice>
		<choice id="B">Un-weighted Index  </choice>
		<choice id="C">Price-weighted Index </choice>
		<choice id="D">Value-weighted Index </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Security-Market Indexes,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 42-46  Study Session 13-53-a  compare and contrast the characteristics of, and discuss the source and direction of bias exhibited by, each of the three  predominant weighting schemes used in constructing stock market indexes, and compute a price-weighted, value-weighted and  un-weighted index series for three stocks;  A price-weighted index, such as the Dow Jones Industrial Average, is computed by summing up the prices of individual stocks  and dividing by a divisor that is adjusted for stock splits such that the index value is the same before and after the split.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>80. Two industries, A and B, have the following values for N-firm concentration ratio and Herfindahl Index:  Industry 3-Firm Concentration Ratio Herfindahl Index  A 40% 0.095  B 75% 0.1938  Given this, which of the following statements is most accurate?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Industry A can be characterized as oligopolistic competition. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Firms in Industry A would have a greater coordination than firms in IndustryB. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Industry A has a larger number of equivalent firms than IndustryB. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Product differentiation strategy would be more appropriate for firms in Industry B than for firms in IndustryA. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Equity: Concepts and Techniques,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 138-139  Study Session 14-58-d, e   discuss the specific advantages of both the concentration ratio and the Herfindahl index;  discuss, with respect to global industry analysis, the elements related to risk, and describe the basic forces that determine  industry competition  The &#8220;equivalent&#8221; number of firms is the reciprocal of Herfindahl Index and it is 10.5 for Industry A and 5.2 for IndustryB.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>81. Chenchell's India Trading Co. (CITC), an importer-exporter of specialty goods and garments, has operations in Asia, Europe,  and North America. Marc Twinsing, CFA, a balanced fund manager, is considering adding CITC's stock to his portfolio and  he has compiled the following information:   CITC Industry Average  Weighted average cost of capital (WACC) 14% 12%  Return on Assets (ROA) 20% 15%  Dividend Yield 0% 1.2%  Consensus estimate of stock&#8217;s value $53 N/A  Current price of CITC&#8217;s stock $50 N/A  Based on his analysis Twinsing's most likely conclusions about the company and its stock, respectively, would be:    that CITC company is a: that CITC&#8217;s stock is a:  A growth company growth stock  B growth company speculative stock  C speculative company growth stock  D speculative company speculative stock  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A </choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Company Analysis and Stock Valuation,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 150-152  Study Session 14-59-a   differentiate between 1) a growth company and a growth stock, 2) a defensive company and a defensive stock, 3) a cyclical  company and a cyclical stock, 4) a speculative company and a speculative stock, and 5) a value stock and a growth stock  CITC is a growth company because its spread between ROA and WACC is larger than the industry average and its dividend  yield is 0% compared to the industry average of 1.2%. CITC&#8217;s stock is a growth stock considering its under-valuation. A  speculative stock, on the other hand, would be overvalued.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>82. Which of the following is the least accurate rationale to justify the use of price-to-book value (P/BV) ratio as a measure of  relative valuation of companies or common stocks?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">P/BV is helpful in valuing companies experiencing negative earnings per share. </choice>
		<choice id="B">P/BV is a useful measure of value for firms that are not expected to continue as a going concern. </choice>
		<choice id="C">P/BV correctly reflects a company's value as the book value is based on the historical purchase costs of assets. </choice>
		<choice id="D">P/BV is particularly appropriate to value companies primarily composed of liquid assets, for example, those in the  financial services industry. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Introduction to Price Multiples,&#8221; JohnD. Stowe, Thomas R. Robinson, Jerald E. Pinto, and Dennis W. McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 211-212  Study Session 14-61-a   discuss the rationales for, and the possible drawbacks to, the use of price to earnings (P/E), price to book value (P/BV), price  to sales (P/S), and price to cash flow (P/CF) in equity valuation  The historical cost basis of assets in P/B ratio is a drawback not a rationalization for using it as a measure of relative valuation.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>83. Metiu Metev, an analyst with Sofia Equity Researchers, has gathered the following information about Balkan Steel Mills  (BSM):   Current year&#8217;s operating free cash flow BGN 5  million  Cost of equity capital 15%  Weighted average cost of capital 12.4%  Estimated long-term growth rate 6%  Given this information, Metev's best estimate of BSM's intrinsic value (in BGN millions) would be closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">55.56 million. </choice>
		<choice id="B">58.89 million. </choice>
		<choice id="C">78.13 million. </choice>
		<choice id="D">82.81 million. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Security Valuation: Part II,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and Keith   C. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 180-181, 184  Study Session 14-60-b, f  calculate and interpret the value both of a preferred stock and a   common stock using the dividend discount model (DDM);  describe a process for developing estimated inputs to be used in the DDM, including the required rate of   return and expected growth rate of dividends  V = OFCF1 / (WACC - g) = 5 (1.06) / (0.124 - 0.06) =   82.81   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>84. Geo Telecommunications Inc. is a fast growing company with a double-digit growth rate that is expected to continue for  three more years. In his pursuit of valuing the company's stock, Dimiter Nenkov, a free-lance equity analyst, has compiled  the following data about the company:  Current year&#8217;s free cash flow to equity &#8364;20 million  30% in years 1 and 2    Growth rate in free cash flow during the next three years 20% in year 3  Growth rate in free cash flow for year 4 and beyond 8%  Weighted average cost of capital 12%  Cost of equity capital 15%  Number of outstanding shares 50 million  Based on the above information, Nenkov's best estimate of the value per share for Geo Telecommunications would be  closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">&#8364; 9.72. </choice>
		<choice id="B">&#8364; 10.13. </choice>
		<choice id="C">&#8364; 17.17. </choice>
		<choice id="D">&#8364; 17.57. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Security Valuation: Part II,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 182-185  &#8220;Understanding the Cash Flow Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn   2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 287-288   Study Session 14-60-b, f; 8-34-i  calculate and interpret the value both of a preferred stock and a common stock using the dividend discount model (DDM);  describe a process for developing estimated inputs to be used in the DDM, including the required rate of return and expected  growth rate of dividends; explain and calculate free cash flow to the firm, free cash flow to equity, and other cash flow ratios     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>85. Sarah Lawton, CFA, gathered the following information about Dalton Computers Inc:  Common stock $1.50 par value &#8211; Authorized 5,000,000 shares  Common stock $1.50 par value &#8211; Issued 4,000,000 shares  Additional paid-in-capital $20,000,000  Retained earnings $5,000,000  Treasury stock (500,000 shares) $10,000,000  Current price per share $21  The price-to-book value of Dalton Computers is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.3. </choice>
		<choice id="B">2.72. </choice>
		<choice id="C">3.5. </choice>
		<choice id="D">4.2. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Introduction to Price Multiples,&#8221; JohnD. Stowe, Thomas R. Robinson, Jerald E. Pinto, and Dennis W. McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 213-215  Study Session 14-61-b  calculate and interpret P/E, P/BV, P/S, and P/CF  BV per share = 4m shares (1.50) + $20 m + $5 m - $10 m = $21 m / 3.5 m sh. = $6.00  Price-to-book value = $21 / $6.00 = 3.50    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>86. In a country that is experiencing neoclassical growth with increasing savings rate, investors can expect which of the  following:    higher dividends? higher dividend growth?  A No No  B No Yes  C Yes No  D Yes Yes  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Equity: Concepts and Techniques,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 133-134  Study Session 14-58-a  classify business cycle stages and identify attractive investment opportunities for each stage  Neoclassical growth theory assumes that marginal productivity of capital declines as more capital is added. Thus, it predicts  that the long-term level of GDP depends on the country&#8217;s savings rate but not the long-term growth rate because of  diminishing marginal returns and reaching a steady state. This implies increase in dividends, as the new level of GDP is  reached, but not an increase in the dividend growth rate.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>87. Which of the following is the least likely characteristic of a call market? A call market is a:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">primary market. </choice>
		<choice id="B">secondary market. </choice>
		<choice id="C">market with participation by a small number of active investors-traders. </choice>
		<choice id="D">market in which buy-sell orders are cleared at a single equilibrium price. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Organizing and Functioning of Securities Markets,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 13-15  Study Session 14-52-b, c  distinguish between primary and secondary capital markets, and explain how secondary markets support primary markets;  distinguish between call and continuous market  A call market is an exchange (secondary market), not a primary market. Typically, it is characterized by a few listed stocks or  a small number of active investor-traders. Buy-sell orders are cleared at a single price (equilibrium price) that satisfies most of  the orders.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>88. In computing free cash flow to equity, adjustment is needed for payments made to which of the following capital providers?    Debt holders Preferred stockholders A No No  B No Yes  C Yes No  D Yes Yes  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A </choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Security Valuation: Part II,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 185   &#8220;Understanding the Cash Flow Statement,&#8221; Thomas R. Robinson, Hennie van Greuning, Elaine Henry, and MichaelA.  Broihahn  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 3, pp. 287-288   Study Sessions 14-60-f, 8-34-i  describe a process for developing estimated inputs to be used in the DDM, including the required rate of return and expected  growth rate of dividends;  explain and calculate free cash flow to the firm, free cash flow to equity, and other cash flow ratios  Free cash flow to equity is after subtracting payments to both debt holders and preferred stockholders.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>89. An equity investment in a producer firm would be more attractive at what levels of the bargaining power of buyers and  suppliers, respectively?    Bargaining power of buyers Bargaining power of suppliers  A Low Low  B Low High  C High Low  D High High  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Equity: Concepts and Techniques,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 143  Study Session 14-58-e   discuss, with respect to global industry analysis, the elements related to risk, and describe the basic forces that determine  industry competition  At high levels of the bargaining power of both buyers and suppliers, the producer would potentially experience a squeeze on  profits and profit margins. Therefore, equity investments in producer firms with low levels of bargaining power of both buyers  and sellers tend to be more attractive.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>90. The latest annual report of Waterford Crossing Inc. contains the following data:  Common stock $0.50 par value &#8211; Issued (2,000,000 shares) $1,000,000  Additional paid-in-capital $10,000,000  Retained earnings $4,000,000  Treasury stock (500,000 shares) $5,000,000  Current price per share $15  The company's ending inventories based on LIFO are valued at $500,000 and a footnote to financial statements reports  inventories valued using FIFO basis would be $600,000. The company's tax rate is 30%. The un-adjusted and adjusted  price-to-book values of Waterford Crossing, respectively, are closest to:    Unadjusted P/BV Adjusted P/BV  A $1.88 $1.81  B $1.88 $1.94  C $2.25 $2.10  D $2.25 $2.42  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A </choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Introduction to Price Multiples,&#8221; JohnD. Stowe, Thomas R. Robinson, Jerald E. Pinto, and Dennis W. McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 216-217  Study Session 14-61-b  calculate and interpret P/E, P/BV, P/S, and P/CF     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>91. A futures trader must deposit an additional amount of money into a margin account at the clearinghouse if the margin  account ending balance is below the:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">initial margin requirement. </choice>
		<choice id="B">variation margin requirement. </choice>
		<choice id="C">maintenance margin requirement. </choice>
		<choice id="D">amount of the loan borrowed from the clearinghouse. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Futures Markets and Contracts,&#8221; Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 55-57  Study Session 17-72-b  differentiate between margin in the securities markets and margin in the futures markets, and define initial margin,  maintenance margin, variation margin, and settlement price   Holders of futures positions must maintain account balances above the maintenance margin requirement.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>92. A futures trader goes long one futures contract at $450. The settlement price 1 day before expiration is $500. On expiration  day, the future is trading at $505. The least likely way the futures trader will lock in her profits on expiration is:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">take delivery of the underlying asset and pay $500 to the short. </choice>
		<choice id="B">close out the futures position by selling the futures contract at $505. </choice>
		<choice id="C">take delivery of the underlying asset and pay the expiration settlement price to the short. </choice>
		<choice id="D">cash settle the futures and receive the difference between $500 and the expiration settlement price. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Futures Markets and Contracts,&#8221; Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 60-62  Study Session 17-72-d  describe how a futures contract can be terminated by a close-out (i.e., offset) at expiration (or prior to expiration), delivery, an  equivalent cash settlement, or an exchange-for-physicals  To lock in profits, take delivery and pay short the settlement price of the previous day, not the expiration day.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>93. A description that will least likely be used to explain put-call parity is:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">the prices of calls and puts on an underlying asset must be consistent with each other to remove arbitrage opportunities. </choice>
		<choice id="B">a fiduciary call option strategy and a protective put option strategy for an underlying asset are equal in value. </choice>
		<choice id="C">a put is equivalent to a long call, a long position in the underlying asset, and a long position in the risk-free asset. </choice>
		<choice id="D">a call is equivalent to a long put, a long position in the underlying asset, and a short position in the risk-free asset. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Option Markets and Contracts,&#8221; Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 108-110  Study Session 17-73-j  explain put-call parity for European options, and relate put-call parity to arbitrage and the construction of synthetic options   The put requires a short position in the underlying rather than a long position.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>94. The effects on the price of a call option from an increase in volatility and an increase in interest rates are:    Increase in Volatility Increase in Interest Rates  A Decrease Increase  B Increase Increase  C Increase Decrease  D Increase No impact  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Option Markets and Contracts,&#8221; Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 115-116  Study Session 17-73-m  indicate the directional effect of an interest rate change or volatility change on an option&#8217;s price  When volatility increases, the price of options increase. When interest rates increase, call option prices increase.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>95. A market participant has a view regarding the potential movement of a stock. He sells a customized over-the-counter put  option on the stock when the stock is trading at $38. The put has an exercise price of $36 and the put seller receives $2.25 in  premium. The price of the stock is $35 at expiration. The profit or loss for the put seller at expiration is:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">($1.25). </choice>
		<choice id="B">$1.00. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$1.25. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$2.25. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risk Management Applications of Option Strategies,&#8221; Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 151-157  Study Session 17-75-a  determine the value at expiration, profit, maximum profit, maximum loss, breakeven underlying price at expiration, and  general shape of the graph of the strategies of buying and selling calls and puts, and indicate the market outlook of investors  using these strategies   Profit = max (0, -value of put at expiration + premium) = max (0, - (X - S) + premium) = -1 + 2.25 = $1.25   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>96. An investor purchases a stock at $60 and at the same time, sells a 3-month call on the stock. The short call has a strike price  of $65 and a premium of $3.60. The risk-free rate is 4%. The breakeven underlying stock price at expiration is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$55.85. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$56.40. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$60.80. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$61.40. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risk Management Applications of Option Strategies,&#8221; Don M. Chance  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 158-162  Study Session 17-75-b  determine the value at expiration, profit, maximum profit, maximum loss, breakeven underlying price at expiration, and  general shape of the graph of a covered call strategy and a protective put strategy, and explain the risk management application  of each strategy   A covered call breakeven price equals the price paid for the stock less the premium received for the call. Breakeven = (S - c) =  (60 - 3.60) = $56.40   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>97. If market interest rates rise, the price of a callable bond, compared to an otherwise identical option-free bond, will most  likely:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">increase by less than the option-free bond. </choice>
		<choice id="B">decrease by less than the option-free bond. </choice>
		<choice id="C">decrease by more than the option-free bond. </choice>
		<choice id="D">decrease by the same amount as the option-free bond. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated With Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 267  Study Session 15-63-c  explain how features of a bond (e.g., maturity, coupon, and embedded options) and the level of a bond&#8217;s yield affect the bond&#8217;s  interest rate risk  A callable bond&#8217;s value is equal to an option-free bond less the value of the call option. As interest rates rise, the value of the  call option decreases by a decreasing amount relative to the straight bond. The option-free bond also declines in value as  interest rates rise, but this is offset by the decline in the value of the call option. Therefore, the price of a callable bond  decreases by less than a comparable option-free bond.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>98. A U.S. investor who purchases an option-free bond with a 7% coupon rate, maturing in 20 years, and issued by a U.S.-based  company is most likely exposed to:   Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:   	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">sovereign risk and credit risk.  </choice>
		<choice id="B">event risk and interest rate risk.  </choice>
		<choice id="C">volatility risk and yield curve risk.  </choice>
		<choice id="D">interest risk and exchange-rate risk. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated With Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 264-285  Study Session 15-63-a  explain the risks associated with investing in bonds  The investor faces event risk in a corporate bond and interest rate risk in a long dated, fixed coupon rate bond.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>99. All else equal, an increase in expected yield volatility is most likely to result in an increase in the price of a(n):  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">putable bond. </choice>
		<choice id="B">callable bond. </choice>
		<choice id="C">option-free bond selling at a discount to par. </choice>
		<choice id="D">option-free bond selling at a premium to par. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated With Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, p. 284  Study Session 15-63-n  explain how yield volatility affects the price of a bond with an embedded option and how changes in volatility affect the value  of a callable bond and a putable bond  An increase in expected yield volatility increases the price of the embedded put option. The price of a putable bond will  increase because the price of the putable bond is equal to an option-free bond plus the put option.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>100. Compared with an otherwise identical amortizing security, a zero-coupon bond will most likely have:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">less interest rate risk and more reinvestment risk. </choice>
		<choice id="B">less reinvestment risk and more interest rate risk. </choice>
		<choice id="C">the same reinvestment risk and less interest rate risk. </choice>
		<choice id="D">the same interest rate risk and more reinvestment risk. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated With Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 266-270, 276-277  Study Session 15-63-c, i  explain how features of a bond (e.g., maturity, coupon, and embedded options) and the level of a bond&#8217;s yield affect the bond&#8217;s  interest rate risk;   identify the factors that affect the reinvestment risk of a security and explain why prepayable amortizing securities expose  investors to greater reinvestment risk than nonamortizing securities  An amortizing security receives periodic payments of both interest and principal that must be reinvested; therefore, it is  exposed to reinvestment risk. A zero-coupon bond has no reinvestment risk since no cash flows are received that must be  reinvested before maturity. Because zero-coupon bonds do not have periodic cash flows, they have the highest interest rate risk  for a given maturity and a given change in market yields.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>101. An analyst determined that if interest rates increase 120 basis points the price of a bond would be $89.70, but if interest  rates decrease 120 basis points the price of that bond would be $99.30. If the initial price of the bond is $95.40, the  approximate percentage price change for a 100 basis point change in yield is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">2.5%. </choice>
		<choice id="B">4.2%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">8.4%. </choice>
		<choice id="D">10.0%. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated With Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 269-271  Study Session 15-63-f  compute and interpret the duration and dollar duration of a bond  The formula for calculating the duration of a bond (estimated percentage price change for a 100 basis point change in yield) is:  Price if yields decline - price if yields increase / 2(initial price)(change in yield in decimal) = 99.3 - 89.7 / 2 (95.4)0.0120 =  4.19287.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>102. For an A- rated corporate bond that has deteriorating fundamentals, but is expected to remain investment grade, the  greatest risk is most likely:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">event risk. </choice>
		<choice id="B">default risk. </choice>
		<choice id="C">liquidity risk. </choice>
		<choice id="D">credit spread risk. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Risks Associated With Investing in Bonds,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 277-281  Study Session 15-63-j  describe the various forms of credit risk and describe the meaning and role of credit ratings  The bond is expected to see a widening of spreads as a result of deteriorating fundamentals and a potential  downgrade but still remaining investment grade.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>103.  Fred Perry, CFA, purchased $100,000 of a newly issued Treasury inflation protection security based on the following  characteristics and information.   Issuance Date: January 1, 2008  Issuance Price: $1,000  Maturity: 10 years  Auction set real rate: 2.00%  Interest payable: Annually  CPI-U (Applicable Inflation Index): 5.00% (annual rate)  The coupon payment at the end of one year is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$2,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$2,100. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$5,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$7,000. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Overview of Bond Sectors and Instruments,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 299-301  Study Session 15-64-b  describe the types of securities issued by the U.S. Department of the Treasury (e.g., bills, notes, bonds, and inflation protection  securities), and differentiate between on-the-run and off-the-run Treasury securities  First adjust the principal by inflation = $100,000 x 1.05 = $105,000. Then multiply the adjusted principal by the real rate =  $105,000 x 0.02 = $2,100.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>104.  A portfolio manager is considering investing a portion of her fixed income portfolio in a security whose cash flows are  dependent on an underlying pool of mortgages. The portfolio consists of Treasury bonds, corporate bonds and Ginnie Mae  passthroughs. The security being considered is Tranche B of a collateralized mortgage obligation (CMO). The underlying  collateral is a Ginnie Mae passthrough security. The rules of the CMO state that Tranche A is the first to receive monthly  principal. By investing in Tranche B of the CMO, the portfolio manager will most likely reduce portfolio:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">credit risk. </choice>
		<choice id="B">inflation risk </choice>
		<choice id="C">sovereign risk. </choice>
		<choice id="D">prepayment risk. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Overview of Bond Sectors and Instruments,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 308-312  Study Session 15-64-f  state the motivation for creating a collateralized mortgage obligation  Adding Tranche B of the CMO to the portfolio will most likely reduce prepayment. A passthrough security, such as a Ginnie  Mae, can be prepaid as the underlying loans pay off principal, i.e., they are exposed to prepayment risk. On the other hand, the  tranches in a CMO will be paid off sequentially, i.e., Tranche A then TrancheB. Tranche B has less prepayment risk than the  underlying passthrough securities.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>105. Hub Global, Inc. has issued two classes of debt securities to finance its operations, a first mortgage bond and debenture  bonds. All else equal, will the default and recovery rates of the debenture likely be higher than the first mortgage bond?    Default rate? Recovery rate?  A No No  B No Yes  C Yes No  D Yes Yes  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Overview of Bond Sectors and Instruments,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 318-321  Study Session 15-64-h  describe the characteristics and motivation for the various types of debt issued by corporations (including corporate bonds,  medium-term notes, structured notes, commercial paper, negotiable CDs, and bankers acceptances)  Default rates apply to the issuer and would be equal for any security issued by that issuer while the recovery of the unsecured  debenture is lower than for the first mortgage bond which is secured.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>106. Which of the statements is least accurate?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Central banks need to ensure that they follow markets rather than guide them. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Central banks can obtain an assessment of expected interest rates from bond markets. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Goods and labor markets provide central banks with information about risks to price stability. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Central banks should clearly communicate their strategies with financial markets and avoid surprises. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Monetary Policy in an Environment of Global Financial Markets,&#8221; Otmar Issing  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5 pp. 379-383  Study Session 15-66-a, b  identify how central bank behavior affects short-term interest rates, systemic liquidity, and market expectations, thereby  affecting financial markets;   describe the importance of communication between a central bank and the financial markets  Central banks should guide markets and not follow them. The reason for this is that financial markets are susceptible to  speculative bubbles that stray from fundamentals. Central bankers must keep their eyes on fundamentals.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>107. An analyst has gathered the following information provided in the table below:  Period Years Treasury Spot Rate (%) Credit Spread (%)  1 1 3.00 0.20  2 2 3.50 0.30  3 3 4.00 0.40  4 4 4.50 0.50  5 5 5.00 0.60  Based on the information provided in the table, the current market price of a $1,000 par value, option-free, 0% coupon  corporate bond maturing in 5 years is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$758.70. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$781.20. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$804.44. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$853.20. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Introduction to the Valuation of Debt Securities,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 398-399, 410-412  Study Session 15-67-e  compute the value of a zero-coupon bond  Interest rate is 5.6% = 5% + 0.6%. The semiannual interest rate is 2.8%. The price of the bond, using semiannual discounting  is:     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>108. An 8% coupon option-free bond maturing in 12 years is currently trading at a premium. Assuming market rates remain  stable, over a period of 5 years, the value of the bond will most likely:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Increase. </choice>
		<choice id="B">Decrease. </choice>
		<choice id="C">Remain constant. </choice>
		<choice id="D">Increase or decrease depending on changes in volatility. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Introduction to the Valuation of Debt Securities,&#8221; Frank J. Fabozzi  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 5, pp. 392-395  Study Session 15-67-d  explain how the price of a bond changes as the bond approaches its maturity date, and compute the change in value that is  attributable to the passage of time  The bond&#8217;s price should move downward toward par as time passes given that it trades at a premium and market rates are  unchanged.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>109. Which real estate valuation approach is most likely to use slope coefficients derived from a statistical analysis to estimate  the value of a property?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Cost approach </choice>
		<choice id="B">Income approach </choice>
		<choice id="C">Sales comparison approach </choice>
		<choice id="D">Discounted after-tax cash flow approach </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 191-192  Study Session 18-76-e  describe the various approaches to the valuation of real estate  One variation of the sales comparison approach (hedonic price estimation) uses recent transactions in the area to derive an  equation that weights various property attributes to determine a value for the property.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>110. Assume U.S. GAAP (generally accepted accounting principles) applies unless otherwise noted.  An investor has gathered the following data, presented on an annual basis, for an apartment complex that is being  considered for purchase:  Gross potential rental income $180,000  Insurance and taxes $15,000  Utilities $10,000  Repairs and maintenance $18,000  Depreciation $21,000  Interest on proposed financing $16,000  The annual net operating income (NOI) for the apartment complex is closest to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">$100,000. </choice>
		<choice id="B">$116,000. </choice>
		<choice id="C">$121,000. </choice>
		<choice id="D">$137,000. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>D</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 193-194  Study Session 18-76-f  calculate the net operating income (NOI) from a real estate investment, the value of a property using the sales comparison and  income approaches, and the after-tax cash flows, net present value, and yield of a real estate investment  NOI = $180,000 - $15,000 - $10,000 - $18,000 = $137,000    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>111. An investor would most likely expect commodities to have correlations with traditional stock or bond investments and  inflation that are:    Correlation with traditional  stock or bond investments  Correlation with inflation  A Positive Positive  B Positive Negative  C Negative Positive  D Negative Negative  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 227-228  Study Session 18-76-q  explain the motivation for investing in commodities, commodity derivatives, and commodity-linked securities   A primary motivation for an investment in commodities, commodity derivatives, commodity-linked bonds, and  commodity-linked equity are the diversification benefits provided due to the negative return correlation with other assets and  the positive correlation with inflation.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>112. Hedge funds that contain infrequently traded assets would most likely exhibit a downward bias with respect to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">measured risk but not correlations with conventional equity investments. </choice>
		<choice id="B">correlations with conventional equity investments but not measured risk. </choice>
		<choice id="C">both measured risk and correlations with conventional equity investments. </choice>
		<choice id="D">neither measured risk nor correlations with conventional equity investments. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 220-222  Study Session 18-76-l  discuss the performance of hedge funds, the biases present in hedge fund performance measurement, and explain the effect of  survivorship bias on the reported return and risk measures for a hedge fund database   The presence of infrequently traded assets leads to smoothed pricing that induces a significant downward bias to the measured  risk of the assets as well as the correlations of returns with conventional equity and fixed income returns.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>113. Venture capital investments used to provide capital for companies initiating commercial manufacturing and sales are most  likely to be considered a form of:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">first-stage financing. </choice>
		<choice id="B">mezzanine financing. </choice>
		<choice id="C">second-stage financing. </choice>
		<choice id="D">expansion-stage financing. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 220-222  Study Session 18-76-g  explain the stages in venture capital investing, venture capital investment characteristics and challenges to venture capital  valuation and performance measurement  Venture capital investments provided to initiate commercial manufacturing and sales is considered a form of first-stage  financing.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>114. Which classification of hedge funds is least likely to use a short position in stock as a part of its strategy?  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Market-neutral funds </choice>
		<choice id="B">Emerging-market funds </choice>
		<choice id="C">Distressed securities funds </choice>
		<choice id="D">Risk arbitrage in mergers and acquisitions </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>B</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;Alternative Investments,&#8221; Bruno Solnik and Dennis McLeavey  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 6, pp. 211-213  Study Session 18-76-i  discuss the descriptive accuracy of the term &#8220;hedge fund,&#8221; define hedge fund in terms of objectives, legal structure, and fee  structure, and describe the various classifications of hedge funds   Emerging-market funds invest in less liquid and less efficient assets of emerging markets that are difficult to short.    </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>115. Which of the following constraints would most likely appear in the unique needs and preferences section of a trust's  investment policy statement? The portfolio is:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">subject to the prudent-man standard. </choice>
		<choice id="B">subject to income taxes of 40%. </choice>
		<choice id="C">prohibited from investing in tobacco companies. </choice>
		<choice id="D">prohibited from holding less than 5% in cash instruments. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Asset Allocation Decision,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 210-216  Study Session 12-49-d  describe the investment constraints of liquidity, time horizon, tax concerns, legal and regulatory factors, and unique needs and  preferences  Unique needs and preferences include the prohibition of certain investments. The investment constraints of liquidity, tax  concerns, and legal and regulatory factors adequately address the portfolio&#8217;s other constraints.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>116. The final step in the portfolio management process is most likely to include:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">investment research. </choice>
		<choice id="B">portfolio construction. </choice>
		<choice id="C">evaluation of portfolio performance. </choice>
		<choice id="D">evaluation of investor's investment knowledge. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Asset Allocation Decision,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 202-203  Study Session 12-49-a  describe the steps in the portfolio management process, and explain the reasons for a policy statement  The final step in the portfolio management process includes evaluating portfolio performance. Evaluation of investor&#8217;s  investment knowledge, investment research, and portfolio construction are part of the first three steps in the process.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>117. The second step of the portfolio management process is least likely to include examining:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">historical trends. </choice>
		<choice id="B">current social conditions. </choice>
		<choice id="C">projected financial forecasts. </choice>
		<choice id="D">current and projected political conditions. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>A</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Asset Allocation Decision,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 202-203  Study Session 12-49-a  describe the steps in the portfolio management process, and explain the reasons for a policy statement  The second step in the portfolio management process includes examining current and projected financial, economic, political,  and social conditions. Historical trends may be educational, but the focus of the second phase is determining the short-term  and intermediate-term expected conditions to use in constructing a specific portfolio.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>118. Over time, the major source of investment return and risk is most likely attributed to:  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">market timing. </choice>
		<choice id="B">stockSelection. </choice>
		<choice id="C">asset allocation. </choice>
		<choice id="D">risk management. </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Asset Allocation Decision,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 218-220  Study Session 12-49-e  describe the importance of asset allocation, in terms of the percentage of a portfolio&#8217;s return that can be explained by the target  asset allocation, and explain how political and economic factors result in differing asset allocations by investors in various  countries  The asset allocation decision explains about 90% of a fund&#8217;s returns over time. Across all funds, asset allocation explains an  average of 40% of the variation in fund returns, and slightly more than 100% of the average fund&#8217;s level of return.   </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>119. When compared to investors living in a country with high inflation, investors living in a country with generous state  pensions will most likely have allocations to equities and fixed income investments, respectively, that are:    Equities Fixed Income  A Lower Lower  B Lower Higher  C Higher Lower  D Higher Higher  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;The Asset Allocation Decision,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008 Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 223-224  Study Session 12-49-e  describe the importance of asset allocation, in terms of the percentage of a portfolio&#8217;s return that can be explained by the target  asset allocation, and explain how political and economic factors result in differing asset allocations by investors in various  countries  The need to invest for portfolio growth is higher in inflationary environments and lower in countries where workers receive  generous state pensions.     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem> 

<problem>
	<question>120. An analyst gathered the following information about a portfolio comprised of two assets:  Asse t  Wei ght%  Expected Return  E(R)  Expected Standard Deviation  E(?)  X 60 11% 5%  Y 40 7% 4%  If the covariance of returns for the two assets equals 0.75, then the expected return and expected standard deviation of the  portfolio are closest to:    Expected Return Expected  Standard Deviation A 8.6% 4.3%  B 8.6% 18.7%  C 9.4% 4.3%  D 9.4% 18.7%  Select exactly 1 answer(s) from the following:  	</question>
	<choices>
		<choice id="A">Answer A</choice>
		<choice id="B">Answer B </choice>
		<choice id="C">Answer C </choice>
		<choice id="D">Answer D </choice>
	</choices>
	<answer>C</answer>
	<comments>&#8220;An Introduction to Portfolio Management,&#8221; Frank K. Reilly and KeithC. Brown  2008   Modular Level I, Vol. 4, pp. 230-245  Study Session 12-50-c  compute and interpret the expected return, variance, and standard deviation for an individual   investment and the expected return and standard deviation for a portfolio  The expected return of the portfolio is the weighted average return of the two   assets = 0.60 x 11 + 0.40 x 7 = 9.4%.  The expected standard deviation of the portfolio is calculated as:      = [(0.602 x 0.052) + (0.402 x 0.042) + (2 x 0.60 x 0.40 x 0.75 x 0.05 x 0.04)]0.5  = [0.0009 + 0.000256 + 0.00072]0.5  = [0.001876]0.5 = 0.0433 ? 4.3%     </comments>
<year filename="2008_part_2.xml">2008</year></problem>
</problems>